<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Olivaires of Castile and Arthur of Dalgarve translated out of Spanish into the Italian tongue by Francesco Portonari, and from the Italian made English by Mark Micklethwait ...</title>
            <title>Olivier de Castille (Romance). English. Micklethwait.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 133 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2128A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42745</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875690</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875690</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2290:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Olivaires of Castile and Arthur of Dalgarve translated out of Spanish into the Italian tongue by Francesco Portonari, and from the Italian made English by Mark Micklethwait ...</title>
                  <title>Olivier de Castille (Romance). English. Micklethwait.</title>
                  <author>Micklethwait, Mark.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 254 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. and J. Churchill, and Fra. Hildyard Bookseller in York,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCV [1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1]</note>
                  <note>"Licens'd, Feb. 1. 1693/4."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:1"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>ITal. Song <hi>line</hi> 10. <hi>read</hi> periglioſo. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> pauroſo. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> potè Sforzò. <hi>page</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> brothers <hi>and</hi> companions. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> at T. <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> to her reſt. <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> oft. <hi>p.</hi> 44. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>for</hi> was, <hi>r.</hi> is. <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>after</hi> you <hi>put, l.</hi> 10. <hi>after</hi> Nobility <hi>put a full point. p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>del.</hi> to. <hi>p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>r.</hi> publiſh'd. <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> comforted. <hi>p.</hi> 83. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>for</hi> covered, <hi>r.</hi> carved. <hi>p.</hi> 96. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> their. <hi>p.</hi> 99. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> Trumpets. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Armour. <hi>del.; p.</hi> 100. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> bath'd. <hi>p.</hi> 112. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>after</hi> faſhion <hi>put, p.</hi> 118. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> Kings. <hi>p.</hi> 124. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> had happy. <hi>p.</hi> 128. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> Kings. <hi>p.</hi> 130. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>for</hi> Son, <hi>r.</hi> Sun. <hi>p.</hi> 135. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> ſo to. <hi>p.</hi> 140. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>after</hi> Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>put, and after</hi> Votes <hi>put a full point. p.</hi> 148. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> he, <hi>r.</hi> they. <hi>p.</hi> 154. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> Sharp, <hi>r.</hi> Smart. <hi>p.</hi> 155. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>del.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>and. p.</hi> 158. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> and gave. <hi>p.</hi> 161. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> in the mean. <hi>p.</hi> 171. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> riſ. <hi>p.</hi> 173. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> and. <hi>p.</hi> 179. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> him to. <hi>p.</hi> 180. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>del.; p.</hi> 190. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> land <hi>put a full point. p.</hi> 195. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> would, <hi>r.</hi> will. <hi>p.</hi> 209. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>aftér</hi> weeping <hi>del.; p.</hi> 209. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>del.</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. <hi>p.</hi> 213. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>del.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. <hi>have p.</hi> 216. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF OLIVAIRES of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> AND ARTHUR of <hi>Dalgarve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>into the</hi> Italian <hi>Tongue, by</hi> Franceſco Portonari: <hi>And from the</hi> Italian <hi>made</hi> Engliſh.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Mark Micklethwait,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>LICENS'D, <hi>Feb.</hi> 1. 1694/5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>I. Churchill,</hi> and <hi>Fra. Hildyard</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>York.</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER OF Franceſco Portonari, Relating to the Enſuing BOOK.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the moſt Noble Lord <hi>S. Odoardo Gomez,</hi> my ever Honoured Lord.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MANY years ago two Writers, ſearching into Ancient Hiſtories, made choice of two Noble Cavaliers, and their Deeds, on that Subject, to compoſe a ſmall Manual. Some time after which a Chronicler of <hi>France,</hi> for the ſatisfaction of a Friend (who begged of him that he would give him to read ſome War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:152282:3"/>Exploits, and Amorous Intrigues and Adventures) tranſlated this Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Olivaires</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> of <hi>Dalgarve,</hi> from the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <hi>Latine</hi> into his own Native Language the <hi>French:</hi> And as all better Writ Books are wont, it generally took: Wherefore diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all over, it got alſo into <hi>Spain,</hi> and was received as a Choice and Delicate Novel. So from the <hi>French</hi> Tongue it was taught to ſpeak the <hi>Caſtilian,</hi> and that moſt elegantly; and there ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd withal additional Bulk, by many new, fine, and curious things inſerted. And for as much as we who breathe <hi>Italian</hi> Air, have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſuck'd in from our Infancy a natural inclination to ſuch ſort of ſmooth and ſhining Compoſures of
<pb facs="tcp:152282:3"/>whatever Climate; I did, for the pleaſure of thoſe who are moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with them, undertake the Task to turn this into the Stile of <hi>Tuſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> And with the light of ſuch kind Stars I writ, that, by reaſon of an Ancient Original of a Third Edition which came, though with difficulty, to my hands, I had opportunity of a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row view, whence ſuch Adventures, and Exploits, and Amours, were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and well enough diſcern'd, how thoſe Excellent Writers had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated the beſt and faireſt of the Hiſtory. From that Old Story then, from the <hi>Latine,</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> I alſo have deduced, and compiled, and ſo methodiz'd this Work, that it appears to me (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flattering my ſelf, or it) to equal, if not excel all the other. Wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:152282:4"/>knowing Your Lordſhip has oft read over the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Original of Mine, I the willinger preſent this to Your view, which has more of the Truth, according to the Relation of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and leſs of the Additional Lyes and Fictions that Tranſcribers have mix'd therewith. I ſhall be highly proud if Your Lordſhip's Incomparable Judgment can give Approbation to what I have done; and my Self, and Service, do I intirely dedicate to Your Lordſhip's Acceptance and Favour.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Venice, <date>March <hi>3. 1552.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhip's moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly devoted Servant,</hi>
Franceſco Portonari.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:4"/>
            <head>SONETTO DI BOSCAN, <hi>In Lingua</hi> Spagnola.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PAſſando el mar Leandro è l'ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſo</l>
               <l>An amoroſo fuego todo ardiendo</l>
               <l>Esforço el viento y fueſſe embrave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendo</l>
               <l>El aqua, con un impetu furioſo</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vencido del trabaio preſuroſo</l>
               <l>Contraſtar à las ondas no pudiendo</l>
               <l>Y mas del bieu que alli perdia mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riendo,</l>
               <l>Che de la propria vida pauroſo</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Como pudo Esforço ſu boz couſada</l>
               <l>Valas oudas ablo deſta manera</l>
               <l>Mas nunca fue ſu boz dellas oyda</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ondas pues no ſe eſcuſa que yo muera</l>
               <l>Dexadme allallegar y alla fornada</l>
               <l>Vueſtro furor executa eu mi vida.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:5"/>
            <head>SONETTO DI BOSCAN, <hi>Tradotto in Lingua</hi> Toſcana.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PAſſando il mar Leandro corrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſo</l>
               <l>In amoroſo fuoco tutto ardendo</l>
               <l>Fe forza al vento, &amp; ſe n'ando rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendo</l>
               <l>Quell'onde con uno impetu orgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glioſo:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ma vinto dal travaglio penglioſo,</l>
               <l>A l'acqua contraſtar piu non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo:</l>
               <l>Et piu del ben, ch'iui perdea mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo,</l>
               <l>Che de la propria vita panroſo;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come potesforzo ſua voce irata:</l>
               <l>Et con l'acque parlò di tal maniera;</l>
               <l>Ne mai da lor fu ſua favella udita:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Acque, poi non ſi puo farch'io non pera,</l>
               <l>Laſciatemi arrivar, è à la tornata</l>
               <l>Voſtro furor s'appaghe di mia vita.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen the Gallant <hi>Leander</hi> Swam the Main;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Waters cou'd not cool his ardent Love;</l>
               <l>He made the Winds to ſpend their ſpight in vain,</l>
               <l>And curling Waves did bravely from him ſhove.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when at length it him had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd now,</l>
               <l>Who cou'd not with its fury further ſtrife</l>
               <l>Maintain, for that he muſt his bliſs forgo;</l>
               <l>He much more grieved than for loſs of Life.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Then the deſpairing Lover ſilence brake,</l>
               <l>And to the Billows thus did parly make;</l>
               <l>Nor was e're after by them heard to ſpeak.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You Waters ſince I ſee I periſh muſt,</l>
               <l>Only give leave t' Embrace my Miſtreſs Firſt,</l>
               <l>And at return againſt me do your worſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152282:6"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF THE Noble CAVALIERS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Birth of</hi> Olivaires, <hi>and of the Death of his Mother.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ACcording as my Abilities will permit, and as an Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on natural unto me for high and noble Deeds of Great and Valorous Knights, whom Fame deſervedly tranſmits to far Poſterity, ſhall give us Aſſiſtance, my purpoſe is to make a Relation of uncommon and marvellous Exploits; to the end that by hearing ſuch honourable Feats
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152282:7"/>done of others, brave Souls may the eagerlier be incited to an impetuous thirſt after the acquiſt of Glory; and ſtill the more ſo, when particularly they take for their Mirrour and Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern the Two Valiant Brothers, for Arms ſo famous; from whom our preſent Story has its origin, and by the favour of him, upon whom all Conduct depends, ſhall have its ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful period.</p>
               <p>I am informed by Hiſtory, That after the Valiant Emperour <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> returned from <hi>Spain</hi> into his own Kingdom, within a ſhort while Heaven put an end to his days; at which time a Prince rul'd in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> who for his excellent Virtues, and winning Behaviour, both of his Nobles and Commonalty was much Beloved and Rever'd. He Married the King of <hi>Galitia</hi>'s Daughter, a Virtuous and Beautiful Lady. But having no Iſſue by her, this made her very Melancholy; and the whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152282:7"/>Kingdom was much Diſcontented, ſeeing one Realm remain deſtitute of an Heir, and other deprived of their Lawful Sovereign; which muſt needs in time produce many Troubles, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, and Wars. The Queen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hearing oft of theſe things, and by ſome words which fell from the King, perceiving that he was much diſſatisfi'd, made her Application by Prayer unto God, who never fails thoſe who rightly put confidence in him: And beginning with Alms, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing of Orphan Maids, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Slaves, and other good Chriſtian offices; ſhe implor'd Mercy and Favour of our Lord, and his Virgin Mother in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating them to grant her a Son, for the preſervation of the Kingdom. And for that her requeſt was equitable, and her Prayers iſſued from a ſincere heart, it pleaſed God in pity to hear their Cry; and ſhe conceived and brought forth a moſt beautiful Boy; which cauſed great Exultation, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and Feſtivity throughout the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152282:8"/>whole Kingdom. But ſhe had not lived four days, when 'twas the Will of the Almighty that ſhe ſhould ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up her devout Soul unto him that gave it; which cauſed a Lamentation as general, as had been the Joy. But the King was the principal Mourner; who bore an extream affection to her, knowing ſo well her Beauty, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Chaſtity, Compaſſionateneſs unto men, Piety towards God, and how in all things to his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhe was conform and agreeable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Baptiſm of</hi> Olivaires, <hi>and the Obſequies of the Queen his Mother; and ſome procedures toward the King's Marrying again for the Kingdoms Welfare.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter all things were prepared for the Funeral, they carried the deceaſed Queen to her Burial; and it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152282:8"/>was ordered that her Child ſhould at the ſame time be brought to his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; ſo both were in the Church to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The Queen was lamented with floods of Tears, and the young Infant was Baptized with fitting So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, and to him they gave the Name of <hi>Olivaires.</hi> As ſoon as the Funeral and Baptiſm were over, the King returned to his Palace, and every one to their own homes. This ſo ſudden Death cauſed the King ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely to lament; and ſo infinite was his ſorrow, that his Life begun to be much deſpaired of. Wherefore his Nobles uſed all endeavours to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his Melancholy by whatever they conceived might be moſt likely to give him any pleaſing Entertainment: And for this end, among others, they brought unto him his little Son <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res;</hi> whom taking and Embracing in his Arms, with heavy Sighs he mixed theſe Words, bearing a kind of delight even in their dolorouſneſs; O my lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152282:9"/>Son! all my remaining Comfort, and the Crown of my Kingdom; thy Birth hath raiſed me to Heaven, and ſunk me to Hell; for by giving me an Heir, it has lifted me up on high; but by robbing me of my Queen, it has caſt me down as low again. And addreſſing himſelf unto God, he beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of him that he would aſſume into Heaven the Mother's happy Soul: And on the little Babe (looking in his Face, ſaid he) may it pleaſe him to beſtow ſuch Grace, that thou mayeſt live in conſtant Obedience to all his Holy Commandments. After this manner the Afflicted King ſpent his time day by day, and would receive no Conſolation. Therefore the chief Lords of his Court ſeeing his Griefs rather increaſe than abate, met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in private to conſult which might be the beſt means to bring their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign out of his heavy Melancholy; for that if he perſiſted in this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he muſt of neceſſity very ſhortly put an end to his days, which would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152282:9"/>prove a grand publick detriment; and therefore they concluded on what would be every way better than that he ſhould do ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> the Matching him with Queen <hi>Dalgarve, Dowager;</hi> agreeable enough for years, Fair and of good and gentle Diſpoſition; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he were ſo inclin'd, it might turn to good effect: So they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to make the Propoſal to him. Coming then into his preſence, and having firſt paid thoſe reſpects due to Sovereignty, they communicated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the iſſue of their Conſultation, ſhewing him what good would follow, and how much to their own, and the general ſatisfaction and advantage his Marrying would be; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſplayed before him the excellent Qualities, and rare Virtues of Queen <hi>Dalgarve;</hi> ſo that this Match (as was ſaid before) would be fortunate and happy for himſelf, content to them, and cauſe the publick rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the whole Kingdom. The King giving ear to them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152282:10"/>a little in ſuſpence, and conſidering withal the reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the thing, and that it was his Subjects Affection to him that urged them ſo to ſpeak, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns them anſwer after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. My own Temper and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for certain is not to marry any more, nor ever to know Woman again. Notwithſtanding, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you, that ſince in what you move, you ſeek the publick welfare, and yours, and mine, and do ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and affectionately requeſt this of me, I am willing to forſake the Path I had with reſolution made choice of, and follow the duct of your Deſires and Counſels, and yield unto you to pitch upon what will be for the beſt, and may tend to your happineſs, the Kingdom's, and my own. When the Lords ſaw ſuch generoſity in their Prince, and had received ſo gracious an Anſwer from him, they were much pleaſed, and gave him infinite Thanks for ſuch Goodneſs. And now Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152282:10"/>Ambaſſadors were quickly diſpatch'd away to make their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, to Queen <hi>Dalgarve,</hi> who upon their Arrival were entertain'd with great kindneſs and reſpect, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Occaſion of their Embaſſy was not at all known. The next day they made their Aſcent into her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, where they delivered unto her the Mind and Inclinations of their King: And their Diſcourſe did not offend her Majeſty's Ear, and ſo by her Courtiers were honourably accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied to their Apartments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Treaty about the Marriage of Queen</hi> Dalgarve <hi>to the King of</hi> Caſtile.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Day following, about Three, the Queen ſent to convene all the Grandees, Sages, and moſt Noble Barons of her Kingdom, with whom ſhe diſcourſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152282:11"/>the King of <hi>Caſtile</hi>'s mind. And as for her Anſwer, and the whole Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, ſhe referr'd it to them, yielding up her ſelf intirely to what they ſhould adviſe, and to their diſpoſal: That whether they thought it fit ſhe ſhould marry or no, ſhe would wholly be at their devoire, and moſt willingly comply with their Reſolutions. The matter being diſcuſs'd, they deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd (to ſpeak in ſhort) that ſhe ſhould not reject the motion; telling her, That ſhe could not match into a nobler or better State, and that her Son <hi>Arthur</hi> was too young for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Thus they counſell'd her to accept of the King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> for her Husband. To which ſhe repli'd; I told you before, and now repeat it, That your pleaſure ſhall be mine. And therefore to you I leave it to form an Anſwer to the Ambaſſadors, in what manner you ſhall beſt approve of. After then they had returned the Queen thanks, Six Barons were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to go and inform the King's
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152282:11"/>Ambaſſadors their Pleaſure, and that it was alſo their Queen's, who had Authoriz'd them ſo to ſay; and theſe alſo told them, That they queſtioned not, but from ſuch an Auſpicious Conjunction, happy Effects, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal good Influences and Advantages would proceed: So the Affinity was leſt to the Liberty of the King of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile;</hi> for his Propoſal ſhe was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together averſe from. Go then, and tell your Maſter to order the Marriage as ſhall pleaſe him; and in this Point we only requeſt one Favour of him, That he would pleaſe to come himſelf for her (ſince all the Coaſts are clear and ſafe) for this will look more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and come alſo with as little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and Pomp, as an Affair of that kind and quality may poſſibly allow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152282:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Eſpouſals of the King of</hi> Caſtile, <hi>and Queen</hi> Dalgarve, <hi>and how he conducted her into his Kingdom, with her little Son</hi> Arthur.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Ambaſſadors having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd their Buſineſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived noble Preſents from the Queen and Court, returned back to their own Country, where the King with great impatience was expecting them, and Anſwer: Who having heard it, and how ſhe was inclin'd, prepared for his Journey; and gave his Courtiers a Month's ſpace for fitting themſelves to attend him: And when that was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, he, with his Court, departed, and in a little time finiſhed their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and upon their arrival were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with great civility and reſpect, and then they ordered all things for the Marriage, which with great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch was nobly conſummated. So
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152282:12"/>they paſſed many days in feaſting, and then prepared for a departure. The King could never have his Eye off <hi>Arthur,</hi> who bore ſo extream reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to his Son <hi>Olivaires,</hi> that many were miſtaken in thinking him the ſame. After the Feaſting was over, the King appointed his Deputy, to whom he committed the care of the Kingdom; and within few days re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with the Queen to his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, with her little Son <hi>Arthur,</hi> who was equally loved and careſſed as <hi>Olivaires.</hi> Now when they were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the Kingdom, and come to the City of their Reſidence, the Feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were renewed with all expreſſions of Joy and Merriment; and the two young Sons immediately contracted extream affection and kindneſs one for the other, and were never aſunder; who were ſo perfectly alike, that not any difference could be perceived, as we ſhall find in the ſequel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152282:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>and</hi> Arthur <hi>were taught the Art of, and exerciſed in Arms, by a Valiant Cavalier, and had noble Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Education.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Olivaires</hi> and <hi>Arthur</hi> were come to years (which they arrived at ſooner than ordinary) that fitted them to bear Arms, they were by the King committed to the Education and management of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Valorous Knight, who inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in Virtue, and exerciſed them in Arms: So that as they advanced in ſtature, their love likewiſe to each other increaſed, and, as much as was poſſible, every way grew greater; inſomuch, that, beſides the tye of Alliance, they enter'd into an Obligation, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Death (if even that had a power to do it) ſhould ſeparate their Affection and Friendſhip: The ſight of which mutual kindneſs betwixt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152282:13"/>them cauſed wonderful ſatisfaction and joy in the Breaſts of the King and Queen, and of the whole Court, eſpecially as they beheld them dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in accompliſhing themſelves in every laudable Acquirement. Nor did any ſhine with any ſort of Vertues and Excellencies, whoſe luſtre they did not tranſmit on themſelves by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if not improve to a greater ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, by exceeding and out-acting thoſe whom firſt they made their Examples: Whether theſe were intellectual or moral Indowments; or Feats of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of Body, as the playing of Tennis, Dancing, Juſting, Throwing the Bar, Wreſtling, and ſuch like Exerciſes; in which they never came behind any, but often outſtript others. The King and Queen having obſerved, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well aſſured of their Valour and Stoutheartedneſs, as well as Skill at Arms, had a mind to appoint a publick Turnament, and try them thereat, though but Youths: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they proclaimed a Feaſt, unto
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152282:14"/>which, at the day aſſigned, repaired many Knights and Barons from divers places, all of honourable Repute, and famous for Chivalry; many Scaffolds and Balconies were made about the Piazza, and Seats for the Judges well ſcituated for fair view, that they might juſtly beſtow the Prize: In Eminent Stations were alſo made Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphal Seats for the King and Queen: And now the appointed day being come, they took their Places, as alſo the Ladies and Nobility, to behold ſo brave and valorous Combat: Then the Trumpets begun to ſound; at which appeared forth three Knights Errant, with their Targets of Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, Sable, and Purple Colour; and having enter'd the Liſts, they ſtood in expectation of any would come to oppoſe them: And combating coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, they broke many Lances to their great honour, until <hi>Olivaires</hi> and <hi>Arthur</hi> ſhewed themſelves in the Field: And now one of the Knights Errant had with a brisk puſh thrown
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152282:14"/>out of the Saddle, and caſt to the ground a Courtier, a very Valourous Knight, and ſtood ready in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a New Combatant. The Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Young <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſeeing this, takes a Maſſy Lance, and turns his Horſe oppoſite to the ſtout Cavalier, who accepting the Challenge, runs full againſt <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and broke his Lance; but ſo great was the blow that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Valiant Youth <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> that it brought both himſelf and's Horſe to the ground: And when he had got another Lance, the ſecond Knight Errant comes againſt him in revenge of bis foil'd Companion; but with the touch of <hi>Olivaires</hi> Lance, the Knight tumbles back out of his Saddle, and in a woful condition lies ſtretched on the ground; and he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſt about from place to place with ſuch air and Gallantry, that he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be every-where in an inſtant. The like proof of his Valour made <hi>Arthur</hi> alſo. So that it was judged that theſe two Companions carried
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152282:15"/>away the Honour of that day. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off then to reſt themſelves till the next, they returned to the Feaſt; and likewiſe on the following day, as on the firſt, they were much admired, and the Third bore the whole Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe away: And the Judges con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring together, gave judgment of their Valour; the two Brothers, above all the reſt, were extoll'd; yet to <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> as the Principal Victor, the Prize was adjudged; then with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forts of Muſical Inſtruments they marched to the Palace, and there <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> ſpent ſome time in talk with the King and Queen, who alſo made him a Preſent; which much ſurprized the Valiant Knight, who ſeemed to himſelf not to have done any thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152282:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Queen is enamoured of her Son-in-Law</hi> Olivaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SO nobly thoſe three days of the Tilting did <hi>Olivaires</hi> behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he got the favour and love of all; but chiefly of the Queen, who was wonderfully inamour'd of his Heroical Courage, and charmed with his Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Noble Aſpect; which made her ſit much revolving in her thoughts the Feats and Bravery of this Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Knight, and ſay within her ſelf; O! under happy Stars was that Lady born, whoſe Beauty ſhall have the power to make <hi>Olivaires</hi> her glorious Captive; and, as ſhe muſt be ſome divine Creature, ſo ſhall her Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports be more than humane; but ſure I think that no Lady can look on this wonderful Youth, either with the Eye of Vertue, or the Senſitive one, but muſt immediately become and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152282:16"/>his Priſoner; inſomuch, that from day to day no other than ſuch kind of thoughts entertained the Queen; which produced in her heart a moſt violent and ardent Paſſion for him, that miſerably afflicted her, and put her by both her neceſſary Food and reſt: And now was the Day dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to St. <hi>John,</hi> come, which was celebrated with feaſting both in the Court and City; on which the Queen gave order that various ſorts of Muſick ſhould be brought into the great Hall of her Palace, and invited the Ladies and Court Gallants to a ſplendid Ball, who met together in all their fine Veſtments, New Modes, and rich Dreſs, both to delight the Queen, and to ſhew their Affection to the Airy and Complaiſant Laidies: But amongſt them all the moſt Comely <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and the much to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Arthur,</hi> did ſo excel in boon Grace, fine Dreſs, all manner of behaviour and deportment, and every thing, that the reſt neglected, the Ladies
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152282:16"/>unanimouſly had their Eyes ever upon theſe.</p>
               <p>But the Queen's Heart above all was raviſhed with the Beauty of one of them, having for many days con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance nouriſhed in her Breaſt a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion for <hi>Olivaires;</hi> ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly fixing her Eyes on him, her Spirits to an exceſs became agitated and inflam'd; which preſently cauſed a change in her Countenance, and a ſwimming in her Head, ſo that from her Royal Seat ſhe fell down as dead on the ground; which as the Ladies beheld (though not ſuſpecting the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) they haſtily run to her, and ſnatching her up in their Arms, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her into her Chamber: And now the Dancing and Merriment were at an end, and all the care was to bring the Queen out of her Swoon; who being at length recovered from it, diſmiſt all that ſtood about her, and deſired them to retire, and leave her alone, the better to take ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; wherefore they every one went
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152282:17"/>to their own Apartments. Now after a little while, her Sons, <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Olivaires,</hi> came to give her a Viſit, and they were gladly received, by her ſhewing more kindneſs and affection to them than ever ſhe had done before; embracing firſt one, and then the other, many times: And among her Careſſes theſe words forced themſelves out (ſpoken with much paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) toward <hi>Olivaires;</hi> You know you are looked upon with admiration above all men: Which words made the Valiant Youth <hi>Olivaires</hi> much to marvail what they meant; but for that he could not ſuddenly conceive whether they were to be interpreted into a good or diſhoneſt ſenſe, he ſhewed no concern, nor gave any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; and taking their leave, they left the Queen to reſt with her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152282:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Queen diſcovers her love to</hi> Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires, <hi>and ſhews her Pain; and</hi> Olivaires <hi>returns her honourable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>MAny days paſſed in which <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> held not any Conference with the Queen, but directed by his good Genius, cautiouſly declin'd all; and ſpent his time with <hi>Arthur</hi> in the Exerciſes of Arms, and at Juſting, and Turnament, and other valorous Feats and Enterprizes; at which the Queen contrived to be always a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Spectatreſs; which did not give any ſatisfaction to <hi>Olivaires</hi> mind: The King enjoy'd full content to have two ſuch brave Cavaliers his Sons, and uſed to ſay he was the happieſt Prince in the World; nor, for their ſake, did ſtand in fear of any Enemy; and for ſo great a Bleſſing was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually praiſing and adoring his, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152282:18"/>the Univerſe's Soveraign: But For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, the Parent of Miſery, and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Humane Content, quickly turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Sweets into bitter: For the Queen being bewitched, and hurried by her Amorous Fancy, could take no reſt; and the unhappy Creature, whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderateneſs made her ſo, ſpent her time alone in her Chamber, ſobbing, and uttering words of piteous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and thus talking low to her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> the perfection of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Nature! O my Star, O my Sun! O! whom I hoor'd up in my paſſionate Thoughts as my chiefeſt Treaſure! For whom, perhaps, I am forced to do that which never Queen did before, being compelled by thy Beauty to caſt off my Affections for the King, on whom in duty and reaſon they ought to be fixed, and place them on Thee, which is diſhoneſt and unjuſt! O un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Queen! (ſaid ſhe then confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſhame) who thus renderſt thy ſelf worthy of an Eternal Puniſhment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were the Expoſtulations and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guings
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152282:18"/>with her ſelf of this Miſerable Lady, when at any time ſhe found her ſelf alone, and ſo her Love-fits came more violent upon her. One day <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Olivaires</hi> went to give her a Viſit, which ſhe received ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream kindly at them; and after a little while ſhe took <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Hand, much careſſing it; which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he looked on as no more than Expreſſions of a Maternal Affection: And entering into various Diſcourſes, yet all relating to the diſorder of her Love-ſick Mind, her trembling Voice ſo falter'd, that ſhe could ſcarce bring out her words; however, with ſome difficulty ſaid, (ſitting near to him;) <hi>Olivaires,</hi> was never Lady ſo happy as to triumph for having made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over your Heart? Was you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver inamour'd of any of the fair Sex, as you are pleas'd to complement us? Did you never, <hi>Olivaires,</hi> think Lady worthy of more than your ordinary Affection? I do aſſure you, Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queen, I am no Captive of <hi>Cupid</hi>'s
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152282:19"/>(replied <hi>Olivaires</hi>) and your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's ſelf can witneſs for me, that I never hitherto have been obſerved to caſt on Lady any Wanton Glances, or Amorous Eye: And I do aſſure your Majeſty, that I do not intend to ingage in that Paſſion, till I have performed ſome Signal and Noble Actions, which then may incourage me to attempt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a conqueſt over ſome fair Ladies ſoft, though, perhaps, at the ſame time, obdurate Breaſt: And becauſe I am conſcious to my ſelf of having done no Feats of that merit as yet; I fancy your Majeſty is pleaſed to incite and ſpur me on (by thus queſtioning) to ſome difficult and honourable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits: And truly 'tis my Deſign, if ſo it ſhall pleaſe the Almighty, to give ſuch proof of my Proweſs and Valour, that both your Majeſties will be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſatisfy'd and content with my Performances: Theſe laſt words were like ſo many blazing Firebrands to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the Queen's heart, who laying hold on him, knowing otherwiſe he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152282:19"/>was upon departure, ſet her ſelf to utter theſe words, which put her into great confuſion, as they came from her. But, tell me, if ſome Lady of high deſert ſhould chance to beſtow her love upon you, as one who well knew your Valour worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with ſo rich a Prize, ſhould voluntarily, having regard to your youthful Modeſty, and that out of a moſt generous and deſerving Mind, offer her ſelf a fair Preſent unto you, could you then be ſo modeſt and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to refuſe a compliance with the lovely Suitreſs? For certain, Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queen, my Virtues, Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Graces, are not ſo potent to fetter Ladies after the rate you ſpeak of: But grant they were, and the bountiful Creator had conferr'd upon me ſuch, I truly ſhould look upon that Lady as very indiſcreet, and to act much out of want of wit, who ſhould throw her ſelf upon any Man, unſolicited, or, at leaſt, without having ſome Aſſurances of mutual Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152282:20"/>from her beloved One: And ſuch a paſſion I ſhould reject, nor could ever entertain an hearty value for ſuch a coming kind Creature. Thus he took leave of the Queen, as cautious againſt any bad thing; who (though not ſhewing it by her looks) remained diſcontented, and not leſs afflicted than inrag'd, both for <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi>'s departure, and his cruel An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which in the leaſt was not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>begs of God to erace ſuch a thought out of the Queen's heart; himſelf contriving a way to expel ſo vain a deſire out of the breaſt of ſo great a Majeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLIVAIRES</hi> deſiring to take honourable leave of his Mother-in-law, the Queen, made ſigns to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur,</hi> and ſaid, it was time now to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152282:20"/>the Knights to the Field for the Turnament. Whereupon ſhe in parting with his hands, ſqueez'd his fingers cloſe; a certain ſecret token of Love: Which thing much afflicted the Valiant <hi>Olivaires;</hi> yet he kept it to himſelf, nor would ſuffer any change of Countenance to appear to <hi>Arthur,</hi> not to give him any occaſion of wondering what might cauſe it. The Queen being left alone in her Chamber, returned to her former complaints, ſaying, O! <hi>Olivaires,</hi> the very center of my Soul, unto which all its motions tend, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they all lean, yet cannot reſt. I very well know that you are Maſter of much more Wit than is needful eaſily to make you diſcern what an Affection I have contracted for you; reſolving with her ſelf, the day following, to make, without reſerve, an open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of it to him. He, on the other ſide, kept the thing deep in his mind, and contrived ſome way to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel this vain hope out of the Lady's
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152282:21"/>heart, propounding certain death to himſelf, rather than the leaſt compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thought for ſo damnable a Wickedneſs: And turning his corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Eyes up to Heaven, and thoſe of his mind to the Divine Author and Creator of it, he ſaid; Thou Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord, who haſt formed me after thy own ſimilitude, and beſtowed thoſe Graces and Favours upon me which I never was in a capacity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; I beſeech thee of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, great Father, and Source of all, that thou wouldeſt deliver me from ſuch ſpiritual deſtruction, and preſerve, my Soveraign and Father, from ſo great diſhonour, by eracing out of the mind of this Illuſtrious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy theſe unrighteous Thoughts; and I ſhall aſcribe nothing to my own Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but freely and intirely all to thy Infinite Mercy and Goodneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152282:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>is courted by the Queen; and his Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> coming to the Palace the next Morning, that he might occaſion no ſuſpicion, according to his wonted cuſtom, paid his humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to the Queen, waiting the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity when many Ladies were in company together with her: But ſhe laying aſide both Fear and Honour, made towards <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and taking him by the hand, conducted him into her Chamber: And <hi>Olivaires,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this would tend more to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's advantage, ſuffered himſelf to be drawn aſide; wherefore, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone, and ſitting together, the Queen, after divers times having look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed earneſtly on him, ſaid thus. Do you call to mind, Sir, our late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe? Truly, Madam, replied <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> I remember nothing at all of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152282:22"/>it, and am utterly ignorant of your meaning. Indeed you have, I muſt confeſs, a very ſhort memory, if ſo ſoon you can forget a Conference and Affair of ſo concerning import. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you diſſemble to pretend igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my torment; and your Eye may perceive it better than my words can expreſs it to your Ear. It much troubles me, Madam, that I can no better underſtand your Majeſty. Dear, Sir, (ſaid the Lady) know then, that I have a deſire to make my ſelf yours, and do give my heart unto you; and although before this hour you was Lord over me, and might have uſed your Slave as you had pleas'd; yet partly out of fear, and partly ſhame, I durſt not declare ſo much to you: And if now (being compell'd to reveal it by thoſe Ardors of love that intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably inflame my heart and fancy) Fortune will be my Adverſary, and alſo your ſelf, in thinking me unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your Affections, I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly with theſe hands procure
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152282:22"/>my own death. Wherefore, dear Sir, for me to dye, or to live, are either of them in your power. When theſe diſhoneſt and harſh words grated on <hi>Olivaires</hi> Ear, they ſummon'd, and made ſtand an ocean of tears in his Eyes, which yet quickly were dried up by the heat of the bluſhes his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty forced into his Face. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without ſhew of being troubled (hoping to draw her from ſo vile a thought) he ſaid; Madam, your Majeſty ſays that you love me, and deſire return of affection from me again. By my Loyalty, I love none better than my Soveraign Lord the King, and do deſire to ſerve your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as a Mother, and to obey you in all things you ſhall command me, as far as my duty ſhall require; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time that I do not execute the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of my King as a Father's, and your Majeſty's as a Mother's, I ſhall with hatred look upon my ſelf as one moſt unworthy to have been born in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:152282:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Queen's Parley with</hi> Olivaires, <hi>and how ſhe diſcharges him her preſence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THen, all in a rage, and full of immoderate grief, the Queen turns to <hi>Olivaires!</hi> uttering theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate words. O <hi>Olivaires,</hi> a Curſe light on your Beauty, if 'tis it has made you ſo proud, and ſo inhumane a Creature: 'Tis high ingratitude this in you to deſpiſe the offer'd Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Crowned Lady: Would you then that ſhould periſh by your Cruelty ſo mighty a Queen? Ah! ſee to whom I have truſted my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Secret, my Heart, and my Life! Shall I therefore of a Friend now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your Foe? In lieu of the Life which I give you, will you procure my death? It ſhall never be that he who ſeeks me miſchief, ſhall go unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited: and one diſcourteſie ſhall not fail to find return of another. God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152282:23"/>pardon thee the Evils which may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low upon thy Injuſtice; get thee hence out of my ſight, and never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in my preſence more. For I ſhall not long be able to conceal my grief, ſo infinitely am I afflicted. <hi>Olivaires</hi> all amazed, roſe up, and withdrew, taking leave after his wonted reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and humble manner. She remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone, and going into her Cloſet, begun ſo ſtrange a complaint and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing, as is impoſſible for Tongue to utter, or Pen in any meaſure to deſcribe. She thought the Torments of the damned were but Flea-bitings to what ſhe felt, and 10000 real Hells but painted Fire to her imaginary One. <hi>Olivaires</hi> then went to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and a little after with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Arthur</hi> to his own Lodgings. <hi>Arthur</hi> perceiv'd his Brother had ſome trouble upon him, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the occaſion: But he having no mind to declare it, told him, to conceal his grievance, that he found himſelf not very well; for which <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152282:24"/>was much afflicted, and ſtay'd with him till Evening, about the time they were wont to go to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. Wherefore <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſaid to him; My dear Sir, and Brother, I deſire you would be pleaſed to go to Court, and, if you love me, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelf very chearful, that the King and Queen may have no occaſion to enquire after my welfare: But, if they ſhall ask of me, tell them, that to morrow I will come to the Palace; for I would very gladly have them not to know any thing of my diſorder. <hi>Arthur</hi> perceived that <hi>Olivaires</hi> had a mind to be alone, and ſo left him after he had ſaid, Dear Brother, I have no mind at all to part from you: But, ſince 'tis your requeſt, I am content; and I ſhall diſcharge that which you have enjoin'd me. I deſire you to keep in a good mind, and act nothing to your prejudice: And embracing him, he kiſs'd him, giving him to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his return would be ſlow, and that he ſhould not diſturb him for that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152282:24"/>night; which words pierced <hi>Olivaires</hi> to the very heart, by reaſon of his reſolv'd-on ſecret Deſign, which he was determin'd to put into act. So he left him with tears in his eyes, and broken words, which he had not power to utter perfectly; which <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> mightily marvail'd at, knowing it muſt needs be ſome extraordinary chance, dolor, or cauſe, that could produce ſuch heavy and diſmal effects. But, to trouble him no further, he ſeemed to take no notice, and depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But much otherwiſe had the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and parting of them both been, had <hi>Arthur</hi> known what was to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: But <hi>Olivaires</hi> at his going away was now the more penſive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152282:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>remaining alone in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, writes a Letter to his Brother</hi> Arthur, <hi>and leaves it with a Vial of Water, and prepares for departing the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſaw himſelf alone, he began to think of the ſad miſhap had befall'n him; and, conſidering he could not follow his Friend, he curſed his unfortunate Stars; and grieved that the Queen had conceiv'd ſuch inormity in her mind; ſo of the two Evils, he elected that which, as appear'd to him, had the leſs danger in it. He ſaw for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the King would be extreamly troubled at his departure; but greater grief would it be to him, ſhould he chance to have intelligence of the lewd importunity of his Conſort: Nor ever went out of his thoughts what power an evil Woman might have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152282:25"/>(tho he were guiltleſs) to bring him in as liable to the heavieſt puniſhment; and he choſe to purſue the paths of Vertue, and ſhun thoſe of Vice: Therefore calling to his Page, he ask'd for Ink and Paper to write, which were brought him; then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering every one away, and that none ſhould come at him till he call'd, he bolted his Chamber door; and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf on the Bed, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with grief, he lamented his ill fortune, ſorrowing to leave his Country, Friends, Father, <hi>Arthur,</hi> and many other whoſe lov'd Idea's preſented themſelves to his mind; yet at laſt corroborates himſelf with ſaying, Tho fortune will not in this Realm, perhaps in another ſhe may ſmile on me; and ſo reſolves for flight, and to wean himſelf as much as poſſible of's moleſting Affections for all; and taking Pen in hand, he puts himſelf in a poſture to write a Letter to his Brother <hi>Arthur</hi> in theſe or the like words. Fortune, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutreſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152282:26"/>of thoſe that excel, enemy to friendſhip, by her continual revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of miſeries, is ever venting her malicious ſpight againſt thoſe ſhe ought not; and thoſe ſhe takes a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for, without any reſpected merit, ſhe often delights to ſet on the higheſt pinacle of her State; ſo that one day we are exalted, the next brought low; lately we ſwom in wealth, and now are reduced to neceſſity. Hence when Hiſtorians record and deſcribe our Virtues, they praiſe our Deeds as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and diſparage them as baſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they think good. If then the great Lady Governeſs of theſe Accidents, and Hiſtory infringe the worth of ſuch grand Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what wonder is it, deareſt Brother, if ſhe thwart my Will, the which being diſturbed by various Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties, cauſes my departure. And let it not diſpleaſe you that I did not make you a partaker of my grief, nor gave the leaſt intimation to you of my going away. For conſidering the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152282:26"/>great mutual love betwixt us, I knew for certain you would either have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied, or detained me; which ſhould not have been, for I am too much afflicted by ill fortune. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not communicate unto you an account of my Diſaſter, for I have oft endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to tell my caſe, but cannot get out my words, ſo impriſoned and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd are they in my Breaſt: And for this cauſe, and that I would not give you ſo great trouble, I ſay, for that I am hinder'd, I keep the ſecret to my ſelf; nor am I obliged to reveal it. Now whilſt I write, reflecting on the ſorrow I ſhall occaſion among you, my heart does tear in pieces; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you to pay my infinite reſpects to the King and Queen, and of both in my name beg pardon for my afflicting departure. I leave you, dear Sir, and Brother, a Vial of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is of rare virtue, on which by our near relationſhip let me oblige you to caſt your eye once every day; and this you will gain to know, That
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152282:27"/>whenever the water is troubled, I am in ſome great extremity, and have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary need of your aſſiſtance, and that will be in caſe of danger of life, or ſome evil equivalent: To what place I ſhall go, Province, or City, to make my abode, I cannot at all inform you, having wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd my ſelf up to the conduct of Deſtiny. I give to you all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices I can poſſibly pay you, and put up my Prayers unto God, the Infinite Potentate, that he would pleaſe to make you proſperous in all things, and elevate your mind to all virtuous and noble Enterprizes, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally raiſe you more and more, nor ever ſuffer you to ſink from your high Station.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152282:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>arriving at a Port-Town, takes Ship, and aſſociates with a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Olivaires</hi> had writ the Letter, he laid it ſo as <hi>Arthur</hi> might not fail of finding it, and alſo the Vial; and took a large Sum of Gold, and Jewels of great value, and lock'd them up in his Mail, which he placed behind him on the beſt Horſe in his Stable; and having mounted, he left the City with deep ſighing, and grievous lamentation; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gone ſome little diſtance, he turns his Horſe, and faces the City, ſaying. O Lord of Truth, who haſt formed the Heaven and the Earth, and of thy goodneſs haſt faſhioned me after thy own image and likeneſs, I beſeech thee by that moſt ſacred Paſſion, whereby thou didſt redeem our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane kind, ſuffering a moſt bitter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152282:28"/>death for it, that thou would'ſt be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of thy Divine Pity to comfort my afflicted Sovereign and Father, who without any his rigour, and alſo knowledge of my departure, loſes the Heir of his Illuſtrious Kingdom; and of thy favour conſolate <hi>Arthur,</hi> who hath loſt the deareſt and moſt faithful Friend he had in the world by my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forced to wander up and down in it; and ſupport the hearts of the whole Court, that they may be able to ſuſtain the being deprived of ſuch a Friend. All his Acquaintance of the Court ſeem'd to be preſent at theſe words, who in dolorous accents made the like complaint. O brave Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, whoſe dear delight was the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Art of War; ſee you have loſt <hi>Olivaires</hi> the Invincible Prince of the ſame; hang up your Armour now to ruſt; leave off the breaking of Lances, where the Valiant are exerciſed at Tilting; where the Trumpets and Clarions ſounded loud to inſpire Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for Victory. O you who walk
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152282:28"/>the paths of amorous Fancy, who ſhall be your Pattern now for comely Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, good Dreſs, and new-invented Modes to make you more acceptable to the fair Ones? The Raviſhing Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renades that were heard before the bluſhing <hi>Aurora</hi> was ſeen, will now be neglected, ſince Harmony it ſelf has expir'd to us and you. Virgins of Nobility, To day you have loſt the Gallantry of the Court, and the fair Mirror, wherein you beheld your own ſweet reſemblance. In a word, All that is good, all that is deſirable and lovely, is vaniſhed: The Balls are now at an end; delicate Airs and charming Songs are ſilenc'd; and all the Inſtruments of Muſick are out of tune, upon the departure of <hi>Olivaires.</hi> Lo! he has turn'd his Palfrey into a rougher Path. Whilſt the Noble Knight prayed with much ardency, his Eyes became a Fountain of flowing Tears. So riding on for ſome days, he arrived at length at a Sea-port Town, where he found a Ship bound
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152282:29"/>for <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and in it was a great Lord of <hi>Africa,</hi> who had hired her for himſelf, and for whom her Sails were now hoiſed. <hi>Olivaires</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Maſter to go on Board, was denied; but a Knight belonging to this Lord, obſerving the temper of <hi>Olivaires,</hi> begged of him, and ſo he was admitted; and together they went up into the Ship; and his Horſe alſo was taken in. Upon this account <hi>Olivaires</hi> and the Knight contracted an intimate friendſhip; and for the comelineſs of his Perſon, his Mien, and virtuous Modeſty, he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfully look'd upon, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly entertain'd by all. But let us leave the Ship to the diſpoſal and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Winds, of Fortune, and of Fate; and turn our diſcourſe to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur,</hi> left alone, afflicted, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, when he did not find his dearly beloved Brother, and then re-viſit the wavy Ocean, and her perilous Rocks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152282:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How</hi> Arthur Dalgarve <hi>enter'd his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and read the Letter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next morning <hi>Arthur</hi> came to <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Chamber, and finding his Page waiting at the Door, he ask'd him why he went not in; to whom the other anſwer'd, becauſe <hi>Olivaires</hi> had ordered him ſo. But <hi>Arthur</hi> ſeeing the Sun was pretty high advanc'd, bid his Page open; and he entering in, quickly ſhut the Door to upon him, and run to the Bed to find his dear Brother; but miſſing him, he was much amazed.</p>
               <p>And looking up and down the Chamber, he found the Letter and the Vial; and taking it up, and reading, he was immediately ſo fill'd with ſorrow, that he was forc'd to caſt himſelf upon the Bed, exhaling and ſpending more ſpirits out of his Body, than were left behind; and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152282:30"/>he that had heard the mourning of <hi>Arthur,</hi> would have thought he was juſt a-going to die of Grief; and truly he would rather have choſen to have done ſo, than have loſt the company of <hi>Olivaires.</hi> O my dear <hi>Olivaires,</hi> cry'd he; O my true Friend! I could never have forſaken your Company, as you have mine. Surely ſome great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion has brought thee to this; yet my faithful obſervance of you, with our ſtrict friendſhip, might have embolden'd you to truſt me with your whole Caſe; that I partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of your Affliction, might have taken a ſhare of it upon my ſelf; but you was too kind to give me ſo much trouble. O Father, O Sovereign, what a ſad misfortune has fall'n upon thee! How will thy poor heart ſuſtain ſo vaſt a dolor? How wilt thou be able to live one hour longer, when thou ſhalt know all the words <hi>Olivaires</hi> has written? And ſaying thus, <hi>Arthur</hi> proceeded to read the Letter; which did ſo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152282:30"/>mightily increaſe his ſorrow, that his Spirits failing, and his Colour vaniſhing, he fell as dead upon <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> Bed, and long time remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152282:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King goes into</hi> Olivaires<hi>'s Chamber to look for him, and finds</hi> Arthur <hi>in a Swoon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Gentlemen that ſtood ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting at the Door, ſeeing none come forth, nor knowing what was become of <hi>Arthur</hi> or <hi>Olivaires,</hi> ſent to let the King underſtand as much, who quickly came, and knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and calling, could get no Anſwer; whereupon he haſtily order'd the door to be broke open, and entring, he found <hi>Arthur</hi> for dead upon the Bed; but his <hi>Olivaires</hi> no where; and calling to <hi>Arthur,</hi> and having no anſwer, he laid his hands on him, and turning him over, he ſaw plainly 'twas a Swoon; and bid bring cold Water, and ſtrong Scents, and ſo reſtor'd him to himſelf: Then <hi>Arthur</hi> ſuddenly finding his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to recover, gave a great ſigh, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Ah! Death, why doſt thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152282:31"/>me to live? Why doſt thou not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thy Office on me, according as I long for it? Why doſt thou raiſe me into Life, who through exceſs of Grief can but a little while continue in it? And having the Letter in his hand, with a heavy groan he delivered it to the King, who took it, and began to read; but no ſooner looked he on the firſt line, than paternal Affection rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Blood into mighty agitation and diſorder, and again, fear quickly made him turn pale; ſo that between the one Paſſion and the other, he was ſeiz'd on by extremity of Sorrow, and renting his Garment, and tearing off the Hair from his Head and Beard, he appear'd as one Diſtracted; now ſmiting his Breaſts, now his Face, and nowcrying out aloud, he begins to vent himſelf in ſome words directed to the great Lords of his Court, who ſtood aſtoniſhed at ſo horrible and unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Accident; Help me to Lament, you invincible Cavaliers; let your hearts bear a ſhare in my Affliction,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152282:32"/>for my Dolour redounds to the whole Realm: Lo! my ſo much Beloved <hi>Olivaires</hi> is loſt, he is gone, and a ſad and hard Fate hath ſent him away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Foreign Realms, to deprive me both of my State and Life. His Lord's moved by their Sovereign's Miſery, and afflicted for ſo freſh and unvalued a loſs, felt within their own breaſts ſo poignant a Dolour, that the ſtouteſt heart among them was overcome and ſail'd; ſo that inſtead of Conſolating their Sovereign, their Sorrow made them alſo imitate his frantick Actions, in beating their Breaſts, making terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lamentations, and tearing their Hair; and even diſtracted through Love and Grief; with their Cries they pierced the Heavens: Oh! the Crown of my Kingdom, ſaid the King, in what ſadneſs haſt thou left me! was not enough the firſt ſtab of thy Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which Launced my heart with thy Mother's Death? Surely that was enough without the addition of this, which has transfixed my very
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152282:32"/>Soul: Where ſhall my old Age find repoſe, which beholding thy Virtue, was delighted and happy? My King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſubject unto thee, which was ſo well ſatisfied, ſo much affected thee, whither will it be reduc'd? Under what hope hath it now to live? One Arm of thy Virtue did lovingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, the other, with the Sword of thy daring Valour, defended it. But the hopes are become fruſtrate, the imaginations vain, and deſigns de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, bottom'd on thy admirable Soul. Oh! my <hi>Olivaires!</hi> How art thou loſt? Where wandereſt thou, O my Son! Where art thou, O the hope and end of all my thinking! The Merciful Almighty grant by thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to this ſo much-afflicted State, Conſolation; and by thy appearing again, clear up that darkneſs has overſpread and put this honourable Court into deep Mourning: But if in deſtiny it be not that thou muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, that it would pleaſe him to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up thy Spirit in Peace, and at the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152282:33"/>ſame time ſet me at Liberty from the Priſon of this wretched and dolorous Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Through all parts of the world Courters are diſpatched in ſearch of the King's Son; and of the Queen's Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King as diſtracted aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning the whole Court, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of but by a few, ſo afflicted was he and diſtreſſed, runs to find out the Queen, and crying out and beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Boſom, throws his Arms about her Neck, who was ſurpriz'd and aſtoniſh'd, not underſtanding the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But when ſhe heard proceed from the King's mouth theſe words, The Victor at our Feſtivals, and the Delight of the Kingdom is gone, a pointed torment ſtruck her to the heart; let us lament (purſued the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152282:33"/>King) let us lament, unfortunate Queen, the great good we are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of; our Conſolation is vaniſhed, the remedy of our evils is ſtolen from us by Fortune; you ſhall no more ſee that Valiant Son whom you ſo much commended, the Victor Invincible; well underſtood the Queen that the Afflicted King ſpoke of her Beloved <hi>Olivaires,</hi> although he never mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Name, and ſhe conceived to herſelf the cauſe of his departure; and ſhe aſſur'd herſelf of the loſs of ſo Noble a Cavalier, knowing ſhe had given occaſion of lament to the whole Court; wherefore her heart was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly prick'd with remorſe, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of her Error; and what by one paſſion, what the other, fell into a Swoon in the King's Arms; who was ſo infeebled that he could ſcarce ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain her Weight; and the Queen's Affliction joining with the Grief for his Son, made their conditions alike; and moving to where he thought better to have ſupported himſelf, he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152282:34"/>alſo Swooned to. In this juncture, the Court who followed him with his Son <hi>Arthur,</hi> arrived, being reſolved in diligent ſearch after <hi>Olivaires,</hi> to ſend through the whole World; and ſeeing the Royal Pair lye extended on the floor in a Swoon through Grief, they did certainly conclude that the Souls of thoſe Crowned Heads had taken their farewel flight; and not without great complaints and infinite lamentation, did approach to the King and Queen, the Lords, and chiefly <hi>Arthur,</hi> ſeeing what neceſſity there was, did boldly come cloſe up to them ſaying, with as loud a voice as he was able, O King! O Queen! (ſome helps being uſed to recover their Spirits) this is not a time to die, but withal, endeavour to ſeek after my Royal Brother, according as we have order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The King (a little come to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) hearing <hi>Arthur</hi>'s words, by ſtretching forth his Arms gave ſigns of his being better, and the Queen the like; who at the ſight of her Son
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152282:34"/>
                  <hi>Arthur</hi> was a little comforted, and the Ladies lifting her up, lead her to her Chamber; the King placed on a Seat, heard all their Conſultation, which was reſolutely to make enquiry after <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and <hi>Arthur</hi> was the firſt who deſired the King's Favour to be one of thoſe who ſhould go after him; to whom the King returned anſwer, Son, if your preſence was ſubſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from our ſight, there would need no other cauſe of Death, for our Life would quickly have a period; be it your charge to ſend away fit men, and take you the management of this important Affair; wherefore the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you diſpatch Meſſengers over all the Provinces of the Earth, the more you will ſtudy our Content, and effect an alleviation of our Grief: 'Tis much my pleaſure, dread Sovereign, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your Majeſty's Commands, and I am ready to Obey you in whatever you enjoyn; although willingly I would be one of thoſe ſhould go in queſt after him, becauſe no man can
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152282:35"/>have a greater love for, or deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining him than myſelf. <hi>Arthur</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Meſſengers, and writ Letters, and Authorized them with the Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the King's own Name, and ſent them into all parts, according as was judged expedient. In the time of this expedition, the Queen finding herſelf deprived of her hearts deſire, cauſed her Ladies to withdraw, and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alone for ſome ſmall time; in which ſolitary opportunity ſhe began to take revenge upon herſelf for the injury ſhe had committed, and with rude hands ſeizing on her Vail, Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Hair, ſhe imagined there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe had pretty well puniſhed her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, accompanying that Cruelty with ſuch Accents as theſe; Curſed was the hour of my Nativity! I am a Woman rightly accurſed of Heaven, becauſe I have not been aſhamed to be an Enemy to Virtue! my Wickedneſs was the only occaſion of the ſelf-Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of him, whoſe Body was the Temple of Goodneſs: Say, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152282:35"/>Queen! were thy Offence pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, what puniſhment would be anſwerable to thy deſerts! O <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res!</hi> the Idea and Mirrour of all our Nobility, how ſhall I ever be able to render ſatisfaction for the injury I have done thee! O Righteous God, and juſt Judge! how canſt thou long permit that ſuch ſacred Blood ſhould ſuffer Affliction for the Wickedneſs of ſo Criminal a Woman! let thy Wrath ſhowre down upon the ſinful Dame, and reſtore to the higheſt ſtation of Honour her innocent Son. O <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res!</hi> how much better had it been that thou hadſt taken away my Life that hour when I ſecretly enticed thee to rob both thy ſelf and me of our Virtuous Fame! and not to have ſuffer'd me, by injuring both thee and the Publick, to put both thy Life and theirs into ſo bitter hazard! I repent from the ſhame which I conceive in my Breaſt. I do repent, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my fault, I ſee my error, and apparent is the Ruin occaſioned by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152282:36"/>my odious immodeſty. The offer was very grating to thy delicate Ear, tho I had not the power to govern my ſelf in a neceſſity: Oh! how ſhall I ever be able to endure the puniſhment of my fault! let Mirth be for ever ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from my heart, and all the days of my life ſpent in Lamentation! Great God, the Sovereign Good, and Righteous Lord, be pleaſed to accept of my Prayers, for I am purpoſed to treaſure up all my wealth in the boſom of the poor, and in holy uſes; for his ſake whom I have ſo much offended, for the ſake of that beſt and moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing flower of Youth. Preſerve him, O Lord, in all dangers he may light into by the way of his Travel, and of thy infinite pity pardon me my great Offence. The King and Queen both comforting themſelves with hopes of news of <hi>Olivaires;</hi> but fortune croſſed their intent who went in purſuit after him, for they could not get the leaſt intelligence of him; wherefore at their return they put the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152282:36"/>Court into ſecond Mourning: But <hi>Arthur</hi> upon it fell into a Sickneſs, and likewiſe the King; the Lamentation was renewed through the Realm, and among the Lords. But let us leave the Kingdom to its ſorrow, and turn our Diſcourſe to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> whom we ſhall find quickly toſs'd in a Tempeſt at Sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Ship which ſtood for</hi> Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>by a great misfortune periſhes in the Main, and all are caſt away ſave</hi> Olivaires <hi>and his Friend the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>YOU have heard how the Ship ſpread her Sails before the Wind. On Board of which was a great Lord, who admitted of, by means of his Knight, the Honourable <hi>Olivaires.</hi> Now you muſt underſtand that being arrived within three days
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152282:37"/>Sail of their deſigned Haven, a great Tempeſt aroſe to thwart them, whereby the Sea became turbulent about a Month's ſpace, ſo that they knew not which way to ſteer; in which time the Tempeſt, Waves, and Wind tore the Sails, broke the Ropes, threw down the Maſts and Sail-Yards; the Rudder was loſt, the Anchors were caſt away, and the Pilot, through his ill fortune, was tired out, and no longer able to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern; therefore the Ship deprived of her Tackling, was left at random, and expoſed to the guidance of the enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Ocean; whereby ſhe was caſt upon a Rock, and from the hind Deck to the fore, ſplit in two. Now the Sailers, by this miſhap, being redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to extream peril of their lives, betook them to Swimming, and thoſe that could not, neceſſity taught; ſome on Boards, others on Tables, and whatever light matter they could lay hold of to help them. <hi>Olivaires</hi> at the firſt ſeized on a large Plank for
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152282:37"/>his ſupport, and taking the Cavalier whom he loved on it in company with him, they faſtened themſelves thereto, nor was he diſheartened to put his Mail betwixt them, binding it faſt, ſo to provide himſelf for whatever ſtreights he might be brought to, and to make all the proviſion for life was poſſible; and after recommendation to the God of Mercy, they expoſed themſelves a prey to the Waves, Swimming as long as their ſtrengths would endure, which was but for a ſmall time; for it being no warm Seaſon, and the Water frigid, their Arms and Legs were benumm'd and made inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by the Cold. So that if they had not been as cloſe faſtened as the Ivy to the Oak, the ſporting Billows had many a time diſmounted them from their Wooden Horſe. So a whole Night, and the following Morning, they remained in this unparallell'd danger: <hi>Olivaires,</hi> who was endued with greater ſtoutneſs of mind, and alſo ſtrength of body, than the other
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152282:38"/>Cavalier, bid him, Courage; but he was ſo diſmayed that he could ſcarce get out a word, and begun to faint; then <hi>Olivaires</hi> lifting up his eyes and thoughts to Heaven, and alſo a ſincere heart, ſaid, O Lord, who prepared'ſt a way for the Sons of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thorough the Red Sea, and delivered'ſt the Three Children from out of the blazing Furnace; who even in thy Fleſh could'ſt walk upon the Waters, and ſaved'ſt St. <hi>Peter</hi> when he began to ſink, only by thy word; I beſeech thee, that as thou extendedſt thy pity and favour unto them, ſo thou would now alſo be pleaſed to ſuccour and ſave us. Lo! this ſhort Prayer pierced the Heaven; and two Harts appeared upon the Water, which running Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly there, came up to ſalute theſe diſtreſſed Companions: Give ſpeedy Glory to God, cry'd <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and having leap'd upon the one, and helped the Cavalier to mount the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they Swom with that Swiftneſs, as if in chace they had run on the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152282:38"/>land, and ſet the half dead couple a ſhore, and left them there, and took their way to the Woody Mountains: the warmth of the Sun now having thaw'd and cheriſh'd their congeal'd Limbs; and having taken ſome heart, being got out of danger, in the firſt place they returned thanks unto God, and then with ſlow pace (<hi>Olivaires</hi> ſupporting the Cavalier, who was full of Water, and ſore ſhatter'd by the Waves) they arrived at a little Cabin and poor Lodging, where with a good fire, and other neceſſaries they were forc'd to ſend far for, he cheer'd up his Companion; and having got him to bed, he after took care of himſelf, as alſo was needful; and there they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited themſelves ſome days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:152282:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How</hi> Olivaires, <hi>the Cavalier growing worſe, orders him to be carried to the place of his Nativity, where he dies; and of various Accidents that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving reſted a while at this ſmall Cottage, and the Cavalier's Malady increaſing upon him, there chanced to come there a Noble Man of thoſe Parts, with whom <hi>Olivaires</hi> enter'd into much diſcourſe, finding him a Perſon had been converſant in the world, and was able to talk of the various occurrences and riſques of fortune that happen in, and attend it: So as they diſcourſed now of one thing, now of another; the ſick Knight could gather that they were on <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground, in which Kingdom he breathed his firſt Air, being born in the City of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and quickly inquir'd after the place of his Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152282:39"/>and underſtood he was but three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore miles diſtant from it; then he turned toward him to queſtion him further, If he knew ſuch a Cavalier, (naming himſelf); The Nobleman replied, No; but he had heard him well ſpoken of for a brave and worthy Gentleman, and that he was highly eſteemed of in that City; and having ſo ſaid, he departed, and left <hi>Olivaires</hi> to purſue his own Journey. I am Maſter <hi>John Talbot,</hi> and this is my Country; in that City I have a good Eſtate, my admirable Friend, and therefore be pleaſed to let me be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried thither, ſince it is not far off, and I will repay you whatever charges you ſhall be at; for I perceive my ſtrength to waſte every day more and more, and if it had not been for your virtue and goodneſs, I had certainly periſhed in the Water, or here on the Land, if not before. <hi>Olivaires</hi> comforted him up, and told him he had hopes of his recovery; however, for the other, he needed not trouble himſelf, and he
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152282:40"/>made him a promiſe; but when he ſaw there were no hopes of his life, he order'd him to be carried, becauſe he was too weak to ſit on Horſeback; and having bought for himſelf an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent good Palfrey, he went along with him, and Men bearing by turns from place to place, brought him at length into his own City; where the Cavalier being arrived, and heartily receiv'd by his Friends and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, he ſuddenly became ſpeechleſs, and after a few days changed this life for a better. It happened that a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, many years before, was to have received a Sum of Monies of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier that was dead, and he made a diſtrain in his Houſe, and would not ſuffer his Body to be interr'd till he was paid of, which he could main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by Writings, and he had ſtood ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate many years. This bad News troubled his Parents, for that it would oblige them to ſell their Goods and Eſtate, neither could the price of them reach it; therefore they reſolved
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152282:40"/>rather to let him remain excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, than ſatisfy the Debt; but the generous Prince <hi>Olivaires</hi> would no leſs be his Friend in death, than Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in life, as you ſhall hear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>cauſes the Cavalier to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and diſcharges the Debt; and of ſome Juſtings proclaimed in the Court of the King of</hi> England.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> ſeeing the great Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of the Knight's Parents, was much offended at it; and uſed all the endeavour he could to accord the matter betwixt the Parties: At length, being neither able to perſuade the one, nor bring the other to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition-agreement, he demanded of the Creditor, how much the total Sum came to; and when he was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd 2000 Nobles, he like a Prince, and Mirror of Princes, paid with Gold
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152282:41"/>and Jewels the Debt for his deceaſed Friend, retaining their late friendſhip freſh in his memory, and ſo procured for him Chriſtian Burial. After few days he heard a Report that the King of <hi>England</hi> had given command for proclaiming a Turnament to continue three days, and that he who ſhould get the victory, ſhould have for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Daughter to Wife, and the Kingdom for her Dowry; and this Royal Maid was the moſt beautiful and admirable young Creature that ever was born, or ever appear'd on the Earth: Nor would her Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow her in marriage on any King, or any other, unleſs he was the moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and braveſt of the Age, to the end that by Arms he might maintain her in her Dominions, and the State in peace. There were 400 Knights appointed to maintain the Juſting and Combat againſt whatever Cavalier had a mind to preſent himſelf on the Field for Encounter; and now Nine Months had paſſed ſince the Feaſt and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152282:41"/>Turnament were publiſhed, and the allotted term was to expire within 15 days. The Valiant <hi>Olivaires</hi> made it his buſineſs to underſtand well the Faſhion and Cuſtoms there; and by a very Experienc'd Cavalier, got Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as to every thing; and, that which delighted him moſt, he was credibly informed that the King's Daughter did much exceed the high Character and Fame that went abroad of her; therefore <hi>Olivaires</hi> fell in love with the very Idea he had conceived from report; thinking with himſelf, that if he ſhould come off Victor at ſuch a Turnament, the Prize would be an abundant reward of all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues and Affliction: And now he is on his way for going to the Juſting, and <hi>London,</hi> for the Court reſided at that City, and there was the place appointed for this famous Turnament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:152282:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What Fortune</hi> Olivaires <hi>has by the way, leaving</hi> Canterbury <hi>to go for the Tilting.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE time being now but ſhort before the Feaſt was to begin, the Valiant Knight is on his Journey, ever having in his mind the delightful thoughts of Victory, and of ſeeing ſo many Kings, Dukes, and great Lords make proof of their Valour; thus thinking he went on till he came to a Wood not far from the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> when lo! from one corner of it ſallied out 15 High-way men, Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates of Travellers, one whereof with Lance in hand advanced up, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf in the front of the reſt, and with villanous words ſaid, Lay down your Arms, Knight Errant, if you deſire to live. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> before he made anſwer, put up a ſecret Prayer unto God, and his Anſwer to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152282:42"/>the Aſſaſſinate was immediately to draw his Sword; and ſencing off the thruſts of his Spear, and making his Horſe give back, he brings him down and kills him; and taking his Lance, he turns himſelf againſt the other Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who made very gallant defence; but in little time the Valorous <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> ſlew the greater part of them; whereupon the reſt fled away wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and, as faſt as they could, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the Wood, amazed at the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty valour they beheld in him; and if they had been double or treble the number, I truly believe he would have conquer'd and kill'd them all. <hi>Olivaires</hi> having free'd himſelf of them, paid his gratitude to God; and riding forward, he ſpies a Spring as clear as Chryſtal, to which he makes, and alights from his Horſe to refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with its water, being extream thirſty and hot, and alſo to waſh ſome Ripples he had got in the Aſſaſſinates Aſſault; wherefore being intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe, his Horſe had ſtep by ſtep
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152282:43"/>wandered a good way off, and being now at liberty began to run and caper about, before <hi>Olivaires</hi> was aware; and with great haſte he goes with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to catch him, when out of the thick Wood came one of thoſe villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Highway-men, and prevents him, ſeizes on the Bridle, mounts him, and flies away with the Mail was faſtned to the Saddle-bow: What Mortal can imagine <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s grief at this Accident, finding himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his Horſe, and Jewels which were of great value! but his chief trouble of all was, that he could not go to the Tilting, being void of all hope, and means, both for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat and Attire.</p>
               <p>Whereupon he begins a Complaint able to rend the Rocks, and ſoften them into tenderneſs and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: O! was not my Mother's Death enough to ſatiate the ſpight of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune? was not enough my Father's Grief, was not enough the Affliction of my Kingdom? Not content to have
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152282:43"/>hurried me into infinite perils of life, when in the height of my deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my Loſſes, ſhe brings a Cloud over my little glimſing Joy, and dawning Happineſs. But thou, Lord, whoſe Eſſence is goodneſs it ſelf, reach forth unto me thy Right hand in this Wood; Let thy Sun diſpel my new darkneſs that ſurrounds me; and laying his Face on the ground in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for dying, after ſobs and tears he was ſilent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of a Cavalier that appears to</hi> Olivaires, <hi>and puts him into hope; and of ſome Covenants betwixt them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> being in ſo melancholly a Mood, a Cavalier came unto him, certainly a Meſſenger from God for his comfort, and with a loud voice call'd to him, O <hi>Olivaires</hi> of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> rouſe up, and hate me not for termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating thy Doubts; rouſe up, and ſleep not; whereupon he quickly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152282:44"/>raiſed his head, being ſurpriz'd to be called on by name, yet not reſolved whether to ſleep or awake, thinking it might be ſome Phantaſy which his Melancholy had preſented to his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination; but looking earneſtly, he was aſſured by his Aſpect, that it was ſome very honourable Knight; and obſerving the black Veſture on his back, he was the more aſtoniſhed; then ſigning himſelf with the Croſs, after the manner of the Chriſtians, he ſaid: I adjure thee by the Maker of the Heaven, and the Earth, and the Merits of his Son Jeſus, to tell me how thou cameſt by the knowledge of my Name, and whether thou art a Man, or a good Genius? Be not afraid of me, ſaid the Black Knight, for that I am a Chriſtian, and believe in God as thy ſelf; enquire not now why I have called on thee; it is enough that thou art heard as to the loſing thy Horſe, Jewels and Gold; and thy trouble (for not being able to go to the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament) hath penetrated where it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152282:44"/>will have the beſt relief; for thou haſt obliged me by many Kindneſſes, and ſignal received Services, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lo! I am ready to oblige you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in whatever ſhall be requiſite for the Turnament (for I will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge Benefits with Ingratitude); and in a word, thou ſhalt have every thing becoming a King not thy Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior. I am willing in recompence of thy courteſy, that thou ſhouldſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with me in all the Acquiſt that thou ſhalt procure by me; and thou ſhalt give me the half of all whatever thy Gains, when I demand it of thee; altho I will have liberty to take it to my ſelf, or leave it to thee. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> who had a burning deſire to be at the Tilting, hearing the Cavalier's Offer, without heeding the Conditions, or the Covenant, anſwered him after this manner: If my Fortune ſhall not diſſent from thy doing me ſo great pretended Service, of furniſhing me with Arms, Horſes, Attendants, and Money, ſo as ſhall be ſufficient for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152282:45"/>me; I ſwear to thee by the Power Omnipotent, and promiſe by the truſt which I put in him, that thou ſhalt ſhare in all the Reward, Gain, and Treaſure, by receiving the half, or more if thou deſire it, in caſe I ſhall be Victor at the Feaſt, and win the Day. The Knight accepted of it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Royal Paroll, and renew'd his Promiſe that he ſhould be ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſerved, and ſo furniſhed in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects for whatever might make him appear brave at the Turnament, as any Knight in the World could wiſh to be; and taking him by the hand, he led him into a Grove, where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhew'd a ſtrait path would carry him to a Sacred Hermit's Cell, he told him he muſt remain there till he could return with all neceſſary Proviſions for his purpoſe. O <hi>Olivaires,</hi> thy true Friend ſo aſſuring thee, willingly wait for him, who ſhall quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice thy heart; and <hi>Olivaires</hi> taking leave of him with much expreſſion of gratitude, went to the Hermitage,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152282:45"/>and the Knight vaniſh'd, and left him alone on the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>comes to the Hermit; and of ſome Diſcourſes betwixt them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE holy Hermit was at his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions when <hi>Olivaires</hi> knock'd at the Dore of his Cell; and being afraid, not any one for many years before having come at him, he would not open it; but when <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſaid he was a Chriſtian, and no Evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or Apparition, having firſt ſign'd himſelf with the ſign of the Croſs, he let him in, and led him to the Altar, there to worſhip his Saviour; then making him ſit down, the Hermit went and finiſhed his Devotions. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he brought him a red Earthen Diſh of dry'd Fruits, Bread and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, muſtering up for the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Valiant Knight all his forces, and bid him to take good heart, for that juſt now by Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152282:46"/>he had ſeen who he was, and the occaſion of his departure from his Kingdom, and how the Cavalier had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited him to his Cabin, and many other particulars the Holy Father told him. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> well ſatisfied of the ſanctity of the Perſonage, paid him exceeding great reverence, and praiſed Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God for his goodneſs unto him. The Hermit, after this, open'd to him the Sacred Law, and expounded it with much fervency of ſpirit, and gave him many good Inſtructions; then he made a Bed with Leaves and Straw for him to repoſe on, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him for God's ſake to take pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently this penance, for that 'twas neceſſary to paſs this miſerable Life with pain and ſorrow, having confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Lord, that after he had gone thorough the Waters of Miſery, and the Flames of Purgatory, God would place him in a Paradiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, and perfect Joys. And after he had given <hi>Olivaires</hi> his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, he left him to reſt. When the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152282:46"/>Morning was come, the Sacred Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit celebrated the Holy Maſs; and <hi>Olivaires</hi> having confeſs'd his Sins to the Reverend Father, received the Euchariſt with mighty devotion and contrition for his Faults. After, he continually inſtructed him in the Holy Scriptures; making it manifeſt unto him, that it was a good Spirit, who by the Grace of God had brought him thither; and continually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him, and exhorted him quietly to ſupport theſe his preſent Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and indure many other alſo which were to ſucceed them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>is overjoy'd, ſeeing come in his behalf, Men, Horſes and Arms.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> was four days in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the Aſſiſtance that was promiſed him; after which he begun to be a little moved, knowing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152282:47"/>that the laſt day before the Turnament was come, and he grew to be much afflicted at the delay of the Cavalier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if the Hermit had not aſſured him that he would not fail him, he had perhaps deſpair'd; wherefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberated often of going to <hi>London.</hi> He beheld from riſing ground (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he went to ſee if he could ſpy the Cavalier coming) many Horſes and armed Troops which were going to the Tilting, which vexed him to the very heart; and when at night he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into the Cell to the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he fell into an extream great paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and could eat nothing; ſo now the whole term was paſt, therefore <hi>Olivaires</hi> reſolved to go alone to Court, but the Hermit with much intreaty perſuaded him to ſtay till the next day; ſo that now all the days were paſt, and the hour of the Tilting was come; wherefore the valiant Knight deſpairing, went to prayer; and after he was beginning his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, lamenting his miſhap; but as
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152282:47"/>ſoon as he had opened the Hermitage Dore, and had ſcarce gone four ſteps forward, he heard a loud neighing of Horſes, and clink of Armour, and they ſeemed to draw near to the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitage; and preſently he ſaw ſix Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers advance before the reſt, all armed in bright Corſalets, and all the Horſes with Trappings, and covered with Black, but without Lance and Shields; after theſe followed ten other Cavaliers clothed in Black Velvet, and alſo all Furniture for Horſe; fifteen Pages likewiſe on fifteen beautiful Black Horſes came after, and fifty men on foot all in the ſame Sable Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; and the two firſt led by the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a ſprightly and wonderful finely ſhap'd Horſe covered and adorn'd with Black Trappings; and on his Saddle-bow he bore a gilded Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, garniſhed around with precious Stones, which enlight'ned the gloomy Grove, and every one carried ſome part of <hi>Olivaires</hi> Armour, which was made of the fineſt Metal, covered
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152282:48"/>with Damask work, and a Tuck of purer and better temper than ever Artiſt in the World wrought, Sword, Lances, Dagger, Shields, and Creſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Pleaſure and Tranſport</hi> Olivaires <hi>was in at ſuch Preparations; and of the Beauty of the King of</hi> England<hi>'s Daughter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Knights being habited af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, as you have heard, came up to the Hermitage, paying that Reverence which was agreeable to ſo great a King; quickly the Knight of the Grove, who had made him the Promiſe, as their Chief, alights from his Horſe, and embraces <hi>Olivaires,</hi> who remembring him, was exceedingly tranſported with joy, and was amazed at ſo pompous Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gave him infinite thanks: This Retinue that thou ſeeſt, ſaid the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152282:48"/>Knight, I have brought, that thou mayſt be well ſerved; and aſſure thy ſelf thou ſhalt want for nothing that in any kind may be requiſite for thee. I beg of you that you will behave your ſelf bravely, that we may not ſpend our Service and Fatigue in vain, and I will accompany you at the Tilting, give you your Lances, and ſpur on your Horſe; dear Sir, reply'd <hi>Olivaires,</hi> The kindneſs you ſhew me is not in the power of any Treaſure to reward, or make the leaſt ſuitable correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to; wherefore I look on my ſelf as bound to you by an eternal obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for I have great confidence in that Celeſtial Goodneſs who has deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered me from ſo many, and ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary dangers, that he will grant us the favour to obtain the glory of this Turnament: The Cavalier re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, God give you all that aſſiſtance and favour that I do heartily wiſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: But, continued he, the hour is now come, wherefore ſit down at the Table I have prepared, and take
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152282:49"/>repaſt, and after arm, and go for the Turnament. The Hermit, after he had given <hi>Olivaires</hi> his Benediction, left him, and went to his Devotions; and he being placed in a Golden Chair at a ſumptuous and Royal Table, did eat, and after (every hour ſeeming a thouſand years to him) was decked in his wonderful Armour, and mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Horſe, he marches away to the Court with his honourable and comely Train: Juſt at the very time that <hi>Olivaires</hi> was eating, and decking for the Turnament, <hi>Helena</hi> the King's Daughter was conducted out of the City to the Piazza prepared for the Tilting; ſhe was attended on by two hundred moſt beautiful young Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels richly adorn'd with Gold, and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious for Blood; and with theſe aſcending a Scaffold, covered all round about with the moſt rich and glorious Tiſſue and Broccade the World could afford, with Ornaments of Crimſon Velvet above and below, her Beauty created ſtupor in all Eyes that beheld
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152282:49"/>her: Under the Canopy, where her Seat was, Steps jetted out behind all of Maſſy Gold, and ſhe ſate on a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphal Chair of Elecorn garniſhed with Jewels and Carved Work of Gold, amounting to the value of a thouſand Cities: And for the ſhelter of the young Ladies of quality num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs Pavillions were erected, richly embroyder'd with great labour and art: Then as to the upper part of the Scaffold, or Canopy for a Heaven, it was all of Azure Velvet full of ſuch ſparkling precious Stones, that they out-brav'd the day, and appear'd like ſo many bright Stars of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Over the King's Daughter hung a Stone about the bigneſs of one's Fiſt of ſuch tranſcendant ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, that the moſt glorious Rays of the Sun could not drown its light, or eclipſe or diminiſh its luſtre: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Canopy, the Ornaments, and Pavillions, ſeemed to preſent one vaſt burning pure flame: But above all, the divine Eyes of the fair Daughter
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152282:50"/>of <hi>England</hi> ſhot ſcorching beams into the hearts of all that looked on her, and her moſt beautiful Shape and Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and celeſtial Dreſs, fetter'd up and ſtounded the Senſes of thoſe vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Cavaliers, who had prepared themſelves for ſuch a dazling Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle: The divine <hi>Helena</hi> then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken her place, with all the Ladies, four Judges of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the Kingdom, appeared forth, and having kiſſed the ground where her Foot trod, in a lower place they alſo ſat down; around on every ſide were Scaffolds and Stages all fill'd with Lords, Gentlemen, and Ladies, enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled both by Birth and Beauty; who all gave out with one conſent, and, as it were, one mouth, O thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Cavalier, who ſhalt by thy Valour gain for thy ſelf ſuch an ineſtimable Prize.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:152282:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the great Feats of</hi> Olivaires; <hi>and how much he ſurpaſt all the Juſters and Kings.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Olivaires</hi> had put on his Armour, and was all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for taking Horſe, he went to kiſs the holy Hermit's hand, beſeeching him that he would ſupplicate our Lord, that of his good favour he would grant him the Victory; and he promiſed him as much. Wherefore taking leave, and lacing on his Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, he begun his Journey, which was very ſhort. Arrived then at the Piazza, they found all the four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Knights prepared for the defence of the Turnament on one part; on the other, the King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the King of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Son, and many more well adorned, accouter'd, and fitted to give demonſtration of their great Valour and Proweſs; and at the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152282:51"/>ſound of the Trumpets divers Lances were broken; every one was amazed and ſtupify'd, looking on the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous unknown Black Knight, who expreſt in his Actions unordinary cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of Mind, and ſtrength of Body; who with mighty reſpect and moſt humble reverence bowed himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Heaven of Beauty, and alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on to his Feet to contemplate her; and being perfectly conquered by her Angelical Aſpect, he became almoſt forgetful of what he was about; and had it not been an Affair thus nearly relating to her, he had been intirely ſo. And now there had been a Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh; and the King of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Son had hitherto the better, and ſtood with his Lance in Reſt, expecting an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; when <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Knight, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Lance, cry'd; Lo, here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends the Victory! and reaches him it: The valiant and hardy Youth quickly took it, and went toward, where <hi>Maquenor</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about; and he expected him, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152282:51"/>turn'd oppoſite to him; whereupon they gave two brisk Encounters, and the great Cry was for the Valour of the King of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Son; but when they ſaw the movement and fierce blows of the Black Knight, their ſhouts pierced the Sky in applauſe of ſuch ſtupendious Courage. <hi>Maquenor</hi> broke his Lance upon <hi>Olivaires,</hi> who remain'd fixed as a Tower; but the puſh which the other received was ſuch, that it brought his Horſe to the ground, and he, as if he had flown, was caſt ten yards out of the Liſts; and preſently the Black Knight had another Lance given him, who run againſt a ſecond that expected him with couched Lance, a very ſtout and nimble Champion; but in Encounter <hi>Olivaires</hi> gave him ſuch a puſh, that the Cavalier's Horſe's Girths, Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, and Reins, all were burſt, ſo that by the blow he made the other Horſe recede, and in his flying back the valiant <hi>Olivaires</hi> Lance ſeated him on his Horſes Crupper, and quickly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152282:52"/>down he fell for dead on the ground; whence great amazement ſeized all the Court on account of the fierceneſs of the Black Knight, who never by any blow was put out of his Saddle, being ſtable and firm like a Rock a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Billows: Thus he acted in the whole Tilting; all whoever came againſt him he lay on the ground, and the laſt he combated with was the King of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Son, whom in like manner he ſhatter'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd by one of the briskeſt Thruſts that <hi>Olivaires</hi> ever made; for which the fair Virgin was much inamour'd of the Black Knight, and ſaid; If that Cavalier were as comely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Armour, as he does appear (and more ſo upon account of his Valour) in it, he would be the firſt and chiefeſt of the World. So, <hi>Olivaires,</hi> the firſt day's Victor, gallopt to and fro over the Field, now all his. The ſecond day he was to combat, after one Lance broken, with <hi>Faucheons;</hi> and the third day with Sword and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152282:52"/>Poynard: The firſt day then <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> was judged the Prince of all the Combatants, and he ſtayed on the Field till all the Knights were gone off: And as <hi>Helena</hi> was going away, <hi>Olivaires</hi> 'lighting from his Horſe, made his humble obeyſance, and then having mounted another admirable Steed, he performed ſuch handſome Feats, as might have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the braveſt King, the beſt Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and chiefeſt man at Arms in the World. <hi>Helena</hi> was delighted with the Valour, Gallantry, and Activeneſs of the Cavalier, and was much ſatisfy'd in her mind with him. The Judges affirmed that he was the Stupor of Chivalry, and the whole Court went off amazed at his Valour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:152282:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>returns to the Hermit; and his Retinue leave him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King and his Daughter, with the Lords and Ladies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Palace, ever diſcourſing of the valiant Black Knight; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one wiſhed to ſee him without Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, that they might paſs their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents on him, whether that would detract from his Comelineſs. It was the cuſtom, that after Supper all the Knights ſhould repair to Court, and with much complaſance and gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try dance with the Ladies; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many Lords came to ſee the Black Knight; and the King and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi> much deſired the ſame happineſs: But <hi>Olivaires,</hi> by advice of the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier who was his Conducter, did not go, but retired to the Hermit, where a moſt plentiful Supper was prepared, to refreſh him after ſo great toil, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152282:53"/>a good Bed to reſt his weary Limbs; and when he was got to this ſacred Lodging, and ſet down to Table, his whole Court and Attendance vaniſh'd. So <hi>Olivaires</hi> was left alone with the Hermit, to whom he related the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of that day, and told of the rich dreſs, and ſplendid appearance of the moſt beautiful <hi>Helena.</hi> After ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving prayed, and paid thanks unto God, he went to take his repoſe; the mean while that <hi>Olivaires</hi> was at the Hermitage, the King made all the Company ſit down in a large Hall, and entertain'd them with all ſorts of Muſical Inſtruments; but the little time ſeemed to every one of them an Eternity, whilſt they expected the Black Knight's Appearance at the Feaſt; ſo in Dancing they paſſed half of the Night: Then <hi>Helena</hi> ſeeing that the Black Cavalier would not be ſo kind as to make them happy with his preſence, cauſed Supper to be brought up, where was wonderful plenty of all ſorts of the richeſt Wines,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152282:54"/>Sweet-meats, and whatever Dainties and Good-cheer were requiſite for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up a moſt ſumptuous and unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell'd Feaſt; then ſhe retir'd with her Ladies to her Chamber, and the King and all the Knights went to reſt, and fit themſelves for the ſecond Day's Turnament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of</hi> Olivaires <hi>coming to the Turnament, and of the Dreſſes, and of his Victory.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NExt Morning, when day appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Olivaires</hi> riſe from his Bed, and went to prayers with the Hermit; and when the Devotions were over, he opened the Door, and ſaw his Knight coming towards him with a Veſture of Crimſon Velvet, which reached down to his Feet, and his Retinue clad in Red, with high mettl'd Steeds deck'd with Trappings of Cloth of Gold, with golden Bridles and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152282:54"/>of beaten Gold admirable to look upon; two Pages led by the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a moſt gallant and Warlike Horſe, Blood-ſpeckled, and on his Saddle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow he bore a Helmet much more beautiful and ſtrong than the former, and alſo other noble Armour which <hi>Olivaires</hi> in a trice was armed with: And having left the holy Father to the Divine Protection, they went to the Turnament; when they were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the Piazza, they found that <hi>Helena,</hi> with the King and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies had already got into their Seats to behold the Juſting, and give the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Victor. He, having firſt paid low reſpects unto them, began to gallop about, and make trial of his new-made Steed, and he appeared as if it had been the God of Battel deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from above to ſubdue the World: And after he had ſhew'd his dexterity in managing, leaping, and courſing his Horſe, he broke a ſtrong Lance againſt the ground, whoſe Splin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were burnt to Aſhes in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152282:55"/>of Fire, ſo far they flew aloft; every one became aſtoniſhed to ſee the Red Knight do ſuch amaſing things as he performed; yet known by all to be the ſame who the day before was Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor at the Tilting: Theſe admired Preludes being ended, the King of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Son enter'd the Liſts attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on by many armed Knights, the King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Britany,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Borbon,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> with an innumerable Company of luſty and honourable Cavaliers. All the Combatants and Maintainers of the Fray having enter'd the Field, 't was judged three thouſand had paſſed on either ſide; the Standard of Victory was defended by ſixty Knights; and he who would have the honour of that day was to take it by force after the Combating: All the Combatants had only one Lance apiece, and that being broken, they were with Fauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to determine the Victory. So from that part where the King was, proclamation was given. <hi>Olivaires,</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:152282:55"/>as Victor of the Field, took his Stand before the fair <hi>Helena,</hi> and raviſh'd with the ſplendor of her beauteous Eyes, as much as was ſufficient to continue him Victor, made a Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge with motion of his Lance to combat whatever Champion would come againſt him. Suddenly the Trumpet and Military Inſtruments began to ſound, which cauſed the higheſt Heavens to re-eccho: King <hi>Maquenor</hi> would be the firſt to make proof of his Lance, becauſe he hated <hi>Olivaires,</hi> for that he had got the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of him the day before; and ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on his Horſe, he came furiouſly up to ſmite him; but <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſtruck him into the Breaſt, and having paſt his Armour, ſtabb'd him to the Heart, ſo that down he falls dead on the ground; and alſo two other Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers came to incounter him in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd ſhining Armour; he dealt like haſty Death, or laid them wounded flat on the Plain; ſo the Fray was ſpread from one part to the other,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152282:56"/>and <hi>Olivaires</hi> appeared like a Lion among ſo many Herds, wounding and tearing Heads, Limbs, Bones, Fleſh and Nerves; diſmounting ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and breaking the Horſes Necks, or daſhing their Brains out againſt the ground by a rapid overthrowing them: And when it came afreſh into his mind, that for a divine Lady he was acting all this, it inſpir'd double ſtrength, and gave increaſe to his daring hardineſs: His Sword was dy'd red with Blood, and his Arm was bath to his Elbow, and his Gantlet was full of, and all ſteep'd in Blood; his blows were more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent at the latter end, than in the beginning of the Battel; he cours'd about the Field from one ſide to the other, ſmiting, and laying proſtrate all that offer'd to oppoſe him; ſo he made ſuch way before him by his Valour, that he could eaſily gain the Standard without Blood, all ſcamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away; wherefore with great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and fierce aſpect, he ſpurs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152282:56"/>and preſs'd into the midſt of the Sixty Knights, alone, without aid from any part; and laying hold on the ſhaft, wreſts it out of the hand of the ſtrongeſt man amongſt them: This brave Exploit did above all the reſt pleaſe the Judges, the King, and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena,</hi> who was troubled at ſo much Blood being ſhed upon her account; but with great difficulty he broke forth from the crowd of the Horſes and Men, holding faſt the Standard in his Hand, and well commanding his Horſe, and defending himſelf, and repulſing the Knights came on him to redeem their Honour; then not being able to make any defence, and ſeeing the Standard born away, all the Knights fled, and the Combatants, as worſted and overcome, retired. Now <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Knight came to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute him with all his Train, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd him, and gave him much joy and honour of his Conqueſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:152282:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After his Victory at the Turnament, the Valiant</hi> Olivaires <hi>returns to the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; and of</hi> Helena<hi>'s compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſlain and wounded Cavaliers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> was the laſt went out of the Piazza, for all the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers were gone to their Quarters, as was ſaid, and the Dead were carried forth to be buried; and <hi>Helena</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go away with the Judges and Ladies, <hi>Olivaires</hi> call'd for another Horſe, and having mounted him, he perform'd ſuch Feats, that the Judges thought him ſome infernal <hi>Daemon,</hi> and not a Man; and every one ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd how the Saddle could keep on, much more the Rider: Then ſaid the King, If the Turnament had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued three days longer, he would have extinguiſhed our whole State, and alſo thoſe of his Encounterers; and he had a very peculiar kindneſs for
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152282:57"/>him. He, ſtaying his Horſe, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend bow took leave, and then went off, and return'd to his Hermit; and his Cavalier vaniſh'd, and went to make proviſion for the next day: At Evening <hi>Helena</hi> had a mind to ſup with the King, and at Table began to ſay to him after this manner. My Soveraign and Father, whom above all things I love, ſtand in awe of, and venerate; I beſeech you that you would put a period to ſo great Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, and no further give leave that ſuch brave and honourable Cavaliers ſhould be ſlain as we have ſeen to day; wherefore if your Majeſty has any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for me, be pleaſed to end the Turnament, or ſo order it, that the Combatants may not die; for if I had imagined I ſhould have occaſion'd ſo much blood-ſhedding, I would rather have made a moſt ſolemn Vow never to have married; and, if it lay in my power, to hinder it, I would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any further Conteſt. The King very kindly thus return'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152282:58"/>Daughter, the true Retainer and Upholder of my Blood, do not think that I have paſt the time of this Feſtival, with its Appendages, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great trouble; and that the death of ſo many Knights and Kings does not yet continue to afflict me; but in ſuch Encounters it cannot be help'd; and it is cuſtomary and ordinary for them to be ſlain, as in all other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats 'tis wont to happen. However, to morrow I will ſo order it, that they ſhall not ſo eaſily hurt one another, and a ſafer way and method ſhall be given them; and this I do promiſe you upon my Royal Word. <hi>Helena</hi> with this took leave (the Repaſt end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) and retir'd with her Ladies into her Chamber, and would not ſtay the Ball, being a little indiſpos'd, and weary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:152282:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>is Victor at the Torney the third day; and is conducted by the King's Order, and by the Grandees of the Court is lookt upon as a wonder and prodigy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King the next morning had a deſire to know the number of the Slain, and the Qualities and Ranks both of the Cavaliers and Kings; and having known too much, he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly grieved; for on each ſide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite numbers were kill'd: Then he order'd ſome of his Kingdom and Court to ſucceed in the places of thoſe Champions who were wounded and dead; but if his Majeſty had been rightly ſenſible what duty he put them upon, he would rather have ſent them on any other Adventure than this, whither they would have gone with much greater alacrity and willingneſs; for the dread of <hi>Olivaires</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:152282:59"/>Blows ſtruck terror into the very gods, much more into Mortal Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: The hour being now come, and the Combatants marching up in their Ranks, as was the cuſtom, they order'd a Battel on foot; and <hi>Olivaires</hi> appear'd all in White in his upper Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, which was beautiful and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing; then ſuddenly procalamation was made, That every one ſhould alight from his Horſe, and lay down his Sword, and arm himſelf defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively as he pleaſed; and, for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Weapons, Arms were given to every one, ſuch as might not ſo eaſily kill; and every one that broke his Weapon, or chanc'd to fall, was to have no advantage taken of him; all this was ſo ordered for the Lady's ſake; and after that the Reward ſhould be render'd to the Victor; the Trumpets then ſounding, Flutes play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drums beating, the Combat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. <hi>Olivaires</hi> was quickly diſcover'd by his ſtrewing the ground with men, ſhattering of Helmets, tearing Coats
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152282:59"/>of Mail, crumbling Bracelets like bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Glaſs; and his Weapon was ſo hard labour'd, that it flew in pieces; wherefore a Knight thirſting for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, thought to have reach'd him a Blow not very ſoft; but <hi>Olivaires</hi> nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſlipt aſide, and the ſtroke hit upon the ground; but when he had got arm'd again, he quickly made a clear road through them all. The King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the other Kings, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, ſeeing that the Black, Red, and White Knight got all the Victory, five of them combin'd together, and all of them with the utmoſt effort of their ſtrength came up againſt him to kill him; but <hi>Olivaires</hi> obſerving their Fury, did with great hardineſs await them; and to the firſt he gave ſuch a blow, as made the reſt fly back, and him recoil as far as under the Scaffold where fair <hi>Helena</hi> ſat. The King ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Olivaires</hi> would have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them every one, ſo mightily was he enraged at their foul Play, quickly threw down the Baſton for concluding
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152282:60"/>the Turnament; and ſo the third Day's Combat ended to the great honour, and immortal fame of the White Knight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires, <hi>the Turnament ende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted into a Palace: And of various Accidents all tending to his Advantage and Honour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King order'd an hundred armed Lords to wait upon the Black, Red, and White Knight, at his coming out of the Piazza, who therefore were in expectation of <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires.</hi> Now when the Turnament was ended, he found himſelf alone, without his Knight, and without any Page, or Horſe, which marvelouſly ſurprized him; and, looking up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Heaven, he ſaid within himſelf: What anvantage is my Valour unto me? for what end do I expoſe my
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152282:60"/>Life? why was I born into this unhappy World? why, when on the pinnacle of my Honours, am I ſo harraſſed by, and made the mark of ſpightful Fortune? And being thus alone, he was going away for the Hermitage; but when he was near the Paſſage, out from the Piazza, he ſaw Knights who came toward him; at which he was ſurprized, and took it for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> King coming to aſſault him for the hatred he bore him for his mighty Proweſs; but he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to die without revenge; ſo, laying hold on his Sword, he boldly made up to them; but their Chieftain diſmounting, threw his Arms away; ſaying, That by the King's Order they came to ſhew their reſpect; and that his Majeſty deſired to reward him according to the merit of his Valour. <hi>Olivaires</hi> kindly received their Ambaſſage, and courteouſly anſwered, that he was intirely at their King's ſervice; ſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152282:61"/>was conducted by them into a moſt ſtately and glorious Palace, and by Noble Attendance was brought into a Chamber furniſhed and adorn'd for the entertainment of a King. <hi>Olivaires</hi> finding himſelf alone, was almoſt in deſpair, and grieved ſore on account of the Cavalier, who had relinquiſhed him in his greateſt neceſſity. What, ſaid he, muſt I appear in this Garb before <hi>Helena?</hi> Muſt I be preſented to ſo Auguſt a Monarch in ſo mean and forlorn a Condition? but no ſooner had he ſpoke this within himſelf, but his Cavalier came in with vaſt ſtore of rich Veſtures, Ornaments, Silver and Gold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:152282:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of</hi> Olivaires <hi>rich Veſtments his Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier gave him, Horſes, Pages, and other Attires of great Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Airy Cavalier brought with him twenty Squires with Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for him all of Damask and white Silk, and forty Pages with Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Furniture, and Gold: Two Black Slaves carried a Mail on their Shoulders with ten thouſand double Duckets of Silver, and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckets of Gold, with Jewels of more value than two hundred Shields: And the Knight ſaid to him, Theſe are all your Servants, and theſe Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are yours, and I will further add to them forty men loaden with all ſorts of Utenſils requiſite to furniſh a ſumptuous Houſe; and give theſe your Servants ſuch Places and Offices as you ſhall think fit. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your Promiſe, ſaid he, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152282:62"/>diſappear'd; great variety of Suits and Dreſſes he found, which much delighted him; and a wonderful Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per being prepared, he dofft his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and refreſhed himſelf; in that juncture came the hundred Knights to cheer him, and attend on him, by the King's Commandment; who after meat, ſtayed in the Hall expecting the Victor of the Turnament. Then <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> put on a Waſtcoat all richly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyder'd with Gold, and Stockings of fine Scarlet, curiouſly wrought by the hand of Art, with Shooes of Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Velvet, and then an upper Veſture of Cloth of Gold, with a Bonnet of Red Velvet, within which was a Jewel of the value of a Kingdom, with a Plume, according to the Royal faſhion of Carnation Feathers; and, having buckled on his Sword, he went down ſtairs for Court; where he found a delicate white Steed with a Saddle of Cloth of Gold, and Stirrops of Maſſy Gold, and for every thing elſe richly furniſhed. He had fifty Horſes in his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152282:62"/>Court admirably adorn'd; and he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mounted, they went to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; and every Page bore two Torches; wherefore the ſight of ſuch a beauteous approaching Court, with all the gay Retinue, ſeemed one of the braveſt pieces of Grandeur that ever eye beheld.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>being arrived at the Palace, is honourably received of the King, the Lords, and Ladies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>GReat concourſe there was to ſee <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and when they had taken thorough notice of him, they ſaid, Truly this Cavalier has all the Perfections and Graces can be deſir'd in a Prince; he was comely in Armour, yet more comely without it; in the one Dreſs he exhibited the air and mien of Valour, in the other of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; his Aſpect, Deportment, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152282:63"/>Preſence, declared him of the higheſt Extraction and Lineage in the World: The Ladies all haſt'ned to <hi>Helena,</hi> to tell her, they had never beheld a more comely Cavalier, and that they never expected to ſee a more lovely Youth. <hi>Helena</hi> diſcreetly kept ſecret her flames, neither could they diſcern by any diſcovery of her ſelf, whether this Character delighted her or no. <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> having enter'd the Royal Hall, was with great complacency received by the King; and all the Cavaliers paid him high reſpects; and though many there were who had bore him hatred out of envy to his Valour, yet when they look'd on his gracious Countenance, and heard his wiſe Diſcourſes, became his ſincere Friends as well as Admirers; the King, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken him by the hand, and made him ſit down by himſelf, talk'd of divers things with him, and with all <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s, whether Queſtions or Anſwers, was extremely ſatisfy'd. <hi>Helena</hi> put on Claoths which had never
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152282:63"/>been ſeen before, and richly adorned, and loaden'd with Precious Stones, and Oriental Pearls, (according as the King had commanded) ſhe came into the Hall; whoſe appearance ſhew'd like that of riſing <hi>Aurora</hi> with an infinite number of Stars about her; two hundred Ladies attended her, and a hundred Knights with golden Spurs marched before her; two Dutcheſſes bore up her Train, and two Dukes led her on each ſide: Surely if that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena,</hi> whoſe Beauty was ſo fatal to the <hi>Trojan</hi> State, had been by her, ſhe would have appear'd like <hi>Cynthia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the rays of the Sun. When ſhe was come into the midſt, the Dukes returned her Hands; then ſhe kiſſed her Father's Hand, and her Father took hers and gave it to <hi>Olivaires;</hi> who kneeling kiſſed it, and ſpoke very high Expreſſions to her, yet not Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which were not ungrateful only becauſe he ſaid them: So the one was fetter'd, and faſt Priſoner in <hi>Venus</hi>'s Tramels, and the other
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152282:64"/>was deep ſmitten with the Darts of <hi>Cupid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>has the firſt place by the King, for the love he bore him for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating, according to the judgment of the King, and the Overſeers of the Turnament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King taking <hi>Helena</hi> with the one hand, and <hi>Olivaires</hi> with the other, made them ſit down, placing himſelf betwixt them; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Muſick ſtruck up, and a brisk and gallant Dancing there was, but not long. After which, lo! the Judges of the Turnament coming to know of the King if they muſt give Sentence, and the reward to him moſt merited it; to whom he gave order to do ſo; then they retired, and went for the honourable Prize of the Tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: The mean while the King turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152282:64"/>to his Daughter <hi>Helena,</hi> ſpoke plainly enough to her; Who, dear Child, appeared to you the moſt Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous in this Combat? <hi>Helena</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, I minded them, Sir, all alike, and every one ſeemed to perform well. Underſtand, Governeſs of my Soul, ſaid the King, that the Preſent will quickly be brought, and given to him whom the Judges ſhall ſentence the moſt deſerving; and that he is alſo to be your Husband, and the Heir of the Kingdom: Wherefore I deſire to know how your Inclications are? Him whom your Majeſty ſhall think of, and whom your Royal Judgment ſhall moſt approve, and him (in ſhort) whom you ſhall name and recommend to me, I ſhall willing accept of for my Spouſe, Lord, and Guardian of my Life. If the Black, Red, and White Cavalier (ſubjoin'd the King) we ſhould make choice of for his Merits, would you be ſo ſatisfy'd; although we yet be ignorant who he is? If, my Sovereign and Father, the Judges
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152282:65"/>ſhall think him worthy of the Prize, to defraud him of it would be high injuſtice; however, your Majeſty's Will and Pleaſure ſhall intirely be mine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the words the King ſpoke, and the Reward that was given to</hi> Olivaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of other Dominions, with the Dukes, Princes, and Barons of their Realms, were ſet down, when the King order'd ſilence, and then thus ſaid: Signories, High Empires, States, and Kingdoms; preſently will the Judges and Lords be here with the Reward of the Turnament; and to whom my ſmall Preſent ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the ſame alſo ſhall eſpouſe my Daughter and only Child, and have all <hi>England</hi> for her Dowry; but I will that that Prince, Lord, or King, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152282:65"/>ſome time in my Court, that I may have experience of his Valour in all Exploits, and after underſtand his Lineage and Deſcent, and then may he enjoy the Crown. Let now then the Prize be brought and adjudged to him who got the greateſt Honour, and was Victor of the Turnament. Firſt came 30 Pages with lighted Torches in their hands, and after 30 moſt noble Cavaliers; then followed 10 Pages in gold Embroidery, with Torches alſo, in midſt of which were 6 Knights clad in Cloth of Gold, and in the midſt of them a Duke all in Armour, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a golden Baſon, and in it a Neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chain of Gold, interwoven with Jewels, and ſo wonderfully wrought, that the very ſight of it alone was a tranſport for all Humane kind; and it might be ſaid to have been one of the Wonders of the World; nor could the value of thoſe Jewels be eſtimated; and after followed the Judges with an infinite number of Knights and Gentlemen; and, being ſo placed that every one
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152282:66"/>might conveniently be a Spectator, they came before the King ſpeaking to this effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The rich Neck-chain is given to the Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> Olivaires, <hi>at which many of the Kings are filled with diſdain, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to them that an unknown Knight was not worthy of ſuch a Preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>MAY it pleaſe your Majeſty, Dread Sovereign, we were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by your Majeſty to be Judges for the Victor at Tilting, and at the Combats on Horſeback, and on foot; which Province we willingly accepted of, and have diligently obſerved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our skill, the Blows, the Hardineſs, the Valour and Force of every King, Duke, Prince, and Lord, and we freely give witneſs that every one of them has made honourable
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152282:66"/>proof of right Chivalry; but, to our thinking, the Flower of all, and he who has merited your Majeſty's peculiar Favour and Preſent, is that Cavalier who was clad the firſt day in Black, the ſecond in Red, and the third in White; which valorous Knight is the ſame that ſits by your Majeſty, the deſervedly deſigned Heir of your Kingdom; and although we be ignorant of his Country, and Name, yet we are aſcertain'd he is come of a Royal Race, and has Illuſtrious Blood in his Veins, becauſe ſuch kind of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour does not lodge in any other Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, ſave thoſe who by ſuch Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction can appear thus worthy of a Crown; wherefore, with your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's leave, and good liking, we will preſent the Gift to him: The King being well contented, made ſign to them to do ſo; the Duke then turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> took the Chain and put it about his Neck, ſaying unto him, Your Valour which has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered ſo many Couragious Knights,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152282:67"/>adorns you with this Gift, a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and, when his Majeſty ſhall think convenient time, you are to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe <hi>Helena,</hi> his only Daughter, and be crown'd King of the Realm: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, reply'd <hi>Olivaires,</hi> I do not ſeem to my ſelf to have done any thing to merit this; but ſince it is the King's Bounty, I am very well pleaſed. So he accepted of the Preſent and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; and bowing low to the King, and <hi>Helena,</hi> in a moſt eloquent Speech he returned them large thanks for their Liberality. And to the Judges, and to the whole Hall, he alſo gave infinite Thanks; and 'twas judged by all that heard him, that he was the fineſt Courtier of the World; and every one conſidering his comely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Aſpect, his Martial Valour, Boon Grace, Deportment, Mein, and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, even wept for very joy; the King taking him by the Hand, and kiſſing his Forehead, ſet him in his place again; then a thouſand Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152282:67"/>began again to play, making infinite delight and feſtivity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Cavalier who was</hi> Olivaires <hi>ſo great Friend, and furniſhed him with Arms at the Juſting, appears in a Dream to</hi> Helena, <hi>and of a Viſion the King had.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE morning after, about break of day, the King had this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. He dream'd he ſaw <hi>Olivaires</hi> crown'd King of his Realm, and that he had given him his Daughter; then he beheld another Crown come over his Head, and ſettle upon that, much greater than the former he had given him, and it doubled his Court, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and Riches; and it appeared to him ſo Auguſt, that he himſelf bow'd to it: Therefore, ſeeing Fortune had been ſo extraordinary kind unto him, to ſend him ſuch a Cavalier for his Son,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152282:68"/>he was mightily overjoy'd, and the tranſport awak'd him; and revolving this Viſion in his mind, he was ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining with himſelf what it might ſignify: And muſing earneſtly, he fell aſleep again; and other Kings ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to come upon him with deſign to take that Crown from off his head, ſaying, It was not fit he ſhould wear two Crowns; but he being moved at their Preſumption, ſeemed by force to bind their Hands behind them, and to take the Crown off the Head of every one of them; to whom, after they had humbled themſelves unto him, <hi>Olivaires</hi> gave every one their own again; and at this he awaken'd. The King did admire at the Viſion, and aſſur'd himſelf 'twas a Divine one, and no natural play of Fancy, and happy Myſtery in it; ſo he treaſur'd it up in his memory, and was fill'd with great joy. When the Morning was further advanc'd, he went to viſit his Daughter <hi>Helena,</hi> whom he found more than ordinary pleaſant, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152282:68"/>and inquiring the occaſion of it, ſhe ſaid ſhe had had about break of day a moſt pleaſing Dream, which was, That ſhe ſeemed to be walking in a Garden of fine Flowers; whence were many gay delightful and odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous ones, caſt as if they had flown into her Boſom, and Lap; and that a Cavalier, whom ſhe knew not, clad all in white, pluck'd one, and gave it into her Hand; that ſmelling to it, ſhe thought ſhe never ſcented a more raviſhing flavour; and having a mind to put it into her Boſom, it turn'd to a Ring, the moſt curious one that ever ſhe beheld; and the Cavalier va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, with telling her that was the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King's: Whereupon ſhe awak'd out of her ſleep, and found the Ring in truth in her hand, and ſhe ſhewed it to her Father; the King being ſtupify'd at ſo amazing a thing, ſaid, Certainly ſome grand Effect will follow upon our new Alliance; and taking it into his hand, he was more aſtoniſhed ſtill, knowing it to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152282:69"/>be of ineſtimable value; and ſaid, that a more precious thing he never ſaw. She ſubjoin'd, The Cavalier who gave it me, ſaid that it was a King's, but I cannot remember the reſt, I was ſo over-maſter'd with tranſport that moment; the King with her leave put it on his Finger, and injoin'd her to ſpeak nothing at all of it, and parted from her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:152282:69"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How</hi> Olivaires <hi>ſeeing the Ring on the King's Finger, knew it to be his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's, and marvelled extreamly; but for that it was not known, he made as if he ſaw it not, and was ignorant of the Matter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King being at Table, and having the Ring on his Finger, every one caſt their Eyes upon it; for that, from the Stone was in it, iſſued out Rays ſo bright, that they reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled a Flame; ſo that the ſight could not long ſuſtain the dazzle. When <hi>Olivaries</hi> ſaw it, he quickly knew it to be his Fathers; and often dubious in his Mind, and revolving things to and fro, he at laſt concluded to be ſilent. The King enter'd into various Diſcourſes with <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive manner enquired after his Name and Blood; who replied my Name is <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and for my Blood
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152282:70"/>it is as noble as your Majeſty ſhall pleaſe to make it. The King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded no further for that time; and was well ſatisfy'd, and ſo likewiſe was <hi>Helena.</hi> The King ſought not after his Nation, for his Speech ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly enough declared that. After Dinner the King of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the King of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Son, and other Dukes, Lords, Counts and Knights, came to take leave of the King: And kindly embracing every one of them, he made them many Royal Preſents; and doing them the Honour to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them a little way, he diſmiſs'd them. When theſe Potentates were gone, they enter'd into a Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Oath, to bring a vaſt Army againſt <hi>England</hi> to deſtroy it; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King had put an affront on their Crowns, in preferring before them an unknown Knight. Alſo they further diſcours'd, among themſelves, whence <hi>Olivaires</hi> might have ſuch honorable Attendance, with Cloaths, Arms, Horſes and Pages. One ſaid
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152282:70"/>he was the King of <hi>England</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe; other, that he was a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cavalier, whom Love had drawn thither, which they judg'd by his Speech, and for that his Dreſs and Garb were after the Faſhion of that Province; other, that the King by Art Magic had made him proſtrate, and kill without any their ill Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherefore they were all una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly reſolved to have Revenge, taking to Heart the Death of ſo many of their Cavaliers: And with this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition they returned to their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, States, and Kingdoms.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King of</hi> England <hi>ſends ſecretly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diverſe parts of his Kingdom, for the interpretation of his Dream, and he has it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Dream was interpreted after this manner, That the King that ſhould by him be Crown'd
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152282:71"/>King of the Realm, ſhould alſo be King of another, and wear a greater Crown than his, and that he ſhould pay him Reverence. Then the Second Dream ſignify'd, That thoſe other Kings would attempt to extort from him the Realm of <hi>England;</hi> that the Second Crown would take away their State and Kingdom; and after cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly reſtore them again. His Daughter's Dream was likewiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, That ſhe ſhould be eſpous'd to a King, the Son, as it were, among other Princes, as that Ring intimated; and if ſhe could tell from what part the Ring came, the King of that State ſhould be her Husband. By the White Cavalier, who gave the Ring, could be underſtood no other than that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, who was Victor at the Turna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was clad the third Day in White, and who would give her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Ring. The King was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the interpretation, and kept it ſecret in his Breaſt; and the rather, becauſe the Effects of all would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152282:71"/>appear, as he was aſſured by thoſe who opened to him the Viſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A ſad Accident befalling</hi> Olivaires, <hi>who was brought to himſelf only by the means of</hi> Helena.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> having remained ſome time in the Court, and being in continual expectation of the King's Promiſe, that he would give him the fair <hi>Helena</hi> to Wife, paſs'd Nights and Days in imagining to himſelf the Hour, the Moment, the Manner, the Joy, and his intire Happineſs. But yet for all his ruminating, he could not ſee any effect anſwer his Thoughts, nor could perceive any act or ſign of Love expreſs'd to him; ſo that on the other hand, he was afflicted and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented inceſſantly, and could get no reſt nor comfort. At length a violent amorous Accident befel him: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a deep and fixed Muſing, in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152282:72"/>Preſence of the King, with many No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, he fainted, and fell down as dead. Whereupon he was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately carried to his Chamber, and the Phyſicians were brought, and many Remedies prepared; but they could not with any recover him out of his Swoon. This dire Accident of <hi>Olivaires</hi> came to <hi>Helena</hi>'s Ear; and ſhe, as knowing his Malady, and who ſecretly loved him, with various con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, and great caution, convey'd her ſelf where her <hi>Olivaires</hi> lay in this <hi>Deliquium,</hi> and calling loud to him, for ſhe would try all means; ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached near unto him, and laid her hand upon his Forehead; which he begun to be ſenſible of, and look'd up as one awak'd out of ſleep. And truly, I think, he would never have come to himſelf and life again, had not <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi>'s Spirits revived his, whoſe very touch did emit enough to cure him. Wherefore being recover'd of this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, he was very thankful to the King and <hi>Helena,</hi> for the care they
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152282:72"/>had taken of him: And leaving him to reſt, the King and <hi>Helena</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. At Night, in the beginning of her ſleep, the White Cavalier appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Helena,</hi> and begg'd of her to tamper with the King to give her to <hi>Olivaires</hi> for his Conſort, in as much as ſhe would have for a Husband the braveſt Hero in the World; telling her, that for this cauſe, he had given her the Ring, which quickly ſhe ſhould ſee on <hi>Olivaires</hi> Hand: And ſo vaniſh'd. <hi>Helena,</hi> keeping the Viſion in her Mind, in the Morning deck'd her ſelf in the richeſt Cloaths and Dreſſes that ſhe had, and deſign'd to reveal the Matter to the King her Father, in the preſence of <hi>Olivaires.</hi> So ſhe procured of the King to go and dine with <hi>Olivaires</hi> in his Chamber, who after invited him to come and eat with him. Thus having got her End; as they were at Table many pleaſant Diſcourſes paſſed between them. At length, in the height of the King's Mirth, two Couriers came
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152282:73"/>to interrupt it, accompanying ſome Ambaſſadors from the Kings of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Speech.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Challenge made by the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Kings to the King of</hi> England; <hi>and the King's Anſwer, and that of</hi> Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter they had pay'd their due Obeiſance to the King, they made a ſurpriſing Oration of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives their Sovereigns had to wage War againſt his Majeſty. And after this manner was their Speech, That Great Sovereign of Sovereigns, the all Wiſe Creator of Heaven and Earth, protect and proſper the Potent Kings of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who challenge to battel the ſacred Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and ſay you are not worthy of it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are prepared to take from
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152282:73"/>you your State and Kingdom, and will come with Arms to ſhed your Blood, and with Fire to deſtroy your Palaces: And thus much I am Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned to ſay of my Sovereigns the Kings of <hi>Ireland,</hi> worthy of all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Empire. When the King of <hi>England</hi> had heard theſe proud Words, conſcious of his Innocency, and the good will he always bore their Royal Majeſties, he took it in ſo high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that it ſtopt his Speech, that he could not get a word out. And ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly he call'd to mind his Dream, and the interpretation of it; and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Eyes this way, and that way, on his Nobles, Dukes, and Knights, and ſeeing none anſwer any thing, or ſay a word, nor himſelf being able to ſpeak as he had a deſire, he riſes on his Feet, with intention to commit the task to <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and, at the ſame time make him eſpouſe his Daughter. Upon which <hi>Olivaires,</hi> riſing from his Seat, ſpoke theſe words: Puiſſant Prince, with all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152282:74"/>and Humility, I beg of your ſacred Majeſty to do me the favour, to let me be the Man who ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn anſwer to the Ambaſſadors of the unworthy Kings of <hi>Ireland.</hi> At this the King ſpies his Ring on <hi>Olivaire</hi>'s Finger, and much marvelled: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the anſwer the King gave him was, Thou art my Son. And taking <hi>Helena</hi>'s hand and his, and joyning 'em together, he ſaid, This is your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort; and in token thereof he kiſs'd them both, and made him kiſs <hi>Helena;</hi> which fill'd all the Court with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Joy; and they were much delighted to hear the News of a War. Now, ſaid the King to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> Take upon you to give anſwer, and to fight for, and defend your Kingdom. <hi>Olivaires</hi> after he had apply'd himſelf to the King, and ſpoke what he thought ſuitable on ſuch an occaſion; turn'd to the Ambaſſadors, and ſaid, Tell your Maſters that <hi>Olivaires</hi> of <hi>Caſtile</hi> (the humbleſt of the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Servants) and legitimate
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:152282:74"/>King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Crown'd Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> will come and make them ſenſible of the Error they are in, and give them cauſe to repent of their Inſolence. When the King and <hi>Helena</hi> underſtood that <hi>Olivaires</hi> was the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> they were ſo filled with Amazement and Joy, as the like was never heard, or can be conceiv'd. Wherefore they began to entertain for him a vaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; and the whole Court for this great News was tranſported, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed, and looked big.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XL.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The departure of the Ambaſſadors; and what</hi> Olivaires <hi>ſaid to them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> did much Compliment and Careſs the Ambaſſadors, and retain'd them a Day longer than they deſign'd to ſtay: Then ſpoke thus to them at their departure; Our
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152282:75"/>moſt Chriſtian Sovereign and Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Father has been pleaſed of his bounteous Goodneſs to accompliſh his Promiſe upon me. Therefore acquaint your Maſters how I have ſworn not to return back from this Enterprize to my Father's Court, until I have taken from them all their Cities, and made every one of them Priſoners; to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the World what Tyrants they are, and Uſurpers of their unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Thrones: So, having preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'em with fine Horſes, he diſmiſſed them. <hi>Olivaires</hi> had made plain diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of himſelf to the King; and <hi>Helena</hi> had underſtood a great part of his Secrets, and had ſeen the Viſions were come to paſs, and that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Ring was clearly apparent. Wherefore the King judging by what had already happened, alſo of that which was to come, and hopefully foreſeeing all would proſperouſly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, ordered a mighty Army to be made ready, of more than Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152282:75"/>well armed Horſemen, and bravely mounted; and Infantry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, with Pikes, Javelins, and other Weapons ſuitable to thoſe times; and made <hi>Olivaires</hi> Generaliſſimo of all. Who having accepted of ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Preferment and Command, ſaid, I do not intend, till I return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to make <hi>Helena</hi> may Wife; till by my Valour in Exploits at Arms I may, in ſome degree, have ſhown my ſelf not altogether unworthy of her Favour. The Affection <hi>Helena</hi> bore <hi>Olivaires</hi> was ſo great, that his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was death to her; the ſeparation of him, the Soul, from her the Body. But being well aſſured of his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſhe bore her Grief moderately, through good hopes of Conqueſt; and comforted her ſelf with the Viſions. In few Days he, with his well-arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Forces, were on their march: And the Kings were arrived for the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>England</hi> with a vaſt Army, Valorous and Strong; ſo they went on ruinating and burning the Villages,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152282:76"/>and ravaging the Countrey. At <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaire</hi>'s departure, his Spouſe, <hi>Helena,</hi> put a rich Necklace about his Arm, which ſhe had always worn about her Neck; and for his Neck making alſo Ornaments. She utter'd theſe Votes, May he who delivered <hi>Jonas</hi> from out of the Deep, of his Mercy and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs preſerve my noble Spouſe, and worthy of univerſal Reign, <hi>Olivaires,</hi> in all Perils which may happen unto him; and may he be pleaſed to give him Victory, as he did to <hi>David</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Giant <hi>Goliah.</hi> Then ſhe embracing, kiſſed him; and alſo the King embraced him, and with the bleſſing of God he left the Palace, and went to his Army.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:152282:76"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Battel</hi> Olivaires <hi>had with the Kings of</hi> Ireland; <hi>and of their Army.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings were incamped round a City containing Ten thouſand Families; and in five Days journey <hi>Olivaires</hi> arrived within half a League of them; and Marſhalling his Army in right order, he made them to underſtand he was come to give them Battel. The Sight and Preſence of <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſtruck mighty Terror into the Kings; nor did they think of ſo ſudden Engagement: Wherefore they raiſed the Siege from before the Town, and drew out their Camp into more convenient Method for fight. <hi>Olivaires</hi> had got good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of the Enemy's Forces, was informed of their Number, which a third part exceeded his; knew the places of the Countrey the Enemy
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152282:77"/>might fly to, and ſave themſelves. Wherefore having accommodated and provided every thing, and given all his Soldiers Arms, and ranked 'em in fit poſture for Combat, he made unto them this ſhort Oration; Valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Lords, worthy Knights, my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Companions, I believe you are well ſatisfi'd of the good Nature of our Sovereign, the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> my Father, and King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> my Father, and of the great Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality he hath expreſſed toward you in Gifts, Preſents, and fair Promiſes: And, I believe, that you have a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage lodged in your Breaſts ready to requite, as much as you are capable, what he has deſerved of you. But this I am moſt ſure of, as a ſhining Truth, that the Glory of an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Death, is far rather to be elected than the living with more eaſe (and perhaps not ſo, even to the moſt faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted) under the brand of Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and conſequently the diſgrace of Scorn and Affronts. This Day there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore offers a fair Opportunity to make
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152282:77"/>honourable Proof of our Valours, and to dilate the Soul of our King, to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſtill greater Kindneſs and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (if it be poſſible) for us all. And I can plainly behold in all your looks Hardineſs, and a riſing Courage, and a longing after Battel and Fame, and for the rendering more honourable and noble your Blood. Summon up then all your Strength and Vigour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract them into a ſtout Heart, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel out of your Dominions ſuch arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, haughty and proud Invaders, and ſpread abroad their Infamy and Diſgrace, whilſt you procure to your ſelves a happy Memory, and leave the inheritance of a valorous Name upon your Families; and whoſoever is of another temper, is a reproach and ſhame to his native Countrey. Here they all with one conſent cry'd aloud, We are ready to undergo a thouſand Deaths for our King, for your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and for our own Honour, and we will follow you whereſoever you ſhall lead; and we will give ſuch demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152282:78"/>both of our Fidelity and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as to make you plainly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how much we think our ſelves engaged to our Sovereign, and how mindful we are of our Allegiance. <hi>Olivaires</hi> having drawn out his Men, divided them into three Parts; on the right Wing he ſet 3000 Horſe, and 4000 Foot, under the Command of <hi>Edward</hi> the noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cavalier; on the left he gave to <hi>Robert,</hi> his Lieutenant, the Command of 6000. Horſe, and 2000 Foot; ordering him not to aſſault the Enemy's Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Edward</hi> had joyn'd his Battalions. In the Night, with all the ſilence poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, he approach'd the Camp; and in the Morning he bid the Drums beat, and the Trumpets ſound; and heading the main Body himſelf, he gave the Adverſary Battel. The firſt that advanced to encounter <hi>Olivaires,</hi> was a fierce <hi>Iriſh</hi> Captain, Stout and Gallant; and engaging with him, two ſuch grand Blows were given, that the very Earth ſhook; both their
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152282:78"/>Horſes fell, and their thick Launces were broken into a thouſand ſplinters. <hi>Olivaires</hi> quickly, without any harm received, roſe up on his Feet: But the diſmay'd Captain, with a piece of Launce ſticking in his Breaſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd on the ground half dead. And ſuddenly did begin a ſharp and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fight, every one valiantly labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sword, and ſlaſhing round about him; mean time <hi>Edward</hi> on the right Wing made but a bad Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it: Whereupon he begun to ſquare his Ranks. And they of the City beholding an Army favourable to 'em, did great damage to their Reer, putting them in mighty Confuſion. This Aſſault being made in little time, <hi>Robert,</hi> during it, was in the Flank; and ſo violent was the Onſet, and ſo briskly did they bear up to them, that the Enemy conſtrained by <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Valour (who having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted like a Lion, made a vaſt Shammels) and freſh Aſſiſtances coming in from all Parts, being able
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152282:79"/>to make ſmall Oppoſition to their Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, fled: Whereupon the Kings ran to catch their Bridles; and having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a Port, enter'd a Ship for ſail. Great was the Mortality of that day's Action; about Four thouſand <hi>Engliſh</hi> having been ſlain; and, we may ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to affirm it, near Twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> King's Forces. So <hi>Olivaires,</hi> after Victory, diſpos'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to reſettle the Army, to take care of the Wounded, to bury the Dead, and to celebrate with Encomiums and Triumphs the valorous Deceaſed; acknowledging himſelf eternally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to the Living, for their admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Fortitude and Courage, and, in a word, for the Victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:152282:79"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the News which the King receiv'd of the Victory; and of</hi> Olivaires, <hi>who reſolves to purſue the Enemy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>COuriers were quickly diſpatch'd away to Court, with <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Letters, ſignifying the Victory unto the King; and having in a ſhort time arrived at the Palace, and the News preſented, the City and Kingdom were fill'd with great rejoycing; and with Bonefires, Feaſts, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, they gave mighty demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their gladneſs. <hi>Helena</hi> was much comforted, and a thouſand times read over her dear <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Letter, whom ſhe lodged in her heart day and night: And another thouſand by day diſcours'd with her Father of him in that reſpectful and decent manner as was agreeable, repeating to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Dreams, and had great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction betwixt themſelves. On
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152282:80"/>the other part, <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſeemed not to himſelf to have performed any thing in putting the Enemy to flight, and was reſolved to make a total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of, and perfect conqueſt over them. Wherefore, conſidering the ſlaughter he had made among them, he perceived they could not readily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit their Army, fortify their Cities, act defenſively and offenſively, and ſo he reſolved to follow them: His Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers therefore being refreſhed, he caus'd them with quick diſpatch to make a great many Ships; and having ſet his Army all in Order in a large Campaign, he went on Horſeback into the midſt of 'em, and thus ſpake: Moſt Noble Cavaliers, Valiant Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, my Brethren and Friends! I think my ſelf very happy for having been Spectator of your Valours, and that the Enemy has felt your hands, how rough they are, and for this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge kind Stars have ſhed their benign influence on me: But ah! what have we done in baniſhing them
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152282:80"/>out of our Territories? We muſt expel them their own; if it be a right Victory, there will be ſeen our Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſance in ſuch an enterprize; there will your Hardineſs, Valour, and Vertue appear. Are you pleaſed, Brethren and dear Friends, that we purſue them, and baniſh them out of their own Dominions? Are you pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that we ſhould revenge our ſelves on ſo great an Affront? their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to have driven us from our State, will it not be a juſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to expel them theirs, to take from them their Kingdoms, their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Life? Whom would you have to take vengeance for this Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offer'd? if we our ſelves have not reſentment enough to do it, how can you imagine our Poſterity ſhould have a warmth for it? Our Sovereign the King, ſeeing our brave and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Courage, will know how much we are the loving Children of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Country, and will be very grateful to, and abundantly reward
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152282:81"/>us. Which of you, my Lords, Knights, and Brethren, will follow me in this Enterprize, for gaining that which indeed hitherto we have not obtained? Then all with one voice anſwer'd they would follow him, and would lay down a thouſand lives for the Crown of their Sovereign. <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſeeing their willingneſs, gave them many thanks, and told them, that by this Adventure they ſhould ſurprize and come upon the Kings unawares; and that he feared not by their Fortitude and Valour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o acquire a glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:152282:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>leaves</hi> England, <hi>and enters the Dominions of the Kings of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and lays ſiege to a ſtrong City; and of his other Sieges and Fights.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Ships and every thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fitted, and all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever were needful, in readineſs, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Tents and Pavilions for the Camp, the next morning <hi>Olivaires</hi> departed, and imbarqu'd his whole Army; wherefore with a proſperous Gale he arrived in few days at an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Port, and got on Land ſooner than he could have expected: A fair Town ſtood upon the Haven compaſſed with Walls; and when the Inhabitants perceived that ſuch an Armado was coming upon them, they ſhut and barr'd their Gates, and put themſelves in poſture of defence; but quickly was the Town taken, and they put to the Sword; the ſame did <hi>Olivaires</hi> to two more, as alſo to a third, all large
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152282:82"/>Towns; ſo that he ſtruck fear into the hearts of all the Country, and many Cities ſurrendered themſelves without reſiſtance; and many of the Kingdom beholding the brave Valour of <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and contracting a love for him, went over to his ſide, and fought againſt their own Sovereigns. <hi>Olivaires</hi> in his march came unto a ſtrongly fortifi'd Paſs, where 'twas neceſſary for him to take a ſtrong and well-garriſon'd City, in which was the Son of the King who was kill'd at the Turnament; therefore he lay ſiege round it, and gave it a brisk Aſſault, but could not conquer it; and many were ſlain on both ſides: Mean while News flew all over the Kingdom, and came to the Ear of the Kings, that <hi>Olivaires</hi> was come, to the great damage of their Crowns; and that he had taken many places, that he would alſo take this City: Therefore giving order inſtantly for refitting the Soldiery, Foot and Horſe, and marching away with thoſe they
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152282:82"/>had in readineſs, the Kings went to relieve the City, and engage with the Enemy. <hi>Olivaires</hi> having put his Army in good poſture, and ordered his Battalions in his Campaign, expected the Adverſary's Aſſault, being well prepared, in right method, and full of courage; 'twas in the morning when the Kings came upon them, and now the Armies confront each other; ſo the Drums beat, and to Arms. <hi>Olivaires</hi> confiding in God's Aſſiſtance, and alſo in derived Valour, thought fit to preſent himſelf before them, and to challenge the Kings to ſingle Combat one after another; judging it moſt certain, that after he had defeated their Chiefs, 'twould be eaſie to give a great blow to their vaſt Army with his little One. So he commanded 'em to leave off pitching their Tents; and when he had fought one or two of the Kings, the Army moved to engage the Enemy; and taking a ſtrong Launce, and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, he expoſed himſelf to publick
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152282:83"/>view. One of the Kings more fool-hardy than truly valorous, yet in his own Conceit ſtouter than the reſt, haſtily mounted his Horſe, and with his Launce on his Thigh went to meet <hi>Olivaires</hi> turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; and in the ſtrokes they gave each other, the King received a ſharp blow, whereby both Man and Horſe were caſt to the ground; ſo he was quickly taken Priſoner. Then a ſecond King ſuddenly aſſaulted <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> and he was laid wounded on the ground. And now a cruel Battel was joyn'd; and for divers Hours the mad conteſt laſted. <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſeemed ſo many Thunderbolts, which terrifi'd and ſtruck down the Enemy: And <hi>Olivaires</hi> by his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtrength, made a wide lane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, infuſing Courage into his Soldiers, reducing them into Order; and running about here and there, as was need. The Noon time of Day being paſt, and the Armies being wearied, the Kings betook themſelves
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152282:83"/>to flight, ſeeing <hi>Olivaires</hi> making a large Shammels of their Army: So they gave their Horſes the Reins, and Routed and Conquered, and with all ſpeed fled away. All the Field run with Blood, and all the Victor's Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were ſmeared with humane Gore: So the one Party fled, and the other withdrew; and Night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, the Battel ceaſed. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> before he would ſleep, cauſed the Wounded to be taken care of; and put in Order the remainder of his Soldiers, and made them refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and take ſome repoſe. After, having bid the Trumpet ſound, he ſaid, Invincible Cavaliers, now is the time to compleat the Victory, and purſue the Foe, who unexpectedly flies before us: Therefore whoever among you either loveth Me, or is ſolicitous of his own Honour, let him follow Me. And ſo early in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he came upon the timerous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and having dexterouſly drawn his to a head, he entered among 'em;
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152282:84"/>ever as he went on encouraging his Forces. Whereupon the Kings and their Army being ſurpriſed at the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſounding of the Trumpet, were mightily afraid: And thoſe fighting Manfully, and theſe defending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Cowardly, they were almoſt all ſlain and diſcomfited. But the Kings being made Priſoners, and ſome principal Perſons beſides, remained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. Thus they became Maſters of their State and Kingdom; wherein much Treaſure was found; but all was diſtributed among the Soldiers; for <hi>Olivaires,</hi> like a noble General, kept nothing to himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The other King being in a ſtrong City, the ſame is beſieged by</hi> Olivaires, <hi>and ſurrenders to his Favor and Mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Army having taken ſome repoſe, and being refreſh'd and enliven'd, <hi>Olivaires</hi> gave Order to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152282:84"/>pitch their Tents and Pavilions round the City, wherein was that other King with many Guards. So put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fire to the Gates, ſcaling the Walls, making Engines of portable Wood to annoy thoſe which were within, they made aſſault againſt it for two Days, and on the third took it, putting all to the Sword that had not yielded themſelves up to them. <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſuddenly commanded a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, That the Churches and the Ladies they ſhould not violate or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order; which accordingly was obey'd. The King, when he ſaw the City ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his Captains ſlain, and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, retired into a ſtrongly fortify'd Caſtle, and ſeemingly inexpugnable. But the indefatigable diligence of <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> and couragiouſneſs of his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, gave many Batteries againſt it, which wearied out the King; who finding no way for eſcape, yielded himſelf to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> craving his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for his refractorineſs. <hi>Olivaires</hi> received him kindly, embraced him,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152282:85"/>gave him his Life; and him he made Priſoner, together with the other Kings, under ſtrong and well-armed Guards. However <hi>Olivaires</hi> order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe Royal Captives to be more waited and attended on than his own Perſon; and he continually entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with Feaſts honorably, and at his own Table. The City being ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and every poor Soldier enriched with the Prey, they reſted and refreſh'd themſelves, until <hi>Olivaires</hi> bid <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> his Captain, refit the Fleet, and repair the Ships whereever there was need. After, when they were well Victualled, he cauſed him to diſpoſe the Army into good order for tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport to their own Kingdom. So in a ſhort time, all things being in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, he is now for departing with his Captive Kings, to the great Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Rejoycing of all his Noble and Valiant Crew, that had attended and gone along with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:152282:85"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>parts from</hi> Ireland <hi>for</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and of the honour was ſhown him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE <hi>Engliſh</hi> loaden with rich Spoils, with many Carriages and Horſes burthened with things of great value, now marched with their Sovereign <hi>Olivaires</hi> on their way; and the Kings rode on moſt beautiful Mules, without Spurs, and ſo travail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Valiant <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and, arrived at the Port, they found the Ships prepared for them, and all things neceſſary provided in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for them by the prudent care of Captain <hi>Edward.</hi> Having enter'd the Ships with all their Trophies, in few days with a fair wind they touch'd at the Port whence they parted when they came from <hi>England:</hi> And <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> having come a-land, and taken Lodgings, diſpatch'd. <hi>Edward</hi> away to
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152282:86"/>the King, and order'd him to inform him of the whole Succeſs of the War: <hi>Edward</hi> being gone Poſt with ſome other Knights, came to Court, and, having kiſſed the King's hand, and paid low reſpects unto <hi>Helena</hi> (for it happened that they were at Table to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) begun, after the Ceremonies of Salutation, to relate the Succeſs of the War; and to give account, in order, of the Valour, Strength, Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, Wit, and great Vertues that ſo eminently appear'd in <hi>Olivaires;</hi> whereat the King dropt tears for joy; and <hi>Helena</hi> kept a Jubilee in her Breaſt, and her heart melted with pleaſure: The Valiant Captain aſſur'd the King, that <hi>Olivaires</hi> was the fineſt Knight that ever bore Lance; and he told him with what courage he had taken the King's of <hi>Ireland</hi> Priſoners; and how with a handful, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he had foil'd and conquer'd them; and that he had brought them Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives with him to his Majeſty. Then the King cauſed to be given to <hi>Edward</hi>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:152282:86"/>a Preſent of Gold, and <hi>Helena</hi> another of Jewels, for the good News he had brought: Mean time <hi>Olivaires</hi> made great days Journies; and being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved near the Royal City, the King with three hundred Knights with gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Spurs, Dukes, Counts, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes, and the whole City, with all ſorts of Muſick, and Feaſtings, made the Heavens to re-eccho again the Applauſes of the Victory: The King rid a white Nag, habited in rich Tiſſue, and had the Royal Crown on his head; and when he came near <hi>Olivaires, Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> haſtily alighted from his Horſe, and ſo likewiſe the King; and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing him with Paternal kindneſs, he kiſſed him many times: The Kings of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſtood aſide, for they were not worthy to look on the ſacred Crown of <hi>England;</hi> and every one paid their reverence to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> the Archbiſhops, the Biſhops, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates; and they followed them on their way toward the City: The King gave thanks unto, and praiſed God; and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:152282:87"/>thanked <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and expreſſed how much he was obliged to him, both for the defence of his Kingdom, and for having acquired a-new ſo great a State: And <hi>Olivaires</hi> attributing the honour to God, and to his Knights, deſired the King that he would be grateful to them for their Valour; and alſo to the other Soldiers; foraſmuch as they all had behaved themſelves gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When they were arrived at the City, all with loud Voices, Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, and Inſtruments of all ſorts, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed their Joys; and when they were come into the Palace, <hi>Helena,</hi> like a deſcended Sun, came toward <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livaires,</hi> who bowing himſelf low, was ſupported by the King; and <hi>Helena</hi> gave him a Kiſs, which ſtruck an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable ſweetneſs and delight on <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi>'s Heart-ſtrings; and all the Evening, till time for reſt, was ſpent in extraordinary demonſtrations of Mirth and Joyfulneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:152282:87"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Captive Kings, and other Princes, are preſented to the King.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN the morning the Kings and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners were conducted to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. <hi>Olivaires</hi> gladly beheld them; and, a while after, when he thought it convenient, he brought them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King and <hi>Helena;</hi> who was well enough pleaſed to ſee their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the love ſhe bore her <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires:</hi> Then all the Priſoners bended the knee to the King; and <hi>Olivaires</hi> made a Preſent of them to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; but he delivered them over into <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s power to diſpoſe of them as he thought good. <hi>Olivaires</hi> then ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly gave them their Lives; and ordering a Table to be placed over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt that of the King, <hi>Helena,</hi> and <hi>Olivaires,</hi> he cauſed them to be as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably attended and waited on as his own Perſon; the Kings were tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152282:88"/>with this Courteſy, and it well pleaſed the Court alſo. After Dinner great Merriment began, and the Kings had fair liberty given them under Guards, and other things that were convenient. Theſe afterward accompanying them to their Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they left the King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Olivaires</hi> together to treat of the Marriage, and what related to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King's Diſcourſe, and what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd on</hi> Olivaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEing left then to diſcourſe by themſelves alone, the King asked <hi>Olivaires</hi> if he might be worthy of, and ſo happy to have his conſtant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and ſtay in <hi>England:</hi> Or if he deſigned to return to his Kingdom of <hi>Spain;</hi> to whom he made anſwer, he would never leave <hi>England</hi> without a King; and this he promiſed him on
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:152282:88"/>his Royal Word. The ſame night after Supper they had Muſick, and a great Ball. After a little Dancing, the King ſaid to his Nobles, who were preſent, My Son <hi>Olivaires</hi> intends to morrow to take my Daughter to wife, (and ſhe him for her Husband) and the Kingdom for her Dowry, which I deſire <hi>Olivaires</hi> to accept of as part of the reward of his Valour; and I think my ſelf, and us all happy, in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Realm upon him, who is the braveſt Cavalier of the World, and the chief King that ſways a Scepter. <hi>Olivaires</hi> making humble reverence to ſo honourable Age, with great expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of gratitude, ſaid, that he did not deſerve ſuch a Reward; and that he ſhould ever have reaſon to thank Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and his Majeſty, for promoting him to, and thinking him worthy of ſo great honour; and begged of God to proſper him, and prolong his days, and fill him with all content and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: On account of this Munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and the Eſpouſals, <hi>Olivaires</hi>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:152282:89"/>gave all the Priſoners, and the Kings, their Liberty; who receiving ſuch a favour, made their Acknowledgment after this manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Kings are made Tributaries of the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>and promiſe Fealty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next day the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings came to the Palace, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their mind to an Ancient No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman, who was a famous Cavalier; and he engaged, and gave his faith for them (and they confirmed it with their own Promiſes) that their Crowns ſhould for ever pay homage to his Majeſty's Royal State. So in the King's preſence they made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Tributary, and gave vow once a year to preſent themſelves before him, and in Peace and War to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to ſerve and obey the King,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:152282:89"/>and his Son <hi>Olivaires;</hi> then they kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the King's Hand. After that, they were preſented with Horſes of all ſorts, Pages, Veſtments, and all things they had occaſion for, and liberty to go or ſtay, as they had a mind; the Kings with low reverence thanked his Majeſty, and deſired of <hi>Olivaires</hi> they might tarry to ſee the Solemnity; and reiterated, that their Crowns ſhould be ever ſubſervient to ſo illuſtrious Worth and Vertue; and as to this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they had their ſatisfaction; ſo they prepared for Feaſts, Juſts, and other Combats, to honour the Eſpouſals; but for the preſent all went to reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>gives the Ring to</hi> Helena, <hi>and eſpouſes her with great pomp and feaſting.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King's Sergeants prepared New Veſtments, Liveries, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of Gold, and of Jewels; and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152282:90"/>all the Palace was hung with Tiſſue, ſmooth Velvet, and other rich Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, for celebrating and ſolemnizing the Marriage; they ordered twelve Biſhops, and one Archbiſhop, for performing the ſacred Ceremonies: All the Kings had their Royal Robes on; and the Dukes, Knights, Counts, and all the Barons were in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per habits; ſo they made a ſhow with their rich and ſplendid Pomp and Attire that ſtupify'd the Spectators; two Kings were elected to lead <hi>Hele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> to the Altar, and the reſt attended on <hi>Olivaires:</hi> The King was admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attired, with all his Court; and ſo <hi>Helena</hi> with all her Ladies; and <hi>Olivaires</hi> alſo flouriſhed in much grandezza: The Muſick was of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and moſt rare and admirable kinds: The day appointed being come, every one was ready to perform his Office, and they went with the King to get <hi>Olivaires</hi> up, and conduct him to the Chappel; and with him were four Biſhops, and other four with
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152282:90"/>
                  <hi>Helena;</hi> and all were to meet thoſe other with the Archbiſhop; who took the Ring, which was brought inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to <hi>Helena;</hi> and giving it to <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> the previous Ceremonies being duly performed, made him eſpouſe her; at which the rejoycings of the People, the gladneſs of the Court, the noiſe of the Military Muſick, and the ſweet Melody of the Sacred and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, with a thouſand other things that conduced to the celebrabing and great pomp of this Divine Solemnity, cannot be expreſſed. Afterward the Hoſt was adminiſter'd by the hand of the Archbiſhop; and, when Maſs was done, they went into the Hall, where ſuch a choice and ſumptuous Dinner attended them, that I think <hi>Jove</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with all his Divine Retinue, would not have diſdain'd to have been invited to, and have been preſent to grace theſe Nuptials: And, all the Diſhes being placed on the Table, new Liveries appeared, and new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments ſounded; and it was ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:152282:91"/>to ſee ſit at one Table ſeven Kings, and one Queen. After Dinner orders were given for Dancing; and after that for a noble Tilting, where the Kings, for the honour of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſals, clad in choice Habit and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and on their beſt Horſes, juſted againſt each other with laudable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of their Proweſs; but it was not agreeable for <hi>Olivaires</hi> to juſt that time. When the Tilting was ended, the two Kings received a moſt rich Preſent from the hands of <hi>Helena,</hi> and ſhe thanked them for ſo great a favour; and they alſo bowed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to her, and humbly thanked her for her Gift. And now the time for Supper approached; wherefore, after a little reſpite, they ſat down to rich, ſumptuous, and ſplendid Tables. He who could penetrate into the ſecret thoughts of Lovers, and, as it were, ſee <hi>Olivaires</hi> mind and deſires, and the ardent love <hi>Helena</hi> bore her new Spouſe, might ſafely ſay, that that Day ſeemed to them both a very long
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:152282:91"/>one, and even every hour a Year. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per being ended, and the Dancing over, the King riſes from his Seat, and embracing <hi>Helena,</hi> and kiſſing her, recommended her to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; then every one retired with much content to their ſeveral Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and the happy licens'd Couple went to taſte that free bliſs which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Youth and Beauty, and deeply inamour'd hearts, is capable of, or has any poſſibility to conceive: It pleaſed Almighty God that the fair <hi>Helena</hi> conceived that night, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall her Travail be, for that of her ſhall be born a grand Champion for, and Pillar of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chronicles fully and faithfully relate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:152282:92"/>
               <head>CHAP. L.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King goes in the morning to viſit</hi> Olivaires; <hi>and the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Kings take their leave; and of other things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> and <hi>Helena</hi> turn'd night into day, and day into night, the cuſtom of all new married Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, eſpecially ſuch paſſionate Lovers as they; ſo that after Dinner the King went into their Chamber, and was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry glad to find his Son in Bed, and uſed ſome pleaſant raillery to him for a while. After <hi>Olivaires</hi> had got up, and was dreſt, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings came before them, and they took their leaves of them all, and by <hi>Olivaires</hi> and the King they were preſented with Horſes for all uſes, and other things ſuitable to ſuch a joyful time, and ſuch a Crown and Royal Majeſty: The Archbiſhop came and bleſſed that Fruit which was hoped to ſpring from them; and all the Biſhops gave them their benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and, the Feaſtings and Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152282:92"/>being renewed, they paſt many days in eaſe and jollity; and the Kings of <hi>Ireland</hi> at their departure did aſſure them they would never forget ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſhewn, and ſuch Preſents receiv'd. After a juſt time <hi>Helena</hi> was delivered of a Boy; and baptizing it with infinite pomp and ſplendor, they gave it the name of <hi>Henry,</hi> which as he advanc'd in years, ſo did he in vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſupporting and diffuſing the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith; and the Lord was moſt gracious unto them, ſo that from that time, at other nine months end ſhe was in travel again, and brought forth a Daughter, whom they named <hi>Claritia,</hi> who when come to years was not her admired Mother's inferior, either for corporeal ſhape and beauty, or endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of mind. <hi>Olivaires</hi> enjoy'd a quiet ſtate, and liv'd in all manner of peace, ever together with his fair ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Conſort, praiſing, thanking, and adoring the infinite Goodneſs of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for his ſo great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Benefits: And his Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-hours
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:152282:93"/>he ſpent in the Chace, Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Hawking, and other Princely Diverſions. When one day Envious Fortune watch'd an opportunity to diſturb his happineſs, and obtain'd it, as you ſhall read in the ſequel of our Story.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Helena <hi>Dreams a Melancholy Dream, her Lord being out at the Chace, and ſends him notice of it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WITH what kind eyes <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> was look'd on, and how much beloved of the Court and the whole Kingdom, tongue cannot utter. And all his paſs-time he ſpent in finding out wild Beaſts, in chacing, and taking them: Wherefore ſome of his Subjects, neighbours to a rough and craggy Mountain, about Two days Journey diſtant, came to give him notice how Two moſt fierce and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:152282:93"/>overgrown old wild Boars did much deſtroy and lay waſte their Country, ſo that they obtain'd but little Fruits or good from their ground. At the hearing of which news, <hi>Olivaires</hi> (upon his own account, and alſo in proſpect of their future advantage) was hugely pleaſed, and alſo gave them preſents for the ſame; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he ordered his Hunters to make themſelves ready, their Toils, and all things elſe that were neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ſuch ſort of Game. So after Dinner <hi>Olivaires</hi> mounts his Horſe, and goes for the place, and lodged that night at a homely Village; the night following <hi>Helena</hi> lying alone, ſaw in a Dream the White Knight ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to her, that gave her the Ring, who preſented to her fancy a fierce Lioneſs Aſſaulting <hi>Olivaires</hi> in the Chace, and ſo hurting him, that he remained Wounded on the ſpot, then vaniſhed. Whereupon ſuddenly with ſhrill ſcreeches ſhe awak'd, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd alſo the Ladies that lay by her,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:152282:94"/>and having told them her Dream, ſhe alſo after related it to the King, aſſuring her ſelf it was over-true ſome ſiniſter Accident would befal <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res;</hi> and therefore diſpatched Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers away to give <hi>Olivaires</hi> intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of it, that he might proceed no further toward the Chace; who quickly, as ſwift as the wind, went after him to overtake him; and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd they were when they found him ſafe and cheerful; and the whole ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they gave him both by Letters and word of Mouth. The advice pleaſed <hi>Olivaires,</hi> who yet went on for the Chace, as one who feared not any thing, being within his own Realm, and among People that loved and were obſervant of him. Then he diſmiſs'd the Meſſengers, and bid them let <hi>Helena</hi> know, That he would be with her the following Evening. So ſhe reſted well content, for that he would take care of himſelf, and was at preſent in ſafe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:152282:94"/>
               <head>CHAP. LII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One of the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Kings coming to pay Tribute to the King of</hi> England, <hi>finds</hi> Olivaires <hi>alone in a diſmal grove; who tranſported with deſire of catching his Prey, is ſevered from his Company, and taken Priſoner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Hunters by break of day went with <hi>Olivaires</hi> to the place, where were ſhewed them the lodges of thoſe great and fierce Boars; and the Hunters, as need required, being ſeparated to their particular ſtands and paſſes, the Dogs went into the thick of the Grove to fetch them forth from their Dens. <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſtood in a more common and trodden path in expectation of the Boar; and Fortune, which took a pleaſure in exerciſing and putting on hardſhips the braveſt Knight of the world, ſent the Savage his way; and he ſmiting him, and that flying, and he purſuing,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:152282:95"/>it happened that the other Boar ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied out of the Grove, and took a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary rode; wherefore the Hunters having not ſpied that which <hi>Olivaires</hi> Chac'd, all went after the other; and although ſome followed their Maſter, ſo ſwift a race the wild Animal led them (and <hi>Olivaires</hi> was much the foremoſt in purſuit) they loſt their way; but lighting on a track, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned back, having loſt that of their Maſter by reaſon of the large fallen leaves that had ſtrew'd the ground. <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſtill purſued the Savage, and ſo far got engag'd in the Grove, that he quite loſt his way, not knowing in what place, what ground, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about he was; here then comes to his mind <hi>Helena</hi>'s Dream, and he knew not what to think; but night haſting on, he traverſes this way and that way, and at length frees himſelf of the Grove, but far enough he was from any dwellings; and he ſaw coming far off a great many Horſe, which much cheer'd him, thinking
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:152282:95"/>they were his own company; but when they came near (for 'twas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to be dark) he found it to be one of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings, King <hi>Maque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi>'s Son, who was ſlain at the Tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and knowing <hi>Olivaires,</hi> he cry'd, Lo! this is he who kill'd the King my Father; wherefore let him be ſeiz'd, ſince Fortune has offer'd me ſo fair an opportunity. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> having only his <hi>Javelin,</hi> puts himſelf (yet weary) in poſture of defence; but it breaking (after he had ſlain ſome of them) he was taken, and bound, and under a ſtrong Guard conducted all the night toward the Realm of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and in a well-fortified and lofty Tower, was committed to the Governor's cuſtody, having charge to keep him ſtrict Priſoner till the King's return, neither ſuffering to talk with, nor ſee any body; and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> King held on his Journey to the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Court; and having done his Homage, he ſtayed a little, for that he ſaw the Court in mighty Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:152282:96"/>on and Grief, becauſe <hi>Olivaires</hi> could no where be found, and then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home. <hi>Olivaires</hi> was in a bottom room of a moſt high Tower, and much afflicted; he prayed unto God that he would conſolate his Lady, and the King, and alſo aid him in his miſerable condition. One time the Governor of the Fortreſs carrying him Meat himſelf, took great notice of him, and was amazed at his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Aſpect; and moved with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, ſaid, Sir, you be ſome noble Cavalier? I am ſo, replied <hi>Olivaires:</hi> Then ſubjoin'd the other, Make me Promiſe that you will not endeavour eſcape out of the Fortreſs, and I will free you from this cloſe Confinement: <hi>Olivaires</hi> told him he would not on his Royal word; for, ſaid he, I am <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires;</hi> then he brought him out, and gave him the whole Caſtle for his ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Priſon, with infinite Careſſes. Had I well Chaſtiz'd my Enemy, ſaid Fortune's haraſs'd Knight, and been more ſevere with him for his Auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:152282:96"/>I ſhould not for life given have received a death; but ſince it ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the grand diſpoſer, Lo! I patiently bear it. Mean while the King and <hi>Helena</hi> made ſearch through the whole Kingdom, through all the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Groves and remote Woods, among the obſcure Caverns, Receſſes, and Valleys, and o're all the high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains for <hi>Olivaires.</hi> One time fearing he might be fallen into a ſwoon, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſt ſome wild Beaſt might have devoured him; ſometime thinking that Highway-men might have light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on him and ſlain him: At length not getting any news of him, they gave themſelves up wholly to Grief and Lamentations; and thoſe that had ſeen <hi>Helena,</hi> would rather have thought her a wild Beaſt than a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whilſt ſhe pluck'd off her Hair, ſcratch'd her Face, rent her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſcreek'd out aloud, and would not take either any Meat or Reſt. The King was aſtoniſhed, and ſtruck al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead with this Accident; and all
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:152282:97"/>Faſhion and good Order neglected, the Court became a melancholy, heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and confuſed Crew; for every one much feared the life both of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi> and the King, ſo exceſſive was their Affliction; and the dolors and ſighs that proceeded from their breaſts did ſo affect and trouble the Lords and Knights, as almoſt to break their hearts. He who had heard the praiſes <hi>Olivaires</hi> had given him of the King, and ſeen what a blow of diſcontent this Accident had given the Crown, would have been very ſenſible his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had felt both the utmoſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of happineſs and miſery: But leaving <hi>Helena,</hi> the King, and the whole Court, to their Sorrows, let us now proceed to look for <hi>Arthur,</hi> who ſo long ſaw the water clear, but of a ſudden beheld it turn'd cloudy; and underſtanding what it meant, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily ſets forward in ſearch after <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> being fully reſolved to find him out; and on the one hand hurried away with a violent deſire of ſeeing
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:152282:97"/>him; and on the other ſtimulated with grief, knowing ſome great peril had behapned him, he as it were flew with Wings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur <hi>prepares to go in ſearch after</hi> Olivaires, <hi>by ſignal of the Water, which ſhews his Calamity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Related before the manner of <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi>'s departure from <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and the grief that it cauſed his Father, the Court, and the Queen the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal occaſion of ſo great an Evil: But the King's Affliction was the heavieſt, and in a ſhort time coſt him his life: Upon his death then <hi>Arthur</hi> was made Ruler of the Kingdom, by thoſe Dukes, Barons, and Knights, and had the Government until they ſhould hear of King <hi>Olivaires:</hi> And <hi>Arthur</hi> willingly accepted of it, for the love he bore to his Brother; and every day
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:152282:98"/>he looked on the Vial of Water. At length, One morning, a while after he had riſe, he was for going out a Hunting, but would before ſee the Water, which he found troubled, and of a bloudy colour: Whereupon he cry'd out, O noble and virtuous Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, my faithful Brother! where ſhall I find thee to free me from ſo great dangers? Whither ſhall I go, which way muſt I ſteer to ſuccour thee? O that I knew the Province, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the City, nay that Heaven that could inform me of thee! And inſtead of going a Hunting (unleſs in another kind) he appointed his Vicegerent, and on a brisk Courſer, with a Sum of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Jewels, with all poſſible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch he is mounted for his Journey: Having to all his Barons deliver'd up the Government, and beſeeched them to adminiſter all things for the beſt, in as much as he hoped that they might ſhortly have <hi>Olivaires</hi> with them; and deſir'd them they would not marvail at his departure, ſince it was of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:152282:98"/>for the good of the whole State. Accompanied then with thoſe few he had a mind to, he firſt takes his way thorough his own Kingdom, and ſo orders the Affairs of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, declaring all along he was going about a matter of grand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, as indeed it was. <hi>Arthur</hi>'s go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, was a great trouble to the Lords of <hi>Caſtile</hi> firſt, and after to thoſe of <hi>Dalgarve;</hi> for his behaviour and carriage to them were ſuch, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one was in love with his noble and generous Temper; and his Vertues made him the Darling of Mankind: So all lamented his departure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur<hi>'s Voyage through divers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, in ſearch of</hi> Olivaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARrthur</hi> being got out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, recommends himſelf unto God, and his good Providence. And
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:152282:99"/>firſt he makes ſearch through all the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal,</hi> in all the Cities, and in all places of the Realm; nor deſiſts his inqueſt till he goes into the remoteſt Woods. Now in his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy inquiry that way, he hears tell, that not far off a fierce Lyon haunted a Mountain; and whoever went into thoſe places, was ſure either to be kill'd, or at leaſt be wofully ſhatter'd by the ſavage; and that many Knights, for proof of their Proweſs, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Country with a publick bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, had made attempts upon him, but with the loſs of their lives. <hi>Arthur</hi> hearing this, deliberated with himſelf whether <hi>Olivaires</hi> might not perhaps have gone on this enterprize: And, having fitted his Armour, he makes for the Mountain; and when he had got half way, he meets the Lion, who had come far, was lean, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and by chance lame of a Paw. <hi>Arthur</hi> ſeeing him, wondered he was ſo gentle, thinking with himſelf it was eaſy to kill him; and for that end,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:152282:99"/>without fear, goes toward him: The Lion reaches out himſelf a length, as Dogs are wont to do, and with a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Roine expreſſed that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended himſelf to his favour, and ſhew'd him his Paw, which was ſwell'd, and had rotted, becauſe a piece of the Splinter of a Spear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in it. <hi>Arthur</hi> then drew him the Shiver out, and forth run a great deal of corrupt matter: Whereupon the Lion perceiving it to be better with him, with many more Careſſes and wantoner play than a Dog can make, gratefully fawns upon him. <hi>Arthur</hi> goes for the Mountain, and the Lion follows him; and having ſought, but not found any humane footſteps, he returns to his own Road, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied by the Lion; all the Country fled before them, beholding the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal: But <hi>Arthur</hi> put them out of fear, making 'em to ſee how tame the Lion was; and he gave him a piece of fat Veal, and it refreſhed him; and in a ſhort time, by attending on him, the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:152282:100"/>Animal became ſound and hearty, and went continually at <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Stirrup as a Page when he rode; and when he ſlept a-nights, lay Centinel at his Chamber-door like a Maſtiff. <hi>Arthur</hi> accompanied of this Lion, made ſearch thorough many, and many Realms, <hi>Catalonia, Languedoc, Spain, Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, France, Piccardy, Burgundy,</hi> and ſpent many a day in travail, yet could never hear any news at all of <hi>Olivaires.</hi> One night melancholly and fatigu'd with his Journy (having arrived at the Port of <hi>Cales</hi>) he argued to himſelf, and having no other in company with him in his Chamber but the Lion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he thus complained: Oh! why may not my dolors have an end as well as thine, moſt loving Animal? Ah! that at the leaſt I could inform thee how excelling a Knight he is I wander in queſt of; how noble, how admirable, and how he bears away, and eaſily deſerves the Palm of all the valiant Knights of Chivalry! The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſenſible of <hi>Arthur</hi>'s meaning,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:152282:100"/>and wept. And next morning the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal took the way before him, and went to the Port, and enter'd into a Ship; but the Mariners were affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cry'd out aloud; and <hi>Arthur</hi> alſo entering, let them ſee how tame and gentle he was; ſo they hois'd Sail, and <hi>Arthur</hi> took good Augury from the Lion, and made no enquiry what Coaſt the Ship was bound for.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of an horrible Monſter which</hi> Arthur <hi>kill'd in the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland; <hi>and of a Viſion that he had.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Wind ſwelling the Sails, the Mariners with a proſperous Voyage purſued their Navigation; and <hi>Arthur</hi> was ever asking where about they were; and being on the Coaſts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in the Evening having touched at the Shore in a Port, the Lion went out of the Ship, nor
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:152282:101"/>would return into it again any more: Wherefore <hi>Arthur</hi> was obliged to ſtay in that Land, and ſearching about all the Country, he could not get any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of <hi>Olivaires;</hi> ſo he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make ſearch in a vaſt Wood: The Lion never forſook him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into the thick of lofty Trees, whoſe leafy Boughs excluded the light of the Noon-day's Sun, the Cavalier began to be afraid of ſuch a place; and his Lion running about over it all, happened to put up from his dark Den, a terrible, foul, and horrid Monſter, of the ſize of a Buffle; but by reaſon of his great bulk, he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Belly on the ground like a Serpent. He had four Feet, with ſhort Legs, like a Lizzard or Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile; and on the tips of theſe he rear'd himſelf about an Ell from the ground with long Claws like Eagles Talons; his Caſe, or Skin, reſembled that of the briſtled Bore, which the <hi>Italians</hi> call <hi>Riccio &amp; Spinoſo;</hi> full of theſe Sharps like a Porcupine, excepting all
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:152282:101"/>the Neck from the Chine-bone, and the Head, which part was like the ſpungineſs of a Rock, but hard, and of diverſe mingled colours: His Neck was like that of a Bull; and a vaſt Head like an Elephant's, but without his cloudy Brow, and alſo ſuch Teeth; however his were large enough, and ſharp: When he open'd his Mouth, it look'd like a Furnace, Smoak iſſuing out of it; and the red of his Jaws was ſo hot, that it ſeem'd a fire: His Taile was four ells long; the extremity of it was hard and horny, and with that he ſmote as with a Javelin, or his Sting: out of his Flanks grew four Wings like a Dragon's, and other four he ſpread abroad, which proceeded from the ridge of his Back; ſo that he was all covered with theſe. When the Lion beheld this new Animal full before his face, he roar'd out ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that all the Wood re<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>eccho'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and the Monſter turned about as if he was mad: The Lion, as afraid, went near to <hi>Arthur;</hi> at this the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:152282:102"/>ſtrange kind of Animal ſtretched forth himſelf, and flapping with his Wings, came towards <hi>Arthur,</hi> and ſmote him on the Thigh with the horn of his Tail, and with the end of his Wing he gave the Lion a bruſh on the Head, and opening his Mouth, it ſmoak'd like a Furnace. <hi>Arthur</hi> leapt aſide, and, laying hold on his Sword, gave him ſo fierce a blow on the Neck, that he made him hiſs; and ſo ſharp was his hiſs, that it diſmayed the other; but ſo hard was that Rock, that the Sword could not pierce it; wherefore <hi>Arthur</hi> look'd on himſelf as a dead man. The Lion fetching a brisk skip, leaps upon his Chine-point, and faſt'n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hind Paws on his Shoulders, and his fore on his Head, and in his Eyes, he made him through anguiſh of his Viſage, fall on one ſide on the ground: <hi>Arthur</hi> ſeeing his Paunch lay expos'd, run to ſmite him in the Belly, and with few ſtrokes he opens it, and through that aperture his life flies away: Beholding the Monſter dead,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:152282:102"/>and conſidering all the Parts of him, he much thanked God who had given him ſuch a Lion for his Companion, and had delivered him from ſo great a danger. Then viewing the Wound he had received, it appear'd very deep; and when it cool'd, it begun to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream painful; but ſuch quantity of Blood had run out, as ſo weakned his Spirits, that he could ſcarce ſtand on his Feet: At this noiſe of the Beaſt, and the roaring of the Lion, a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Country People and Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds came down from the Mountains, and ſeeing the fierce Monſter dead, they were amazed; and after wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the familiarity of the Lion: And <hi>Arthur</hi> aſſuring them of his gentleneſs, begun to talk with them, and told them the particulars of the Accident; whereupon they much careſſed him, and conducted him to their Cottages, and the Lion was continually by his ſide: And after he had taken ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, they left him to his night's repoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:152282:103"/>
               <head>CHAP. LVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The White Cavalier appears in a Dream to</hi> Arthur, <hi>and heals his Wound.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen on his firſt ſleep, the door being ſhut, the White Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier appears unto him, and wakens him; ſaying, <hi>Arthur,</hi> I am come to comfort thee. <hi>Arthur</hi> ſeeing ſuch a Perſon, and ſo accompanied, and then that he ſhould call him by his Name, wondered greatly. Do not marvel; for I will inſtruct thee concerning <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires.</hi> Good God! Am I in a Dream, or am I awake? Thou art awake, ſaid the Knight; and for a ſign, ſhew me thy wounded Thigh, that I may heal it. And having dreſſed it, he took precious Balſams, which he had ordered to be brought with him, and quickly anointing it, and binding it up, ſaid, To morrow you ſhall be well. You then do me a mighty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; and you promiſe to inform me of <hi>Olivaires;</hi> Oh, to whom muſt I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:152282:103"/>my infinite Thanks? Tell me, Dear Sir, who you are that do me ſuch Kindneſſes? Oh! how ſhall I ever be able to requite them? It is not ſo convenient that you learn my Name at this time: See here is a Root for you, which you ſhould eat, ſaid the Cavalier; for it would make you new Blood, and recover your loſt Strength. How am I obliged to you, admirable Knight, and what ſhall I do for you? No other thing than go into <hi>England,</hi> and conſolate the King and <hi>Helena,</hi> who are in great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and almoſt ſpent with ſorrow; for <hi>Olivaires</hi> is her Husband, and ſhe the King's Daughter. And here the Cavalier told <hi>Arthur</hi> all the Journey, Accidents, Deeds, Feats, Behaviour, Diſgraces, Fortunes, and every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuteſt thing concerning <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and how he was taken, and that he was in Priſon: Forther, thou ſhalt ſay, that thou art <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and ſhalt ſleep together with <hi>Helena</hi> (but touch her not.) After thou ſhalt return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:152282:104"/>this place, that I may ſet thee on thy way for getting <hi>Olivaires</hi> out of Priſon: And he told him and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him in every thing that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Then he gave him a little Electuary; which when <hi>Arthur</hi> had put in his Mouth, he ſuddenly fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur <hi>does all that the White Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier ordered him; and how he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved of every one to be</hi> Olivaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARthur</hi> reſembled <hi>Olivaires</hi> in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, in Speech, in Shape, in Viſage, and in all his Manner and Ways; and they differed in nothing, ſave a Mark in one Arm; for <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> had three Moles at the ſetting on of his Shoulder, with ſome ſlender Hairs which appeared like the fineſt Wire-drawn Gold; and <hi>Arthur</hi> had not ſuch. When <hi>Arthur</hi> waked in the
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:152282:104"/>Morning, he thought he had been in a Dream, and that of the Cavalier but a Viſion of Fancy: But deſirous to be aſſured, he begun to handle his Wound; and not making it ſmart, when he had unwrapped it, he found it healed; then his Joyfulneſs return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, and he no further doubted. And ſuddenly was on his way for <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and ſpurring on, and alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving croſſed the Sea, he came to a Town, walled about, whoſe Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants very well knew <hi>Olivaires.</hi> And ſeeing <hi>Arthur,</hi> they all forthwith run into him to make their Obeiſance, and Congratulate his return; and they made an extraordinary great Feaſt. Then diverſe of them took Poſt for <hi>London,</hi> to tell the News at Court. And himſelf, a little after, with an honourable Attendance of the Chief of the Countrey, rode to <hi>London.</hi> When the Poſters had told the News, the King ſo recovered himſelf of a ſudden, that he roſe from his Couch, and honourably rewarded thoſe that
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:152282:105"/>brought it; and gave order for Feaſts, Triumphs, and great Rejoycings. And underſtanding his entry into the City was to be the next Day, great Multitudes went out to meet him; and the King himſelf: And when he was near, he run to embrace him, and clung faſt to him, but could not ſpeak for Joy. But he, moved with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion for his Brother <hi>Olivaires,</hi> was inwardly much troubled. All the Knights and Lords kiſſed his Hands; and the World kept a Jubilee; every place re-ecchoed with rare Voices, and muſical Inſtruments, both Civil and Military. The King having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a little breath, embraced him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſaid; O my Son, <hi>Olivaires,</hi> your coming has lengthened my Days. Sir, my departure was forced; and I have undergon great affliction on ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Love which I know your Majeſty always entertains for me; but I hope in God to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for all the Evil my abſence has cauſed: And the Bounty and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:152282:105"/>I have received from you, I will never forget.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur<hi>'s entry into</hi> London; <hi>and the viſit he gave</hi> Helena, <hi>who is ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Joy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen the King and <hi>Arthur</hi> came to the City, ſuch multitudes of People ſo throng'd in the Streets, that they could ſcarce paſs through them; all the Ladies ſtood in the Windows ſinging pleaſant Songs ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Occaſion; all the Streets were adorned with fine Hangings; and all the Clergy met them, firmly belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it was their King; all the Bells rung merrily, and wonderful Bonfires were made on the tops of the Palaces. <hi>Helena</hi> inquired the meaning of all this Feſtivity, and what was the reaſon of ſuch Solemnity; but ſhe could not learn, for the Phyſicians had
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:152282:106"/>given charge againſt too ſudden a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the News unto her, that the over eager Joy might not produce ill, not to ſay fatal, Effects: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore warily, and by degrees, they hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to her that <hi>Olivaires</hi> was come. She aſſuredly gathering as much, lift up her Hands to Heaven, bleſſing and praiſing God for ſo great a Mercy: May the hour of my Death come when it ſhall pleaſe him, for I ſhall not fear it after having had once more a ſight of my deareſt Conſort. And ſhe would have raiſed her ſelf up (making indeavour) from her Bed, but her weakneſs would not permit. Oh, what raviſhment gave to her Soul the thoughts of ſeeing her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Olivaires!</hi> The King clome up the Stairs, having <hi>Arthur</hi> by the Hand; nor would let go till he had brought him to <hi>Helena</hi>'s Bed-ſide, who threw her Arms about his Neck; every one of them Weeping; ſhe for Joy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving 'twas <hi>Olivaires;</hi> he out of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Compaſſion for the true <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires.</hi>
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:152282:106"/>So being undiſcovered, he invented agreeable things to diſcourſe of with <hi>Helena</hi> till time of Supper. Then the King ſent for him, but <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi> detained him to ſup with her. The Phyſicians ordered that he ſhould not ſleep with <hi>Helena;</hi> ſhe would not conſent unto it: Then <hi>Arthur</hi> went into her Bed, but lay as if he had not been there; for <hi>Arthur</hi> ſaid, I am ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by a Vow againſt all Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, either in Thought or Deed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til firſt (as I have promiſed unto God) I pay Reverence and Homage to the holy Apoſtle <hi>James:</hi> Therefore I deſire you would excuſe me, for it is an Ordinance of God; and in that time you will recover your Health. She was very well contented; and asked him how his departure was, and where he ſpent ſo long time without her? and ſaid, ſhe fully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved 'twas a forced thing. He told her it was ſo, and that he could not have endured ſo long an abſence, but that it was neceſſary he might not
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:152282:107"/>appear, before the time for accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing his Vow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur <hi>feigning to go to diſcharge his Vow, goes for freeing</hi> Olivaires <hi>out of Priſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARthur</hi> remained a few days at the Court, (and all the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers were amazed at the gentleneſs and beauty of his Lion;) but then urged by his love for <hi>Olivaires,</hi> he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly imparted to the King and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi> his intentions of going to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his Vow; and ſaid, he after would immediately return. The King commended his devotion; and his Train having all made ready, leave taken, and promiſe made of a ſpeedy return, he departed. When he was gone on his way ſome days Journies, he ordered his Attendance to make a ſtop, and to ſtay where they then
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:152282:107"/>were, till his coming back; for that he would go alone unto this Duty, without pomp, in a plain and humble manner, (wherefore they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſtay behind, and obſerve his pleaſure) and he ſaid he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back to them, and go together with them unto his Kingdom. In the morning then <hi>Arthur</hi> departs for a time, accompanied with his Lion alone, and he croſs'd the Sea, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd <hi>Ireland,</hi> and arrived at the place he parted from; and they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring him, expreſſed great joy at the ſeeing him again. At night when he ſlept, the white Cavalier came and inſtructed him where <hi>Olivaires</hi> was, and how he ſhould go immediately and releaſe him out of Priſon, for that the Lion was ſent him of God for his Companion, and that he ought to follow his conduct, who would bring him to the City, and the place he had in Viſion repreſented unto him. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> gave him thanks for his obliging cure, and alſo for his now much more
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:152282:108"/>obliging information concerning his Friend <hi>Olivaires;</hi> then he diſappeared. <hi>Arthur</hi> waking, ſaw the Sun was well advanc'd, and riſing from his Bed, he followed the Lion, who by ſecret and unknown ways conducted him in ſhort time unto the City; and when he was at the entrance, he found the white Cavalier, who ſaid, <hi>Ply thy Sword, and my ſervice to</hi> Olivaires; and vaniſh'd. The Lion then running into the City, <hi>Arthur</hi> followed him on Horſe-back; after he enter'd a Garden where was the King and all his Nobles, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fierce Animal, were affrighted; then <hi>Arthur</hi> laid his hand on his Sword, and ſaid, <hi>Wicked King, thou ſhalt not eſcape the juſt vengeance of Heaven.</hi> At this all thoſe Cavaliers were diſmai'd, and in ſo great fear, that they could ſcarce draw their Swords; in this jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture the white Knight with a great Army ſeiz'd the Piazza, and gallop'd about the City as his own; wherefore the King being depriv'd of his reli'd-on ſuccor, was all in deſpair and confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="chapter">
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:152282:108"/>
               <head>CHAP. LX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur <hi>takes the King Priſoner, and ſets</hi> Olivaires <hi>at Liberty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Lion ran to make havock among thoſe Cavaliers, and ſlew many. And <hi>Arthur</hi> ſmiting and making a large ſhammels of them, opened himſelf a wide Lane, and run after the King, who endeavoured to get into the Fortreſs; but <hi>Arthur</hi> overtook him with a cleaving ſtroke on his Head, which would certainly have divided it, had it hit fair; but it glanced and brought him only to the Ground, where he begs of <hi>Arthur,</hi> for God's ſake, to ſave his Life. Ah! unfaithful Man, ſaid <hi>Arthur,</hi> Is this the reward of that Mercy and Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thou hadſt ſhown thee by <hi>Olivaires,</hi> to detain him in Priſon? And making him riſe, he pricks him on with the point of his Sword to trip to the Caſtle, and open to <hi>Olivaires;</hi> then lets him
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:152282:109"/>go, knowing that he could not get out of the Yard. The Lion having glutted himſelf with Slaughter, not finding now any remaining, followed <hi>Arthur;</hi> and <hi>Arthur</hi> could not keep him from killing the Governour, and the Soldiers that were in the Fort. Lo! <hi>Olivaires</hi> coming out of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all pallid, meager, and miſerably afflicted; who throwing himſelf at <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Feet, not knowing him, but thinking he was one of the King's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſaid theſe words: Wherefore does the King ſuffer me to languiſh thus? Why does he not kill me? What better revenge than to take his Life away, whom thou holdſt for thine Enemy? I beſeech thee that thou wouldſt kill me, or make ſome endeavours for me, that I may no longer have ſo hard and cruel Uſage. <hi>Arthur</hi> ſeeing and hearing him ſpeak theſe piteous words, was inwardly extreamly afflicted, and his Wrath glowed hot againſt the King. I am thy Brother <hi>Arthur,</hi> ſaid he, O my
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:152282:109"/>
                  <hi>Olivaires.</hi> At which voice his Spirits revived, which were ſadly ſunk and dead before; and they ran together and embrac'd one another. And ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the place, they found Meat, and alſo wherewith to recruit, every way help, and Royally habit <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> The mean time that they rook ſome Refreſhment, Diſcourſed, and provided for themſelves, every body in the City locked themſelves up in their Houſes. And the King could not find any to make him help; wherefore oppreſſed with Grief, and in fear of his Life, he ſaid, 'Tis the beſt for me to yield my ſelf up into <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Hands, for I know he is ſo Pitiful, Courteous, Noble, Good and Gentle, that he will give me my Life. And returning, all beſmeered with Blood, into the Fortreſs, he found on the Stairs, and in the Halls and Chambers, all his Vaſſals ſlain, which troubled him infinitely. At length being come before <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> he falls down on his Knees, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:152282:110"/>lamenting, and begging of <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> that, for the ſake of God, he would pardon him; and craved Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with hideous Sighings. Here <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> would have made an end of him, but <hi>Olivaires</hi> holds his Arm; and ſays to him, Take heart; for, for the love of God a greater thing than this ought to be given; and bidding him riſe, they cauſed ſome men they ſpied to come and help him; who, with great fear and trembling, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from high Places whither they had fled for refuge. Here the King being made Priſoner, and the fortifi'd Places taken, he renounced the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to <hi>Olivaires;</hi> who was by them acknowledged and accepted of for their Sovereign. Words cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Lamentations <hi>Olivaires</hi> and <hi>Arthur</hi> made betwixt each other, the Moans, and the Weeping; alſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycings. But to have told him the News of the Death of the King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> his Father, and all the ill Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents had happened thoſe many
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:152282:110"/>Years they had been ſeparated from one another, would have been too too Melancholy a Theme, and the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would almoſt have broke his Heart. That Night the City was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up, by means of the White Cavalier: And many Days after they remained in the Town, till <hi>Olivaires</hi> might recover more Cheerfulneſs and Strength; he judging it equal Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, either to return and ſee <hi>Helena,</hi> the King, and his Children, or to have in his Sight, and the Company of his <hi>Arthur</hi> alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The departure of</hi> Olivaires <hi>and</hi> Arthur <hi>from</hi> Ireland; <hi>and how</hi> Olivaires <hi>would have ſlain</hi> Arthur.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT appearing to <hi>Olivaires</hi> that he had done but ſmall ſervice for the ſake of God; therefore when he left the City, he gave back, and reſtored the
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:152282:111"/>Kingdom to the King; telling him, That he ought to become a Man more worthy of ſuch a Crown, and that he ſhould learn to fear God; ſo they depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great Honour and Joy. By the way <hi>Arthur</hi> began to tell of his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which he had undertaken for him; he told him of his Lion's Malady; of the danger he had ſcaped by the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Death; and of all that Kindneſs ſhewed him of the White Cavalier, for ſaving his Life by the Cure; and how by his Counſel he went into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and was received as <hi>Olivaires,</hi> and not as <hi>Arthur;</hi> and that for <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena</hi>'s Recovery, and the ſaving her languiſhing Life, he had ſlept toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her. Here <hi>Olivaires,</hi> as weak as he was, ſuddenly drew out his Sword, and ſmote <hi>Arthur</hi> on the Head, hearing he had ſlept with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena;</hi> not expecting till he had told the remainder: Whereupon he fell ſtounded to the Ground; and he would have killed him out, but that the White Cavalier appeared and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:152282:111"/>him. <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſeeing his Knight, of whom he had received ſo many Benefits, caſt himſelf from his Horſe on the Ground, and rever'd him as a Father; and he told him all the Matter of <hi>Arthur,</hi> and gave <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> a reprimand: Wherefore grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, he begged Pardon of the ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Arthur,</hi> and deſired of the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier to forgive him; who quickly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied his Hand for the Cure of <hi>Arthur,</hi> and healed him: And when he was come to himſelf, he made them as good Friends as ever. Then he took ſome certain Roots of Herbs, and gave <hi>Olivaires</hi> them to feed upon; by which means, in a few Days, he was reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, refreſhed and brisk, equal to, and ſo like <hi>Arthur,</hi> that every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that it was ſome deſign of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that two ſhould ſo ſtrangely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble each other. The Knight, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had done all, turning to <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> ſaid; Recollect your ſelf, I can no longer attend you, and you will have no further need of me:
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:152282:112"/>When will the time be for my Share, according to your Promiſe? and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <hi>Arthur</hi> hearing the Knight, proceeded to tell <hi>Olivaires</hi> the whole Succeſs; and he found that every thing had fallen out agreeably to what he had ſaid to him in a Viſion: And ſo he was aſcertained that this was ſome Divine Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How</hi> Arthur <hi>returns by the ſame way; and when he finds his Cavaliers, they ſtand amazed, not knowing which of the two is</hi> Olivaires; <hi>and the great delight this produces.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE valiant Brothers being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived where the Cavaliers were ordered to ſtay, thoſe could not tell, at the ſight of them, unto which they ſhould pay their Obeiſance, even al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lion was ever by <hi>Arthur</hi>'s ſide, and knew his: Therefore pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:152282:112"/>Reverence to them both (for that they were continually together, and gave mutual Reſpect) they alſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended on them both, and honoured them equally alike. And one of 'em ſaid to theſe Noble Knights, I am <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> who brought you ſuch a way, and ſaid, and did ſo and ſo. And the other ſaid, in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the ſame thing, and how he did it. So they both made every one marvel; and it was referred to <hi>Helena</hi> to determine which was the true <hi>Olivaires.</hi> And they ſtaied ſome Days in that City for the making of Feaſts and Triumphs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing detained of the People, to expreſs their Joyfulneſs for having regained their Sovereign. They diſpatched Meſſengers up and down with the News, ſo Feaſtings were every where prepared; and as they paſſed from City to City, all honoured their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign; and every one took a great pleaſure in ſaying, For one Sovereign which we have loſt, we have gained two. And the Fame hereof had got
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:152282:113"/>to Court; and it was ſo confidently affirmed, that many Lords went ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Days Journey to meet them out of curioſity of ſeeing ſuch a Rarity; and were ſtill more eager of it, for that 't was ſaid, they were equals, and alike in Turnament, at Juſting, at mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Horſes, at Arms, at Dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in Age, Size, Speech, Tone; and that to pleaſe their Fancy they dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alike, and wore the ſame Habit; and loved ſo intirely, that they ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one Soul animating two Bodies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>and</hi> Arthur <hi>arrive at the Court, and are equally received of the King, and of</hi> Helena; <hi>and how</hi> Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires <hi>is known; and</hi> Helena <hi>well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfies her ſelf by ſeeing the Moles on his Arm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEING arrived at <hi>London,</hi> they were received of the King and <hi>Helena</hi> with unſpeakable Joy; and
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:152282:113"/>they were amaz'd, not knowing which to take for <hi>Olivaires.</hi> But <hi>Arthur</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed the Secret: And <hi>Helena</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Moles, which ſhe had ſeen before, embraced him, and printed a Kiſs on his Lips. And, after having reſted a while, <hi>Arthur</hi> began to relate all that had happened; and <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> to tell what Miſery he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone. And as they made relation of one thing after another, from greater to leſs, they cauſed the King's Heart-ſtrings to tremble, and his Pulſe beat in great diſorder; and his main Vexation was (for the preſent) that he could not take revenge of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable Injuriouſneſs, for that <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> had pardoned the King of <hi>Ireland.</hi> But lo! juſt now Couriers come over, who bring Letters, that give <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> Intelligence how the King had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled. <hi>Arthur</hi> was glad to hear o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch Inſolence, ſince it would give him occaſion to revenge the old as well as this new Affront. He having Courage and Ability enough, with
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:152282:114"/>the help only of his Lion, to lay waſt a thouſand Realms, much more <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> alone. The King having heard of the Proweſs of <hi>Arthur,</hi> and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teague he had undergone, gave order for his being Honoured and Attended on as his own Perſon. And he was preſented by <hi>Helena</hi> with rich Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and precious Stones; and by the King with a large ſum of Gold; and he remained in the Court loved and reſpected of all; and every Day they Juſted, Feaſted, and went to the Chace. And <hi>Olivaires</hi> remembring the Day on which he was taken, ſaid to <hi>Arthur,</hi> It ſeems to me to be full time that your ungrateful King ſhould be made know his Error; wherefore let us go and reduce the revolted Realm. No, ſaid <hi>Arthur,</hi> Let that alone to me, and remain in your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for you have been enough in <hi>Ireland.</hi> And being returned from the Chace, they ordered a vaſt Army to be made ready; and then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan their March for <hi>Ireland.</hi> The
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:152282:114"/>King having made him his General, gave him his Bleſſing; and ſo he took his leave. <hi>Arthur</hi> having got into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the King Intelligence of his arrival, he goes againſt him with his Army to give him Battel; and he ſent a Trumpet to him to put him in mind, (thinking it was <hi>Olivaires</hi>) that his old Priſon waited for him, and to tell him he hoped to take him. <hi>Arthur</hi> laughed, and ſaid; Go and tell your King that 't would be too great an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for him to make my Lion devour him; but that I will give him for Food to the Crows, and other Fowls of the Air. And, diſperſing his Army, he burnt, ruinated and ſlew every where; and without all pity and compaſſion deſtroy'd and laid waſt the whole Countrey; ſo inraged was he at the King's Inſolence. And he ſoon arriv'd to where the King had poſted himſelf; who hearing of his exorbitant Fury, fled into a ſtrong City, nor would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him at his Campaign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="chapter">
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:152282:115"/>
               <head>CHAP. LXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Aſſault that</hi> Arthur <hi>gave to the City, and took it; in which Battery the King dies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN the Evening <hi>Arthur</hi> put his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in order, made his Squadrons, and placed them in their firſt, ſecond, and third ranks, to give aſſault to the Gates, and ſent to the Walls thoſe who ſhould ſcale them; and he gave them fierce battel, when night came on, with the one part, and at midnight be cauſed the other to make an Aſſault; and early in the morning with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, who had taken repoſe, he did great execution; whence thoſe within were overcome through want of ſleep, and wearineſs; then <hi>Arthur</hi> divided all his Camp into three places, and begun a ſharp Fight; and burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ope a Gate, he enter'd in with Lance upon his Thigh; and thoſe who came upon him he run thorough, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:152282:115"/>their Armour as if it had been of Wax; and his Lion enter'd into the Battel, and made in the City that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock and Maſſacre among the Men, as if they had been Herds of Cattle: They remembred <hi>Arthur:</hi> And the King ſeeing him, would have made reſiſtance, but <hi>Arthur</hi> kill'd him; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the People were all terrify'd, diſpers'd, and fled away. Some threw themſelves down to the ground from tops of Houſes, rather than they would fall into the hands of the Enemy; and others drowned themſelves in Pools: So he cours'd about the City as his own; and conſtituted Governors of, and put a Gariſon in the place, a part of his own Army; and with the reſt he returned victoriouſly to <hi>London,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving placed Gariſons where ever elſe was thought needful to keep the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in ſubjection to the Crown of his great Majeſty of <hi>England.</hi> The King of <hi>England</hi> having underſtanding of the Victory, cauſed univerſal Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to be made; and when he came,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:152282:116"/>
                  <hi>Olivaires</hi> went with great triumph and exultation to meet him; and the King gave him many Careſſes, freely beſtowing on him all he had got. So the two Brothers continued together, every day feaſting, making merry, Hunting, Juſting, and diverting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with other noble Exerciſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of an Infirmity which hapned to</hi> Arthur; <hi>and how by ſome Dreams they ſee the remedy for his Cure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMong theſe Sweets, Fortune muſt needs be mixing her Bitters; and ſo ſevere ſhe was, as to bring upon <hi>Arthur</hi> an incurable Diſeaſe; and 'twas after this ſort. <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Body was all corrupted within, whence proceeded out of all parts of it an infinity of Vermin; and they would certainly have devoured him, but that he ever haſtened to kill them: Not a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:152282:116"/>but diſguſted the ſight, nor a Servant that could indure the ſtench. He had half loſt the ſight of his Eyes, and his Speech falter'd, and he was become a perfect Skeleton: Yet his Body was inwardly ſwell'd, all the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments of his Joints were diſſolved and lax, like a Paralitick; he could not raiſe his Head from his Pillow, nor turn him in his Bed; whatever he eat gave him no nouriſhment; and in a word, ſo ſtrange was his Malady, that the Doctors could not find any remedy for it. None but <hi>Olivaires</hi> had courage to look on him, and he continually attended him: And when <hi>Arthur</hi> wiſh'd and begg'd for death a thouſand times in an hour, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him, and pray'd him to bear his condition patiently; telling him, He did not think it the leaſt trouble to wait on him, but did it freely, and with great ſatisfaction. One night <hi>Arthur</hi> dream'd he ſaw <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Daughter breathe a Vein; and that, ſhe ſprinkling ſome of the Blood iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:152282:117"/>from it on his Viſage, and giving him more to drink, he was cured by the virtue of it. Whereupon he waken'd for joy; but then finding it only a Dream, he ſaid nothing of it to <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatres:</hi> The Virgin was of competent ſtature, and ſhe alſo dream'd the ſame night ſhe ſaw <hi>Arthur</hi> drinking of Blood out of a Bowl, and to be cur'd thereby; and ſhe told it to her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Olivaires</hi> one morning 'bout break of day ſee in a Dream a Lady drawing blood out of her Vein, and with it bathing <hi>Arthur,</hi> and alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him of it to drink, and that he was cur'd thereby: The ſight whereof wonderfully rejovc'd him; and the ſame morning told the Viſion to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur. Helena</hi> from her Soul loving <hi>Arthur,</hi> as if he had been her own Brother, declareed alſo her Daughters Dream. <hi>Arthur,</hi> though ſecretly, had made his Viſion known to the Doctor, who did aſſure him that Blood was his only remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="chapter">
               <pb n="223" facs="tcp:152282:117"/>
               <head>CHAP. LXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Conſult of the King,</hi> Olivaires, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena, <hi>and the Phyſicians, upon</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur<hi>'s Infirmity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen the King heard of every one's Dream, he knew for certain that <hi>Clariſa</hi>'s Blood was to be the Medicine whereby <hi>Arthur</hi> muſt have relief. On the one hand he was dubious, on the other he was reſolv'd; and having called <hi>Olivaires, Helena,</hi> and the Phyſicians, deſirous he ſhould recover, he enquired of them which was the moſt facil way to perform the Operation. On the one part <hi>Olivaires</hi> conſented to the doing of it, for that he was his Brother; but was afflicted on the other, fearing it might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger his Daughter's Life. <hi>Helena</hi> lamented the miſhap. <hi>Arthur</hi> would rather have dy'd, than any hand ſhould ſpill the leaſt drop of his Neece's Blood; the Phyſicians knew not any way to take Blood from her without great hazard, and fear of harm to the
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:152282:118"/>Damſel: The King was ſorry he could not ſhed his own to ſerve him. <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> likewiſe would freely have bled; and <hi>Helena</hi> was troubled ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly. Under theſe Difficulties his Royal Friends labour'd a whole day, and earneſtly recommended with Prayers themſelves, and their Caſe, unto God: At night, when <hi>Helena</hi> was about going to bed, ſhe with all humility kneel'd down on the Floor, and with a moſt ſincere heart made her application unto God, begging of him to inſtruct them how, without danger, or pain, to extract Blood from her young Daughter, inaſmuch as they were reſolved to free him of his Diſeaſe by that Remedy: Lo in the night a Lady arrayed all in pure white Silk, with a Crown of Gold upon her head, appear'd to the Royal Damſel, and with ſaying things that delighted her, and with winning Smiles and ſweetneſs, made gentle application, and lanced a vein of her right arm, and having ſaved the blood in a baſon
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:152282:118"/>of Alabaſter, and healed the little ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſaid to her, you ſhall give this to <hi>Arthur</hi> to drink, and bathe alſo his Face with it. In the morning the thing being underſtood, the King and they all render'd thanks unto God, and publiſhed the Miracle, and Solemn Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was appointed. The Damſel in the morning, accompanied of her Mother, and alſo her Father, with all the Ladies, went unto <hi>Arthur,</hi> and bathed him with that ſame blood, and gave him thereof to drink, whereby in a moment he was ſeen to admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to recover, and in a ſhort time was perfectly cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After the reſtoring of</hi> Arthur <hi>to his health, Cavaliers came out of</hi> Spain <hi>to compliment</hi> Olivaires <hi>as their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen <hi>Arthur</hi> was well again, the rejoicing was no leſs than if he had ſtrictly riſen from the dead,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:152282:119"/>and the world kept a Jubilee; his Subjects of <hi>Ireland</hi> came to compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him upon, and with great joy congratulate his recovery. The ſame time alſo many Embaſſadors arrived from the Kingdom of <hi>Spain,</hi> to make demonſtration of their mighty glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for having found again their King, but withal expreſſing ſorrow for the Queen's death, ſo that there was a neceſſity of declarations of ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for <hi>Arthur</hi>'s ſake; but when the Court was out of mourning, there came many Dukes, Lords and Knights, and begged of their Sovereign, King <hi>Olivaires,</hi> that he would be pleaſed to make happy with his preſence his own Dominions; wherefore they all ſupplicated the King of <hi>England</hi> to give conſent that <hi>Olivaires, Helena,</hi> and <hi>Arthur,</hi> might go for ſome days to their Realm. The King was pleaſed, and proffer'd to accompany them alſo himſelf; and having order'd the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, Attendance, Treaſure, and all other things to be in readineſs, they
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:152282:119"/>took their progreſs for <hi>Spain.</hi> He who could relate the number of the Guards thoſe three Kings had, the Pages, Knights, and infinite Train that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them, and alſo the Ladies, would be able to make the moſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Narrative that was ever heard. Only the Queen and her Daughter had two Courts of Knights and Ladies that equall'd the Stars of Heaven both for their number and their brightneſs. <hi>Caſtile</hi> having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the coming of ſo belov'd a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, and of his People ſo much deſired, made great Jubilee and Exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and the more, for that they underſtood they had for their Queen the Daughter of <hi>England;</hi> and that ſhe had alſo a Son and Daughter. The Feaſts, the Pomps, the Rejoicings, the Triumphs, the Juſtings and Turna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were infinite; every where as they paſſed were ſuch great Feaſts and Entertainments made for them, as was poſſible to be prepared among ſuch hurry of joy and rapture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="chapter">
               <pb n="228" facs="tcp:152282:120"/>
               <head>CHAP. LXVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Olivaires <hi>and</hi> Helena <hi>having enter'd</hi> Caſtile, <hi>are crowned.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THeſe potent Princes were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in <hi>Caſtile</hi> with Pomp and Expences ineſtimable; and the third day, according as was before ordered, <hi>Olivaires</hi> and <hi>Helena</hi> were crowned King and Queen of that Kingdom. <hi>Olivaires</hi> was obliged to ſtay for ſome time in his Dominion, and <hi>Arthur</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to go to his of <hi>Dalgarve;</hi> ſo the King of <hi>England</hi> was to return alone, which was ſomething melancholy to him, eſpecially he leaving alſo behind his Daughter. He returned then for <hi>England,</hi> however accompanied a good part of his way by many Dukes, Counts, Lords and Knights, and ſome went thorow with him into <hi>England.</hi> After that, <hi>Arthur</hi> being gone to his Kingdom to redreſs and put in order what ever he found amiſs; <hi>Olivaires</hi>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:152282:120"/>likewiſe gave great diligence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his State, to reward his Subjects, and careſs all; and for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Kingdom, and to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his great affection to King <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garve,</hi> he determin'd to make Alliance with him, and that ſo ſtrict, as the knot might be Gordian and indiſſolvable; ſo he and the Queen reſolved to give him their Daughter <hi>Clariſſia</hi> to Wife; the only ſeeming Obſtacle was, that her years did not well ſuit his. In that pleaſing thought then, and in other honourable Affairs and Diverſions paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the time, at length one morning <hi>Olivaires</hi> and <hi>Helena</hi> in their Chamber, having bolted the door too, begun to take a view of all the Treaſure that they had brought, and alſo that which they had found in the Kingdom; ſo having laid the Jewels to one ſide, and the Gold to another; and having put the Veſtments of great value that way, and the to-be-admired heaps of Silver this: upon this they heard a violent thumping at the door, which on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:152282:121"/>unbarr'd it, and made it fly open; and the White Knight who gave <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> the Victory at the Turnament, and who had delivered him out of ſo many troubles and diſtreſſes, appear'd in the middle of the Room in the twinkling of an eye; <hi>Helena</hi> knew it to be him of whom ſhe had received the Ring; wherefore <hi>Olivaires</hi> and ſhe moſt joyfully welcom'd him, and ran to embrace him, who then ſpoke in this manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Diſcourſe of the White Cavalier; and what</hi> Olivaires <hi>and</hi> Helena <hi>did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>MOST Invincible King <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> and you moſt Sacred Queen, I am come for that which upon your Royal Word you promiſed me, that is, the full half of all your Gains through my aid and aſſiſtance; and I came now, becauſe you are going to
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:152282:121"/>gather together all your ſeparated Treaſures. <hi>Olivaires</hi> made anſwer, It was but juſt, and very reaſonable it ſhould be ſo: Wherefore taking Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets of precious Stones, Veſſels of Gold, Silver, Raiment, he ſaid; I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to have had this Treaſure from you; lo! divide it as you pleaſe, for your Deſerts challenge as much. The Cavalier ſetting ſome things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, ſaid, Of theſe I ſhall deſire no more; but of your remaining Acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition I muſt. <hi>Olivaires</hi> anſwered, And what further is your pleaſure, dear Sir? To have one of your Children, anſwered he; for to me appertains the half of whatever you have got. Ah me! ſaid <hi>Helena,</hi> Take all the Treaſure before you for reward, and leave me my Son. I ſhall not do it, ſubjoined the Knight. Then ſaid <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires,</hi> I put ſo much confidence in this honourable Perſonage, that my Son ſhall be his; for he is able better to educate and gratify him than I could do, though his own Father. I
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:152282:122"/>do not know what I ſhall do, ſaid the Cavalier; but let him come, for he is mine. <hi>Olivaires,</hi> though his Heart ſwelled as was fit to break, for having promiſed, yet would not he recede from his Duty; and cauſing his <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to come, he took him by the Hand, and gave him as a Booty to the Cavalier. When <hi>Helena</hi> beheld her ſelf robbed of her Son, ſhe ſet up a loud Cry, and a violent and extream Lamentation. Then the Cavalier tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> ſaid, I who have ſo faithfully ſerved you, have inriched you, and ſaved your life; Am I for this ſo diſcourteouſly rewarded with the ſhare, that according to compact belongs unto me? But now go, for I further require, and will alſo have, either for Love or by Force, the half of the Queen; and quickly take thy Sword and divide her, and give me my Right; for I ſhall demand of thee no other than juſt and reaſonable Things; otherwiſe thou ſhalt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience my Strength and Valour,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:152282:122"/>and what Ability and Proweſs I can exert.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Intreaties of</hi> Olivaires; <hi>and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the White Cavalier gives him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE big Words of the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier created mighty dread in the Breaſt of <hi>Olivaires;</hi> and <hi>Helena</hi> was ready to fall down in a ſwoon for Grief about her Son; and greatly trembled alſo by reaſon of his threats, for fear of Death. Wherefore <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> turning to the Knight, ſaid, Dear Sir, It is true that I promiſed you the half of my Acquiſts, but not ſo of what I ſhould Procreate: However, for that I know you faithful, I have not replied one word for the having my Son again. But ſhe whom the God of Heaven hath ordained for my Wife, and hath joyned us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Ought ſhe to be divided from
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:152282:123"/>me, and her ſelf too, with the Sword? Is it not written, <hi>Whom God hath join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, let not man put aſunder?</hi> I tell thee, <hi>Olivaires,</hi> thou oughteſt not to diminiſh my ſhare: For had not I made thee Conqueror, by furniſhing thee with Horſes, Men and Arms, thou hadſt never got the Lady. I will have it ſo, and make no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that I turn not thy happy ſtate into a ſad one; quickly give me half. <hi>Olivaires</hi> ſeeing his reſolvedneſs, turn'd to <hi>Helena,</hi> and ſaid; Alas! my dear Life, how ſhall I be able to ſuſtain ſuch a ſorrow? how ſhall I wound her who is my very heart? why hath Fortune brought me to this Dilemma? On the other part, <hi>Helena,</hi> as if beſides her ſelf, remain'd half dead, nor heard <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s words; and ſhe run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all the ſad Accidents had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd in her life-time, and with dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous complaint gave moſt hideous ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings: Set me at liberty quickly, ſaid the Cavalier, and detain me not in this place: You ſhould have conſidered of
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:152282:123"/>it before you promiſed, and not now ſeek delays to augment your ſorrow; you give me nothing but what is my own. <hi>Olivaires</hi> embracing and kiſſing his Lady nigh dead already, purpoſing to obſerve his Word, of a ſudden draws forth his Sword, and raiſes high his Arm for a terrible cleaving ſtroke over the Head of the fair and divine <hi>Helena,</hi> the ſplendor of the World, that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood, and pure Soul: But the Cavalier haſtily held his Arm, and cry'd out, I have enough of thee, my deareſt Brother, no more, I am ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd; and would not indure he ſhould ſlay the Flower and Queen of all Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World: At which awful Cry <hi>Helena</hi> look'd up, as from a Trance, and ſeeing the Cavalier careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Olivaires,</hi> ſhe took comfort: What followed you ſhall hear in ſhort, and the Concluſion, according to Ancient Hiſtories.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="chapter">
               <pb n="236" facs="tcp:152282:124"/>
               <head>CHAP. LXXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Gift the Cavalier gave</hi> Olivaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>YOU have given me however, happy Couple, your Son, and your Treaſure; lo, I reſtore you him again: For over-inſupportable are the dolours which are felt for Children, and the nine months grievings of a Mother, while ſhe bears her Infant in the Womb. I very well know what powerful influence Fidelity has on thy breaſt, ſince thou haſt not ſhunn'd to wound thy Soul, to maintain thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Promiſe. O <hi>Olivaires,</hi> the Deity proſper thee, the Deity bleſs thee, the Deity increaſe thy State, thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and propagate thy Seed eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Surely thou art worthy of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Empire, thou art full of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all noble indowments of mind do appear, and are reſplendant in all thy Actions. <hi>Olivaires</hi> taking aſſurance by reaſon of the Gift re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:152282:124"/>and <hi>Helena</hi> having recover'd her fainting Spirits, ſeeing her Son before her face return'd to her deſire, they undertook to demand of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, that of love he would be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to manifeſt himſelf unto them: And by that Power that created the Heavens and the Earth, they begged of him, he would permit them to know to whom they were ſo ſtrangely obliged. O <hi>Olivaires,</hi> I am that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>John Talbot,</hi> I am that Cavalier whom thou didſt conduct to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country; that Gentleman I am, whom being excommunicated for a large Debt, thou didſt at thy own Expences, diſcharging the Sum, cauſe to be re-bleſſed, and have Chriſtian bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial. God, for ſuch Charity, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love, and thy goodneſs, did command me to do ſuch kindneſſes for the Poſſeſſor of ſo honeſt an heart. He delivered thee in all thy Diſtreſſes; he at length hath tried, and fully known that precious Soul which he has given thee: That Elemoſinary
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:152282:125"/>Pity which thou ſhew'd unto me, ſhall alſo prepare thee a Manſion in the Heavens. My giving the Black Habit, ſignify'd my being in the ſtate of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; the Red Livery intimated the ardent Fire of Purgatory, which hath purged away my ſins; the White Veſtment manifeſted the Celeſtial Country which was opened unto me. I ſerved thee therefore with Arms, Horſes, and Men; I directed <hi>Arthur</hi> to the place, and made him take thee out of Priſon: At that inſtant I ſeized the City; I gave the Lion for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to <hi>Arthur,</hi> who killed the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and who fought like an Army in the Campaign. I healed his Wound, I gave the Ring of the King thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Helena,</hi> and I begged of the Lady to act with hers for giving thee her to Wife: Therefore thou haſt had every thing through me; but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all from God as the Author; And let each of you render infinite thanks unto him, who hath delivered you out of ſo great Afflictions, and
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:152282:125"/>who for the future will fill your hearts with joy and gladneſs. All theſe words ſpoke the Cavalier; and at laſt being ſurrounded with a Divine Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, ſaid, Peace be with you, fare you well; for I mount to Eternal Life; and vaniſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King and Queen pay their gratitude unto God; and of the coming of the King of</hi> Dalgarve, <hi>with the Eſpouſals of</hi> Clariſia.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE King and Queen rendered infinite thanks to Almighty God, ever amazed and admiring at ſo ſtrange a matter, and terrible Accident as had befall'n them; and they order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that a ſolemn Thankſgiving ſhould be made throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> having in this time ſetled his Realm of <hi>Dalgarve,</hi> went to the
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:152282:126"/>Court of <hi>Olivaires,</hi> his Brother-in-Law, where he could never enough ſatisfy himſelf with looking on <hi>Clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> both for her Beauty and Behaviour; and in conſideration that it was her Blood out of her own Veins that had cur'd him, for which he every day gave thanks unto God. One day <hi>Olivaires</hi> call'd to him, and ſaid, My Brother, who art ever in my heart, and who haſt done ſo much for me, I much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that you ſhould marry, if you fancy ſuch a ſtate. I like your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Propoſal very well, reply'd <hi>Arthur;</hi> but whom may you beſtow upon me? whom might it be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that you ſhould give me? my <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſia,</hi> who hath ſaved your life; ſhe ſhall be your right Eye, your Soul, and dear Companion; for by your good deeds and carriages towards me, you have deſerved her. And as they were deſigning to make this Alliance, four Lords came poſt from <hi>England</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> that the King had been ſeiz'd with an Apoplexy, whereof
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:152282:126"/>he died in a day's time; which news made a melancholy Court, and they all went into mourning: The Funeral was ordered, and the ſolemn Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies duly performed. After ſome time the Nuptials of <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Clariſia</hi> were concluded on, and all things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and fitted for the celebration; and <hi>Arthur</hi> was crowned King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by <hi>Olivaires:</hi> The report where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſpread ſuddenly all over the Realm. Whereupon Counts, Knights, and Barons came to the Feaſts, and Juſts, and all the Cities ſent to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation; then after a convenient time's ſtay, <hi>Arthur</hi> went to <hi>England,</hi> and gave the Government of <hi>Dalgarve</hi> to his Natural Son, and conſtituted him Vice-roy, a perſon of a gentle, virtuous, valiant, and admirable Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="chapter">
               <pb n="242" facs="tcp:152282:127"/>
               <head>CHAP. LXXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur <hi>King of</hi> England <hi>goes to</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>and</hi> Henry <hi>is made Commander of an Army againſt the Infidels.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HE who would have taken a true eſtimate of the love between <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> and <hi>Arthur,</hi> ſhould have been preſent to ſee their parting when he went from <hi>Spain.</hi> For I believe his heart was well nigh burſt with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; and <hi>Helena</hi> ſeeing her Daughter go away, was fill'd with extream grief; at laſt they took leave, and departed with a great, comely, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Train. A few days after, an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy from the King of <hi>Cyprus</hi> arrived to <hi>Olivaires</hi> to demand Aid of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Enemies of the Catholick Faith; and <hi>Olivaires</hi> deſigned to go ſuddenly himſelf in perſon for ſuch an Enterprize: But his young Son <hi>Henry</hi> hearing of it, begged of his Father to leave the conduct and management of
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:152282:127"/>his Forces to him, for that he deſired to get a name, and honourable repute among famous Cavaliers; which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, though with difficulty, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Having made him then Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Royal, he gave him Twenty five thouſand well armed Men: and when he had put them all in right order, and had made ready their Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all things neceſſary for the War, and their March, he departed for <hi>Cyprus:</hi> 'Twas a grand affliction to <hi>Helena</hi> to ſee her ſelf deprived of both her Children at once: At his going away, a great number of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers accompanied him, and ſome went with him to <hi>Cyprus;</hi> others join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him in battel, and aſſiſted him. When Prince <hi>Henry</hi> was arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Kingdom of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> he uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his with the other Army, and with mighty fury fell on the Enemy, and got a glorious Victory. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all following and adhering to him as a prudent and valorous Prince, he reſolved to give them a total rout, and
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:152282:128"/>deſtroy them all, and take many Countries before he made his return into <hi>Spain.</hi> The news of this his ſo ſucceſsful firſt Attempt was brought to <hi>Olivaires</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ena,</hi> which won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully pleaſed them, and rejoyced the whole Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arthur<hi>'s Entry into</hi> England; <hi>and of the Feaſts, Triumphs, and other Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings made for the Nuptials; and of a Rebellion of the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHEN King <hi>Arthur</hi> made his Entry into <hi>England,</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Lances, and a thouſand Men on Horſeback all clad in Silk, came to meet him. Cavaliers, Counts, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes, and an infinite number of Knights and Gentlemen received and attended on him with his Conſort <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſia;</hi> and they admired her for being the Daughter of ſo beautiful a Lady,
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:152282:128"/>the Daughter of one of their Kings; and fancied they had got <hi>Helena</hi> again, ſo much ſhe reſembled her: Thither to the Nuptials, was concourſe of all the moſt valiant Knights that were in the whole Kingdom, and infinite Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Juſting they made; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days the Court was abroad. After that, <hi>Arthur</hi> was publickly inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; and with the aſſiſtance of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Counſellors he put in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his whole ſtate, and diſpoſed every thing for the beſt; it pleaſed God that <hi>Clariſia</hi> conceived, and at the due time brought forth a lovely Boy, and they gave him the name of the late King of <hi>England.</hi> Now the fame of this Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Heir of the Kingdom beginning to ſpread wide, certain Princes were moved with envy at his great Felicity; and inviting the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings to their aſſiſtance, they cauſed a part of the State to riſe in rebellion. Wherefore <hi>Arthur</hi> was forced upon a new Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who thought he enjoy'd the Kingdom in perfect peace. Fitting
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:152282:129"/>then as many Forces as he judged ſufficient to repreſs the inſolence of his Subjects, he went on the Deſign. The Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> headed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; for being Couſin to the old King, he imagin'd he had ſo ſome Title to the Crown. <hi>Arthur</hi> engaging Battel with him, in few days ſpace deſtroyed the whole Army; and taking the Duke Priſoner, he would have ſlain him; but he begging of him for the Lineage ſake of which he was deſcended, he gave him his Life, and ſet him at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and he renounced all his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to the Realm of <hi>England;</hi> but within a few days died of grief. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> returning, after lived in peace and quietneſs; and was bleſſed with a Daughter, who prov'd an occaſion of an Illuſtrious Alliance, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Tranquillity of the State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="chapter">
               <pb n="247" facs="tcp:152282:129"/>
               <head>CHAP. LXXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Alliance</hi> Arthur <hi>made with his Daughter by the Counſel of</hi> Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, <hi>and of his Son</hi> Henry.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> having underſtood of <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Journey, proffered him ſupply of Men and Horſes; but <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> had no need of any. Hearing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward of his Victory, he made great Rejoicing: And having knowledge of the Nativity of his Daughter, he writ to him to ſeek to contract Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with ſome potent Prince, that his State might not be in fear of War, or Rebellion any more. Wherefore calling together his Council, he read to them <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Letter; who all approved of his Advice, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to make trial on the King of <hi>Portugal.</hi> And when ſome Months had paſſed, Ambaſſadors were ſent to treat of the Match; and it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Daughter ſhould
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:152282:130"/>be given to the King of <hi>Portugal</hi>'s El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son, who was a few Years elder than her; and the Dowry was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Determining. Now <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Son being dead, who governed for him the State of <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garve, Olivaires</hi> Arbitrated that the Kingdom of <hi>Dalgarve</hi> ſhould be given in Dowry to the King of <hi>Portugal:</hi> Wherefore that State hath ever ſince continued under the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Crown. <hi>Arthur</hi> was much troubled for the loſs of his Son; but bore it the better, for that his Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Daughter ſucceeded him. So in fit time, according as Hiſtories write, ſhe went to her Husband. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi>'s Son growing up, imitated his Father's Valour and all his Vertues; which gave mighty Content and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to <hi>Olivaires</hi> alſo, who was continually inquiring after him. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Olivaires</hi>'s Son, gave alſo conſent to this Alliance, to whom Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were ordered, who found him in his Camp before a ſtrongly fortified
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:152282:130"/>City; and he had already conquered and taken many; and he kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them; and they returned ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. <hi>Arthur</hi> underſtanding the great Soul and Proweſs of <hi>Henry,</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely delighted; and did by Letters much Congratulate, on his account, his Brother <hi>Olivaires;</hi> who lived in great Pleaſure by continual hearing of his Son's brave and honourable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXXVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of an infirmity happening to</hi> Olivaires; <hi>and of</hi> Henry <hi>who was aſſaulted, and almoſt ſlain, whom</hi> Arthur <hi>goes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>OLivaires</hi> by reaſon of uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Harraſſings and Fatigues in his Youth, and alſo his ſo many Months Impriſonment in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Age became more ſenſible of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore better ſupported Miſhaps and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:152282:131"/>and their ſculking Effects, and waiting an Advantage, proved over-match for his infirm Years, and ſo he muſt truckle under their ſevere Preſſure. His Stomach then is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo infeebled, that nothing that he eats will Digeſt with him; and he is tormented with continual and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable pain in his Head; and unto his Malady, and to increaſe his Grief, an unlucky Accident was added; which was, That his Son <hi>Henry</hi> puſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward with ſome Cavaliers, more couragiouſly than their Strength and Ability to come off well could ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, was thruſt into the throng and main of his Enemies; from whence it was impoſſible, without great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and hazard, to ſave himſelf, and get back to his Army again; ſo that, as was thought, he was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Wounded. When <hi>Olivaires</hi> heard this ill News, he writ to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> to deſire him to go and relieve his Nephew; who did not ſtand to make much Preparation, but with a
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:152282:131"/>Choice and Valiant Detachment march'd away. This gave ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> reckoning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was there in Perſon if <hi>Arthur</hi> were. When <hi>Arthur</hi> arrived, he found <hi>Henry</hi> very bad; however he gave notice to <hi>Olivaires,</hi> that it was much better with him; and taking extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary care of him, he in a few days ſee him well again. In the mean time the Enemy-Army felt the Forces of <hi>Arthur,</hi> who oft vigorouſly aſſaulted them, and with a vaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction made Mountains of the ſlain. When <hi>Henry</hi> was recovered, <hi>Arthur</hi> returned and went ſpeedily to give his <hi>Olivaires</hi> a Viſit, who was much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with his infirmity. <hi>Helena</hi> was mightily overjoy'd at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and ſhe perceived that <hi>Arthur</hi>'s preſence did ſomewhat recruit <hi>Olivai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Arthur</hi> diſcourſed to him the whole Matter concerning <hi>Henry;</hi> ſpoke of the Beauty of his Daughter, and by degrees gave him an account of his Son, how as he grew up he
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:152282:132"/>imitated <hi>Olivaires</hi> in all Noble and Virtuous Indowments of Mind. And having reſted for ſome Days, with his honourable Cavaliers, he return'd into <hi>England</hi> to enjoy his Rich and Beautiful State and Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXXVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is Recorded by</hi> Engliſh <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> Spaniſh, <hi>and others, concerning theſe Kings.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> conquered many and many Countries, and at laſt died Fighting for Holy Mother Church; a true doubly Militant Son and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof. The ſame foreſaid infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, after a long Life, brought <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaires</hi> to his Grave: When he died <hi>Helena</hi> took on ſo ſadly, that ſhe alſo Expired on <hi>Olivaires</hi>'s Face; and they were both Buried together. <hi>Arthur</hi> was Crowned King of <hi>Caſtile;</hi> and his Son Married, and had Children;
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:152282:132"/>and ſo likewiſe had his Daughter: So for many Years flouriſhed the Fame of all theſe mighty Kings. But the Heavens, which give an end to every thing, not to the Grandees only, but to us who have writ this preſent Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and alſo ſhall to all the Readers thereof, bring our deſtined Periods about, that after the Fatigue of a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Pilgrimage we may find ſome Quietude; and that leaving behind them for a time, but not long, the (yet) mortal Garments Nature ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated them with, our Spirits may return into the Hands of the Lord who gave them, of him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Good or Evil, Rewards or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, according as we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and behaved our ſelves. Let us therefore make humble requeſt unto the Almighty, with ſincere and cordial Affections, that he would pleaſe to look on his Mercy, not our Merit, his Grace, not our Works; and that for thoſe he would bring us unto, and make us Partakers of his
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:152282:133"/>Kingdom, that which is not Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, that which no Tyrant, how po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſoever, can uſurp or moleſt; that wherein no Vice dwells, which none can enter or approach, wherein no wicked Perſons have ſhare, place or reſidence, which they may not (unleſs to increaſe their Torment) behold; but where have their Source and Origin, where for ever are Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, where for evermore Inhabit, are Secure and Eſtabliſhed, Goodneſs, Vertue, Wiſdom, Peace and Felicity, through him who is all theſe Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preamly and Eſſentially: And that he would beſtow theſe alſo upon us whilſt in this World; to the end, that waſhed and purified from the pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sin, we may joyfully go hence to enjoy, revere and adore Him, and Face to Face eternally gaze on the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atifick Viſion. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152282:133"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
